Hello everyone.
Thanks for coming to this talk.
My name is Wayne Johnson.
and today I want to talk
a little bit about audio.
Sorry and today I want to
talk a little bit about audio,
and how to build audio concepts in Unity.
To begin with,
I wanna talk a little bit about me.
I grew up in Australia.
I studied engineering and science at university.
And before I started at
Unity, I worked at FMod,
which is an audio middleware company some of you might know.
And then I packed up and moved
to Denmark and started at Unity.
I work in the core team and
specifically on audio.
Something about me: I can eat 12
McDonald's cheeseburgers in one go.
And I also enjoy diving and cave diving.
So today I want to talk about a couple of
things that you can do in Unity,
and some audio concepts that you want to
kind of follow to make really good audio within Unity.
So I want to talk about ambiances.
So environmental sounds and stuff like that.
I want to talk about interactive sounds.
Sounds that change with the game logic,
so coming from other subsystems,
for example Mecanim or other scripts.
I want to talk about interactive music--which
is my favorite topic. I'll tell you why later.
Then if we have time,
I wanna do some questions.
So let's talk about ambiances.
So ambiances are, as I said,
environmental sounds and sounds that
don't take any input from sort of game logic.
They just sit in the world
and do their thing.
And they're really powerful, because you can actually
pretend a lot is happening within the game.
Without actually having any models or any other sort
of particle effects or anything, you can just pretend,
for example, that the forest you're in is full of birds
and other creatures just with ambiances.
Ambiances usually contain a
number of variations or grains.
These sound clips, that are small and
are usually of the same theme, for example,
they're all of the same type of sound.
They're usually placed in the world by the designer.
So for example, dropping bird sounds in a forest,
or they can be done automatically by
script code, which is also very powerful
if you have a really large level.
They usually have no input logic
from the game, as I said.
And they're usually long playing sounds.
They can play, you know, during the
whole level or maybe the whole game.
So they have to be something
that the player can listen to
for an extended period of time
without getting sick of it.
They're usually subtle sounds.
You know, this is so that they don't
get too annoying for the player.
So some examples, just quickly.
Forest noises, you know, bird chirps.
Insects.
Leaves. You know, things like that.
Wind sounds.
But also things like urban things,traffic noises
and just crowds. That's very powerful, to just have ambient
crowd noises if you're in some cityscape.
So, how do ambiances work?
Ambiances are usually made up
by some sort of script code.
So you want to create your ambiance logic,
which is sort of driving your ambient sound,
in some sort of script object.
You know, packed into a game object.
You want to assign some variations or raw samples
to that logic--which we'll get to later.
Those two things combined
make some really powerful ambient sounds and
I'll explain how powerful they can be later.
So there's a couple things with ambiances.
As I said, there's your variations and your logic,
which generally comes down to property randomization.
So for example, randomizing volume,
pitch, spawn rate, spawn location,
these sort of things can keep the sounds that you're
playing unique and fresh all the time.
Variations or different grains are generally
preferred, but you know obviously they're kind of
limited by the memory you have. So I mean if you
had a million variations that would be great,
but you know, it's completely infeasible for any game.
And randomization, or the logic itself to keep
the sounds fresh, has no effect on performance.
There's no sort of performance hit for changing the pitch
or volume of a sound as it's being played.
So this is kinda preferred for limited platforms
like mobile, Android, iOS, stuff like that.
And all this comes together, and you can
create some really powerful sounds
with as many as five short samples.
Which is pretty amazing.
They're always continuously fresh and unique.
So an overview of how you would do this.
Generally you would select a random location
to play the grain.
This is the sort of the basic logic that you would do:
You would select a random volume
within some range,
half volume to full volume,
a random pitch again within a range,
then you would play the sound.
And then what you do is, you would repeat
this process at random intervals
between, say, half a second and one second. Or
if you want this soundscape to be quite full,
you would do it between 100 milliseconds
and 200 milliseconds.
With this, you're going to have sounds, ambiances that
you can put in the world, and they will always sound
fresh and unique--which is really important.
And it's not going to consume many resources.
So let's have an example.
This is the bootcamp demo that
some of you might know.
I've removed all of the sounds in the game, except
for some footsteps and stuff like that.
And I've placed what I've
created is an ambiance object.
So we've created an
ambiance game object.
We've put some ambiance scripting
there--this is the logic that I was talking about--
and we've exposed some audio clips
that we can set. This is the variations.
We've also set some properties that you
can see here as I was describing before
and we have an
ambiance template.
This is a game object that has an audio
source in it and it defines the template.
Like output I suppose,  for your ambiances
or ambient sounds,
and you can see I've defined
some 3D roll-off curve here.
So let's have a quick listen on how it sounds.
Just with five variations and these sounds
I've just grabbed quickly off the internet.
So there's nothing special about them.
You can see that if you have
this sort of setup
placed randomly around the world at
every tree or every group of trees,
you can create the feeling, or the continuous feeling
of something's going on.
Instead of just four or five trees, models sitting
there in the world, and that's really powerful.
Alright, so I'm just going to show you quickly how that's done.
So you can see here that I've defined some variables,
which I showed you before,
and the variances.
The actual code that plays this continuous,
random sort of ambiance is really simple:
You basically just get the template,
instantiate it in a bunch of
random locations within some area
around the place where you place the ambiance,
you set the audio clip on it, and then for the rest the game
or for the rest of the level you just do as I described.
You select a random emitter, you
set the pitch, and you play it
at some random volume and then you
wait for some random amount of time.
It's pretty simple. I mean you
would create more details or more
extensible ambiances in your game, but this is just to show
you how simple it can be to create really nice sounds.
Some best practices for ambiances:
Don't use streaming sounds, and prefer load
into memory or compressed in memory.
This is because if you use the
same sound over and over again,
it creates a new stream
within Unity for each one.
So in the end you're actually gonna blow more memory
using streaming sounds than you would if you just
loaded the sound into memory.
Use multiple audio sources.
Because pitch changes are not applied to--sorry,
they are applied as soon as you play a new sound.
So for example, if I change the pitch of an
audio source and play a bunch of sounds one shot,
the pitch will apply to all of them instead
of just the one that you play next.
So use multiple audio sources if you can, as I did.
If the randomization--sorry.
If you have some budget restrictions and game objects
or you're just running out of memory in general,
you can use one game object with
multiple audio sources and not have this
random location thing that I had going.
It just means that the sound will be coming
from one location. Which is actually,
I mean it's not perfect but it still
sounds really good.
But if you are using multiple game
objects, you can also add audio filters.
So for example,
You can add an audio filter into this...
into this game object here,
like a low pass or something like that,
and then you can also randomize the
properties within that filter.
Which again, increases the amount of
variation and freshness of the sounds.
Use really short sounds, because that's a
lot more preferred than long ones.
Because the listener will be able to hear
repetitions really easy.
Keep the variations similar, don't have one
sound that the sound stands out above all others,
because then the listener will be able
to hear that really quickly.
Don't do large pitch variations, because if you pitch
up or down too much a sound it
kind of destroys the sound altogether.
Sounds with background noise, for
example, if you have a bird sound and
you can hear the traffic in the
background every time you play it
it's going to sound horrible, so avoid that.
Have pure sounds when you are using ambiances.
And all this will reduce the ear fatigue or how annoyed the
listener is going to get while they're playing the game.
Which could be for hours.
Well you would hope that it's for hours right?
Cool. So let's talk about
interactive sounds quickly.
Like I said, interactive sounds are
sounds that change and shift during playback.
So other subsystems, other scripts are changing
how the sound is played or what is played
through this sort of sound object by interfacing it through
parameters And you define those parameters in game logic,
in script code.
They're commonly known as events in
other audio systems like FMod or
WWise and other systems like that.
They encapsulate sound logic and define an interface
to the game through a set of parameters.
What that means is they, like I said, all the logic
you define in one sort of script, in one game object
and you can place that
in lots of locations, in lots of vehicles
for example, or other concepts like that.
And then you define these parameters,
this interface.
Parameterize sound and effect properties, for example,
you can define an interface for
volume, pitch, speaker spread
low pass effects, echo resonance,
anything that you can--any property
you can change on an audio...
audio source you can sort of
parameterize that property.
Plus, you can actually introduce new sounds, fade
out sounds, cross fade in sounds, and stuff like that,
all through this interface.
Just define, keep all of
this sort of logic in one place.
Which, this is the problem that I see with
a lot of people writing audio in Unity.
Is that they're just placing all these concepts in all
different places and trying to tie it all together.
And this is really not extensible. It's not
something that you can reuse and extend well.
So try to keep it in to
game concept, game objects.
So usually you define again,
just game parameters,
this logic that I was talking
about and again the raw sounds.
Same for ambiances.
They come together and they define your
interactive sound.
Examples:
Car engines, of course.
Your parameter would be the rpm, how fast
the car is spinning--engine is spinning.
Load--how much under load the car is.
Or a machine gun turret.
Is the enemy within range?
Should I shoot?
Am I being blown up by the enemy?
Should I explode?
Crowd chatter, crowd walla.
Parameter could be the panic level of the
crowd, how excited, how fearful they are.
And the crowd density.
How many people are in the crowd?
As I said parameters are defined and controlled within scripts.
As with ambiances, you build the "Sound Object," as I said,
within script classes.
You also have to define an
interface to apply the audio clips.
And you also create
some template
output audio sources, like I showed you
with the ambiances. That's usually the
best practice for that.
You also want to
diffuse animation curves
within Unity to define the
map between the game concept.
For example, if you have
a characters health between 100 and 0.
You want to map that to the pitch
of a sound within him,
between 1 and 1.5.
You do that by using "AnimationCurves"
instead of putting that in your script code.
Because then it's easily
modifiable and changeable,
as you want to iterate your sounds
and iterate your sound objects,
as you're creating your game.
It's really powerful.
You can see here's an example.
You're mapping the low pass cut-off to
distance from the character or something.
So let's have an example
of an interactive sound.
Back here we have... We have our
our world and I've defined
this barrel over here
that has an exploder script in it.
Basically all that does is,
allows the user to shoot the barrel
and as the barrels getting shot,
it's going to sort of get more and more
buzzy, and then eventually explode.
You can see this animation curve here
defines the health versus the pitch,
as I was describing.
All the logic is
encased in this one script
put onto a game object, and then placed within
another game object or some other concept.
So that the game can then get the game object,
get the script, set some parameters
and then, yea. So I'll just play it
so you can see
exactly what's going on in terms of audio.
I placed it a bit far away. I'll just take a walk there.
So now if I shoot the barrel,
you can see it's blowing up,
or it's a timer or something.
Every time I shoot it, it increases the damage
and the pitch is applied.
Right.
So.
Fairly simple I suppose.
Nothing too exciting there.
But if you package it up nicely and, you know,
for example, you can put that game object
we just had there into a prefab, and then drag it on
all of your barrels really quickly or something else.
So another concept, then change the sounds
that you're using and then you can have
this explosion mechanic just happen on
just about any type of object.
When we look at the script
itself we can see it's pretty simple.
Again we define the interface here,
and the actual parameters we've
defined just drive the playback.
I mean we just play the sound
if its not been shot before,
we evaluate the damage, and apply to the
pitch, and if the damage is below zero
then we stop the sound and play the
explosion sound.
Fairly simple, but you can
see if you package it right,
you can actually create some pretty
powerful sounds.
Cool. So I'm going to quickly go
through the the best practices.
As I said, do the sound as
an interactive logic, like a script.
Allow the inspector setters for the audio assets,
so the audio clips.
Like I described then, you can have the same
logic with different audio assets
being applied to different audio
concepts within the game.
That's really powerful, and
it's very simple to do.
Package it up within a game object,
as I showed you.
Create a prefab, like I said.
Use "Object.Instanciate" to create
these interactive sounds on the fly.
So what that means is you can have these
sort of interactive sound objects
as templates within the game, and then
only instanciate new ones when you
want to use them. For example,
don't have all of the barrels
having audio sources all at once.
Only really create these sort of
audio objects when they're needed.
On the fly using instanciate.
And then you can destroy them and that
saves on resources quite a lot.
Cool. So let's talk quickly about interactive music.
And this is like I said,
my favorite part of audio.
Cause interactive music is something that
you guys can define
that is really going to engage and immerse
your users in the game
without actually defining anything visually
or any sort of game mechanic.
I mean, having interactive sounds draws the player
into what's happening, and directs them
how you want them to feel in a
particular situation.
So the whole idea behind
interactive music
is that you want to create dynamic music
that changes with the game state.
So when you walk into a cave,
the music changes, and you know, it becomes
more sinister or something like that.
We do this by transitioning between
musical elements or what's known as stems.
You know in a beat synced way, so you transition
between one musical theme to another.
And you can do it on the beat or
the bar or some sort of cross fade
between the two, on a beat or a bar.
This allows the music to transition nice and
smoothly and seamlessly, so that the user
kind of doesn't even notice that it's changed, but
they just feel that it's changed.
You also want to allow the game to apply
musical additions to the playing stems.
So what's known as flourishes and stingers.
So for example:
Imagine a game where you are running
around and you pick up power-ups.
And each time you pick up a power-up,
you play some nice enhancement
or duh duh duh dah
on top of the already
playing music system
in a beat synced way, and that
really sort of comes together
to make a really good music system.
The music changes and transitions with the
mood of the game, like I said.
Liike I said, this is really powerful for drawing
the users in--the players in to your game.
Games that a lot of indie
players sort of come to really love,
for example, Journey
or Braid, games like that.
A lot of people don't really notice that it's because of this
powerful music, and powerful sound design that they've kind of
included within the game mechanic,
which also enhances, you know
enhances the games quite a lot.
So you want to build a
scripting system that
encapsulates all of the playback
and transitions on beats and bars.
So your scripts shouldn't
actually ever play sounds,
you know when another sound is finished,
or through some other mechanic.
You want it to transition always on beats and bars.
And you want to schedule that
transition ahead of time,
because this allows the transition to
happen perfectly in a sample-accurate way.
To do that use the "AudioSettings.dspTime" setting.
So this is a new feature in 4.1 or 4.2.
It basically allows you to
get the current DSP clock, or
the sound clock--the sound engine clock of the game.
Then you can schedule the playback of new sounds
based on the current time of where you are,
and you do that using the audio source play schedule.
Then you can play this audio source,
this, you know, stem or musical theme.
You can play it ahead of time, using the play
schedule and you pass it a time, or you know the
absolute time that you want to play it at,
not any sort of delta or anything like that.
Again you want, you really want to schedule
based on beats per minute or beats and bars,
because then you won't have
any sort of musical drift or
the music won't scatter as
the as the time goes on.
So you assign stems to themes, and define
transition logic from one theme to another.
So you want to define themes and transitions, so you want
to be able to transition from the cave to the dungeon.
This basically changes
what stems are playing, what sounds are playing
and how they're played.
You trigger these theme changes
from scripts and game input.
So, you know, the game, you walk from
the forest to the cave and you trigger that off.
Like I said,
your engine, your music engine, you really want to
define a schedule look ahead.
So this basically is
a small amount of time
ahead of where you actually are right now.
Where you schedule the transition from one sound to another
on the exact beat.
This allows the music system to be
extremely accurate and extremely tight.
So let's have an example:
I have a project here which doesn't
actually define any transition,
logic from the
game, or the game state.
But it's just something simple to show you how...
So we have an audio stitching script, which
is something simple to show you how you
would define this transition logic. And then you can
build your own music system on top of this idea.
As you can see I've got
the drums, a set of drums
a set of bases, and a set of effects.
And I'll just play it.
And you can listen. You can see actually how it's being
transitioned, and then I'll look through the script.
So the transition...
You can see that the red line here
defines when we actually schedule
the playback of these sources here,
like one second ahead of time.
That's very generous, usually
you only need to set it at,
a few hundred milliseconds max.
But it's just to to be
able to show you that
the transition in time is
actually happening here,
but you want to schedule it here.
Then when I play it, you can
see that it transitions perfectly
from one to another.
And again.
So the engine driving this is really simple.
You can see here that,
like I said, you've just defined
the "AudioSettingsDSPtime."
But you define the next
event as that time plus some
look ahead time. And then when you are actually
within that range, so as you saw then,
when you are within
that window, you just play
or schedule the playback of that next source.
And this is done here just randomly selecting
the next source to play and
then you play that source
at the look ahead time. Very simple.
Very simple, and you just keep doing this over and over
again at however many beats or bars you want.
And that's how you would define the
basic logic of your music system.
So as I said schedule the stems based
on beat times, not on the length of the stem.
This is because, for example, if you do
the length of the stem,
compression artifacts like MP3,
if any of you guys have had this problem,
wiill cause stutters and sort
of breaks in your sounds.
Any sort of tails at the end
of your sounds will cause the music to drift.
And you want to tune that look ahead,
that sort of schedule buffer
to make the sound system as
responsive as possible to game input.
But you also want it to be
long enough so that
you never have any sort of
problems, in terms of stream--
streaming sounds not ready to play,
they haven't buffered the sound properly
and then you have artifacts from that.
So how do you make it sizzle?
As I said beat match the flourishes on top,
so picking up a power up.
You want to keep the stem sizes small, so that they
can transition at any time.
You want the beats generally, or you want to be able to
transition on a beat or a bar. Beats are preferable
so that it's super, super responsive.
And you want to transition on
bars or even beats, like I just said.
This relies on the scheduling system to work
with time, like I said, beats and bars.
Cool. So what we've done here
is, we've kind of defined
three of your most used
audio concepts in games,
and we've defined nice ways
of sort of structuring those within Unity.
And creating audio frameworks in script,
and defining these sort of sound objects
that you want to reuse throughout your game.
And I just wanted to say that you guys are here
probably because you have some
interest in audio
and I thank you for that.
But remember that audio
is half of the game.
So when you play a game
you'll look at the screen
and you also hear, and that's exactly
half of your senses of the game.
So audio is pretty
important right?
You can get a lot out of just
improving the audio within you game,
just a small amount. You can actually increase the
quality of the game that you're making so much.
Great sounding audio should be as important as
other parts of your game, your game mechanics,
the graphics, all those sort of things.
So with all of that you should go away from this talk
and, just think about what I'm saying and think
about the concepts I've described
and make the sound that your game has awesome.
So, yeah, just want to say thanks.
If you guys have any questions, let's have them.
Yes, yes I can.
(Hi. I know this is not necessarily a
Unity question, more of a sound design question.)
(What's the rule of thumb you follow for
basically balancing ambient sounds and music?)
Yup, so this is something that
I wanted to talk about
if I had time, but I didn't really have time. I wanted
to talk about mixing and how you would do that.
So in Unity we're kind of moving
forward with our audio systems, and we're kind of
moving towards being able to do that in
a much more intuitive way in the future.
You know, defining some mixing ideas and concepts.
But in Unity you can still actually define
your own mixing system using
things like the on-audio filter read,
it's in the mono behavior function.
That's basically a call back that allows
you to apply your own attenuation or filters,
and pipe that audio to other parts or
other audio sources and stuff like that.
If you wanted to create your own mixing solution you could
do it using this one function.
Rather than that, you're kind of
mixing in Unity at the moment,
just from the basic concepts.
You want to kind of play around with those
properties while the game is running
and change the volumes and the levels
of the ambiances in real time, and then you can apply
those changes after you've exited play mode.
So I would, like I've defined there,
the volume of the--
Sorry, I've defined a number of variation-like
properties, like randomization properties.
I would perhaps have like a volume--
like a static volume variable
and that volume is multiplied
with everything else when you play all of your ambiances.
And then you can change that volume in one place.
And that you can bring the mix up of all your ambiances
or a subset of those ambiances
from one place. So that would help.
Cool, thank you.
I hope that helped.
Any other questions?
(Hi. Thanks for your talk.
With regards to dynamic music,)
(what's the best way to keep the beat
synchronization going?)
(Is there any kind of danger of getting out of sync
because the sample runs on in time, if you use, say,)
(an unusual time signature like 130 beats per minute?)
No. Like I said, if the sound is
being played
sample accurately
in terms of in the subsystem.
If you schedule the playback of your sound is based on
current if you get the DSPtime thing.
That gets the DSP time of the mixer
with what's happening in the audio subsystem,
and then if you schedule, ahead of time, you're
never going to get any drift.
It's going to be scheduled
sample accurately. Bang, bang, bang.
So using these methods
you're gonna have tight music.
(Any dangers of say in a high resource
load environment getting out of sync or anything like that?)
The only problem you're going to have is if
you're not scheduling
ahead of time enough, that's going to be one problem.
But if the audio is stuttering because the
game is just being blown away.
It's going to slowdown everything,
including the clock.
So you're going to--
Everything is statically
synchronized, linear, so it's not going to
drift because of stutter.
(Thank you very much.)
Anybody else?
Currently the way
we'd expose file formats in Unity is a little confusing.
What I recommend is, you should always import
audio assets into Unity as plain wav files.
Then per audio source define
whether you want that to be compressed or not.
Then let Unity decide which compression
format is best, for example on,
iOS and android that's going to be MP3,
Windows and Mac and web player and
everything that's going to be OGG Vorbis.
The reason why it's going
to be OGG Vorbis is because, OGG is better
the compression is better in terms of artifacts
at the end of the sound,
like MP3 doesn't loop
properly, stuff like that.
But on mobile devices,
playing an OGG file just doesn't make sense
because it just consumes too many resources.
So yeah, I mean, like I said,
generally keep it to your
import in wav.
Let Unity decide what compression format,
and if you really want to decide for
Unity, like maybe you want to play
a particular looping sound
on iOS and it's very small,
and so you say "Okay I want it to be OGG."
Then compress it to OGG
and import it into Unity.
And then just set it to leave it as native and then it
will actually get built and played in the game as OGG,
and that that decoder will decode the OGG file.
Don't do it for many
files, because OGG is very expensive.
But yea.
Thank you.
It's time?
I just want to say thanks guys. Thanks for coming
here and listening to my talk.