...And we make a lot of mobile
games in Southeast Asia.
I guess you guys do
here in Japan, as well.
And one of things that comes up very
often is they want to make 2D games.
And doing 2D games in Unity
isn't necessarily hard,
but it's not like drag-and-
drop, out of the box.
So today, what I want to do is I want
to go through a 2D content workflow.
What I mean by workflow is
we want to start at one end,
and we want to follow our
content through a pipeline
and have it ultimately arrive
in our game at the other end.
So by definition, unfortunately, workflow
also means there's a lot of parts.
And because there's a lot of parts,
it can also be a bit confusing.
So I know it's after lunch, everybody's stomach
is full, and the room could get a bit warm,
but hopefully, you'll all be able to
stay with me and I won't lose you all.
Hopefully, some of you will make it to the end.
So you probably might wonder "is this talk for me?"
So you're gonna be looking at quite a
bit of code. We're gonna be looking at art tools.
We're going to be looking at a lot of stuff.
So if you're a designer, an artist, a programmer,
my goal today is basically
to take you very slowly,
step-by-step through one pipeline.
Then we'll check the time. Assuming there's
time, we'll do it again with another tool,
and another tool, and another
tool, until we run out of time.
So my goal is that, at least at the end
of the day, you know what's possible,
and maybe open up some possibilities in Unity.
Okay, so let's get started.
Basically, what we have a is
we have all this stuff, right?
We all this great stuff that
artists might produce for us.
And it just brings up the question of
"how can I get this into Unity?"
But actually images suffer a little bit
from the fact that they're
not very rich in information.
We have the name of the file,
and if it's a jpeg or some other
type that supports metadata,
you might have a little bit a metadata that's
good for wedding photographers or somebody else.
But for game developers,
it's kind of a problem.
So really what we want to do
is we don't necessarily want our
images to communicate to Unity.
What we really want to happen
is we want our applications
to communicate to Unity.
So we need some way to get
the stuff from our app
into Unity and back out.
And so to do that, what we're gonna
do is define, basically, a workflow.
So we're gonna start with our
application on the far side, our art tool,
and we're gonna have Unity
as where the destination is,
and we're going to need
to make a few pieces.
So the first thing that we're gonna
need is, on the content tools side,
we're gonna need some
way, some mechanism,
an order that understands the art tool
and can communicate with the art tool
to get some information out that we want.
So in other words, we're gonna write
some sort of exporter from our art tool.
Something that gives us what we want.
And what do we want from that?
Well, we want the images
that we got before,
but in addition to that, we're also going
to want some more metadata.
We're going to want as much
metadata as we can get.
So the exporter is going to then
not only give us the images out,
but it's going to give us the
metadata in the form of XML.
Then on the Unity side, of course
we can bring the data in normally, right?
The XML file will be recognized as a text asset
and the images will be recognized as images.
But that's not exactly what we want. We also are
going to want to write something on the Unity side
to makes sense of all that extra information
that we put on the art tools side.
So it all begins of course with a tool.
And the first tool I'm gonna start
out with today is Photoshop.
And one of the goals of
this talk that I have is,
obviously I'm trying to make it understandable,
and I'd like to make it useful,
but I'd also like to make it real.
So before I joined Unity, I did
work on a number of games,
but the last game I worked on
before joining Unity was
a 2D game, so I thought I
would just use use that.
And that was what's called
a "hidden object game."
And the game I'll be using today
is called "Goddess Chronicles."
Here's just a screen cap. This is
from the Mac App Store, actually.
And basically, if you don't
know hidden object games,
this would be found on like
Big Fish Games-type portals.
It's this thing where you're
kind of on an adventure,
looking to find certain things in the scene,
you collect those things together, and then you
move on, solve puzzles and things like that.
So this game had puzzles,
hidden object scenes, a story.
Today, I'm just going to show you the main part
of the game which was the hidden object part,
and how that worked.
And we're gonna do that,
as I said, in Photoshop.
So we're going to switch over to Photoshop.
And here is that scene that
was in the screenshot.
So I tried to use one that was
actually there in the App Store.
And you can see that it
basically looks the same.
So, we want to basically author
our games in Photoshop.
In this game, just so you
understand, at the end,
all of the levels were
built in Photoshop.
And they were just brought straight into
Unity, no programming whatsoever.
Everything was done on this side.
There was programming done on the Unity
side to create this sort of little engine,
but the code is very simple
and I'll show you that as well.
So what we want is to unleash our artists
and designers to be able to go do that.
So we recognize in a hidden object
game, we need some constructs.
So for this particular game,
we had two kinds of things.
We had items and we had scenery.
There really isn't that much
distinction between the two
except "scenery" means it can never be
"found." It will always be in the background.
Now there's another interesting thing
that happens and that is,
you can imagine that say one of my
search items was the bottle of water.
So, in the game I might have this bottle
of water here and as you can see,
you cannot see the
entire bottle of water.
But we also may be doing an image.
It could be a photograph,
or our artist could have drawn,
say, an office scene or a podium.
So this podium, and this everything might
actually be drawn into the background.
But I want the water bottle to be found,
so the water bottle will actually be
in front of the podium in Photoshop.
So the first thing that we need to do is we
need to have two kinds of images for our scene.
One will be whole, the whole image.
The other will be obscured.
So it may be obscured, right? So in this
case my water bottle here is obscured.
But when I find it, if I
clicked on the water bottle,
then it may fly of the center
of the screen and then zoom up,
out towards the player, or go into
a backpack or something.
So I obviously want to have the full version.
So every item has to have a whole.
That's a minimum requirement, and if I
had the water bottle just sitting out,
then there's no need to have
an obscured version of it.
If I do want obscure it, then I want to be
able to basically erase the pixels
so it gives the illusion of being
behind even though it's in front.
I need two more image types. One other
type that I'm going to need is shadow.
In order for the water bottle to actually
look like it belongs, it'd be nice
if it casts a shadow on
the desk that it was on.
But when I find the item, if it zooms
out and then the shadow came with it,
that would look a bit funny, right?
So what we're going to do is we're actually going
to keep the shadow separate from the image.
And then finally, you might
have something in your game
like a golf club that you
might be looking for.
And that would be really hard to click
on or to tap on with your finger.
So we'll have a hot spot region, as well.
So we're going to have four
different kinds of layers.
So I have an example here of one.
So in the back, I think in the upper screen.
Of course my battery picked it
up. It works, but doesn't show.
Right up here, you'll see a shell.
It's kind of a small example, but
I'm gonna show and hide the group
so you can see, it goes away.
And if we look over here in Photoshop,
you can see it has an "obscured,"
it has a "shadow," it has a "hot
spot," and it has a "whole."
So normally, we enable the "obscured
in shadow" or "whole in shadow."
And then the rest just sits here.
So we go through and we create
the whole scene like this, right?
So I can hide the whole background and
you can see there's a lot of stuff
that's actually pre-baked
into the background.
And then I have all
the rest of the items.
So I try to only export the minimal things,
because I want to perform well on mobiles as well.
Okay, so I've authored the scene in Photoshop,
and I've got some very basic coding.
So I make sure I just mentioned it. So like on the shell.
So we name the layer here "obscured."
We name "shadow," "hot spot," and "whole."
Right? So it's not artist naming.
The artist can name anything they
want, like here on the scenery column.
As you can guess artists are a creative bunch.
They have all kinds. This
one's actually not named bad,
but a lot of times you'll have "layer 52,"
"layer 53," "layer 54 copy," "layer 55,"
and so on. So scenery, we don't care so much.
The group name is important but the layer names are not.
And the item names? We actually
care about the layer names.
So, good! So we authored up some content,
and so that takes care of our tool,
that takes care of our standard.
But now we're gonna need some way to
actually get this data out of Photoshop.
And the way we're gonna do
that is with Extend Script.
Extend Script is actually a free scripting
environment that comes with Adobe applications.
If you've installed Creative Suite before,
it was actually installed by default.
And you can find it, I think on the Mac, it will be in
utilities, Adobe Utilities Extend Script.
And you'll find it in there.
And it allows you to script some of
the more popular Adobe applications.
And this is fantastic.
It didn't used to be this way. You
used to have to sign up with Adobe,
pay a lot of money, and it was a C++ SDK.
And even if you wanted to give them money, they
didn't always give you permission to develop.
So it was very tough thing to do. But now
we can just write scripts in Javascript,
and away we go.
So I'd like to show you the exporter
that we used for Goddess.
And that would be over here.
So here's the Extend Script toolkit.
And it's pretty standard
IDE that ships with it.
The Javascript and the IDE, everything isn't
very fast but it's okay, it's not runtime.
So we're just going to configure
our level, we're going to export.
We don't really care how long it takes.
It would be good if it was fast,
but it doesn't really matter. The
important thing is that it's here.
And up here at the top of the menu,
we're actually going
to choose Photoshop.
Now, I know it's interesting because
my mouse is all the way up there,
but you should actually watch down here,
in this corner. You'll see that when I click this,
that all of this part goes
away and then it comes back.
And that's because it
talked to Photoshop,
and then they're communicating live.
Now when you write a script it's nice because
you can write it here, debug, write, debug.
When it's done, you don't have to do this.
Your script will actually appear
here on the scripts menu, and I
have it down here, export, Unity,
hidden object, scene--you can
see I write lots of exporters.
This is actually production scripts. So
let me just go through this real quick.
I'm not going to go super deep, but I just
want you to get an idea what's in here.
So we just simply create a
few variables that we need
for our scene, the PSD,
and the duped one.
I'm going to cover some of
these a little more in depth.
We just make sure that we
have an actual valid document.
And this is again because your artists
are gonna go off and go crazy,
and you wanna make sure that you're
giving them lots of error messages,
so it just helps them to make
sure they have a document open.
They select a destination folder,
and they cache some useful variables.
They make sure that it has layers.
And then probably the meat of
it is just these few lines here.
And probably the most important
step is this: "duplicate."
So we must duplicate the document,
because in Photoshop, what you'll notice
is this odd behavior you can see right now
in the upper left there's the disclosure,
it's showing a little dot up there.
So if I save this file, now it's not
dirty anymore, right? It's normal.
If I just open a folder or close a
folder, it's already dirty again.
So the problem is the
act of exporting your file
will cause the Photoshop
file to become dirty.
And what will happen is an artist,
they're doing a lot different things.
They'll run the exporter,
after they're done exporting,
they'll try to quit, maybe later in the day,
5 o'clock or 8 o'clock, when they go home,
and it's going to be like,
"Do you want to save?" Uh oh.
"Do I want to save? I don't remember.
Oh, I guess I better save."
Now your version control system is going
to say that Photoshop file has changed.
Now the programmer is
gonna get all the files,
and they're gonna see all the exported
images were exported at 11 in the morning,
but then the Photoshop file
was updated at 8 PM at night.
So then the programmer is like, "Do I have to
re-export?" And you end up in this loop
where the Photoshop file
is always getting dirty.
The other thing is,
I want to tell you right now,
if you start writing exporters
for Adobe products,
you are not stupid.
You will think you're stupid because it
is a very head-banging experience.
The manual's very nicely written,
everything looks good,
but even the best programmers, it is
very frustrating to write these things.
It's very trial and error,
and there's a lot of little caveats and not
everything is as well documented as it should be.
So the other reason you want to duplicate
is because when it dies, and it will
when you're writing your own,
then it will leave the original untouched
because it will take down everything,
and then you will have to kill everything.
So then it allows you to just keep going.
So anyway, we just want to duplicate
And then we're going to set
the active layer to the last layer.
Right? And the reason why
is because in Photoshop,
the last layer is the farthest back.
And we want to export from back to front,
so that we know where everything goes.
And then we're going to remove
all top-level art layers.
We do this because, well, we made
like twenty over console titles.
So in the old days, this is
because we did NTSC and PAL.
And we had the safe area, right?
And then on mobiles, we
now use it, or used it then
for Android, write all different screen
configurations, so the artist could go in,
and what we did is we just said, "Hey, if it's not
in the group, then it's just a development file."
So they could put anywhere in the
sorting order, but not in a folder,
any kind of file they want.
They could make masks, they
could make reference images,
anything they want to do. Maybe they want
to put in the HUD so that they can see,
make sure it's not being blocked by an item.
So we just remove all
the top-level art layers.
Then we remove all the empty layer
sets, in case there's any other ones.
Then we hide everything.
So what we should end up with is the
duplicated Photoshop file
with only groups
and everything hidden
with just a checkerboard,
transparent background.
We set up our XML variable.
And then we export.
When we're done exporting,
then we close off the file,
and write everything to disk.
To export the layer, it's pretty easy.
It's a recursive function. It calls itself.
So it's going to drill down,
it's going to take the last group.
And within that group, take the last group
within the last group within the last group
until it finds no more groups.
Then it's going to--and that's
backward, you see, "i--."
It starts at the end and goes backwards,
and it's going to call itself.
So now it means it has a layer set.
We create a running number,
because artists copy.
So you may have tree,
tree, tree, tree, tree.
And then we just at a running number
so the backs of the images we export
don't collide with each other.
Then we check that "item:."
So that's here, right? "item:."
So it tells us we have an item, and then
we grab out the name after the colon.
And then we check what it is. Is a hot
spot, obscured shadow, or whole?
And then we simply save out the PNG down here.
And to do that, what we do is we trim the
left and top--that must be it's XY position.
Then we trim the right and bottom.
And then we get the size, and
then we know how big it is.
And then we simply save out the image
and write the XML data. And that's it.
There's a bit of code in here, but it's
pretty logical, pretty easy to understand.
And so what I'm going to do,
at the risk of this dying on me,
we will actually--actually, I'll run
this from the debugger itself.
So what you'll see is, hopefully, got Photoshop
configured. I think this should work.
So it's asking me where I wanna put
this, and I need to put this in "projects,"
"workflows," and "hidden
object game," "levels," "Greek hall."
And here it is. This is where my file
goes, so I'm just gonna stick it in here.
And then what you see immediately
is that it made a copy.
And Photoshop, if you have
a really powerful machine,
you'll be able to see it more, but it
only gives you snapshots.
So you're gonna see things
kind of randomly looking random.
But it's actually going through the code.
And you should eventually see
that everything gets hidden.
And then you'll see that
it's just pulling items out.
So we have the original Photoshop file, we
have the duplicate with everything hidden.
Then what we do is we duplicate
that, show the current layer,
collapse the entire thing, trim, trim,
save out the image, save out
the XML, and keep going.
And when we're done, we should hopefully have a
whole directory full of images and some metadata.
And this is when the artists go to lunch.
Okay, it all finished, it didn't crash, everything's good.
And if we go look at our files here,
let's just go have a look-see at them.
"Assets," "hidden object game," "levels," "Greek
hall." And you can see it created all these items,
as well as the metadata that we wanted.
So now, based on that, we
took back that Greek Hall file,
and we generated all of the small image
files, as well as the XML we needed.
So now we've got step two done.
Now, the only thing we need
to do is get it into Unity.
Now by default, when we first
bring it into Unity, of course
it's just going to come in as normal
images and a normal text asset.
But then we're also going to need
to write the importer part. Okay?
So let's bring it into Unity.
And we'll see that all
the things are coming in.
And fair enough, if
I go and open this,
then here, I see all the
items that are in here.
So I see some hot spots,
I see some statues, right?
And then of course, I got all the
metadata, the XML is in here as well.
But we don't really want these
as just, you know, Unity by default
will just make these textures, right?
And then we also want a game. We
want to generate a game out of this.
So we need to write the
next piece, and to do that,
we're gonna create two classes.
We're going to create a C# class that's
going to be able to deserialize.
What we're going to do is take the XML and
convert it into a usable class for us.
And then we're gonna have an editor
script that can make sense of that.
And to do that, we're going to use
our old standby, Mono Develop.
So, we go into Mono Develop.
And what I can see here is I've got my HOG
scene class--my "hidden object game" class,
and let's go open the metadata that was generated.
So this was generated about all
of our Photoshop exporter, right?
We wrote out for each layer
all this information.
And if I scroll sideways, right,
it's got all the positions and everything.
So the way deserialization works is,
I have a HOG scene that has layers.
So I create a class called
"HOGscene" that has layers.
And for each one of those layers,
you can see there's a type,
there's a name, and there's
a number of images.
So we have a type, we have a name,
and we have a number of images.
Okay, so basically, we
can take this, load it up,
and we're gonna get this.
And this will be much easier to work with.
For the importer itself.
If you just watched the talk, if you've
seen Tim's talk on asset serialization.
Did it already happen? Or maybe it's later today.
You can get a lot more information about how to do this.
But basically, what we're gonna do is, now
we're just gonna create an editor script.
And it's gonna have a menu item.
So its assets create "import HOGscene."
And that's simply going to open a file.
File chooser dialog box.
And assuming that we actually chose a
file, that's going to call our importer.
So what are importer is going to do is call "deserialize XML".
What it means is "take the XML and give
me a real class that's based on that."
And then I'm also going to ask the user if
they want to save the current scene.
So we're actually going
to generate a full scene.
We're generating everything. We're gonna
generate meshes, we're gonna generate a scene.
The whole game, ready to go.
So first thing we gotta do, is see, do you,
do you want to save the
current one if it needed saving.
And if it's like, "Ooh, I see you're gonna
redo my scene," yeah, we let you bailout.
Okay, so looks like we want to go ahead, so what we're
gonna do as grab our base file name and base directory.
And what we're gonna do is find out if there
is even a scene file that already exists.
If the scene file already exists, we delete it.
Right? This is a fully destructive
process for generating games here.
And then we create a new scene.
Now what we're going to do is
look through all of our textures.
And we need to fix the settings, so if you look
over here at any one of these textures,
right, let's look at the bell.
So the bell is here, and you can see it's just
texture, but that's not really what we want.
What we actually we need is we
need it read-write enabled.
We want to disable the power of two.
And we don't want mipmaps,
so we need to fix this up.
Okay, and the way we're gonna
do that is come through here.
We're gonna get that texture importer.
And then we're going to disable mipmaps,
make it readable.
We don't care about power of two,
because we're going to make an atlas.
We're gonna try to make
this game very performant.
And we're gonna set the wrap mode, the
filter mode, everything that we need to do.
And then if it's a visible image
that's actually in the game,
we're going to create a separate
array of textures to hold it.
This is because to generate an atlas in
Unity, you pass in an array of textures.
So we add all the images that we actually
wanna generate in the atlas to a texture list.
Then we're going to create a material,
a single material, to hold our atlas.
And same thing, if there's already a
material there, we're going to delete it.
So, normal game development, right? You do
the first time, everything comes through.
But then you're gonna iterate,
you're gonna play test,
make change, export again,
play test, make change.
So there could be files in this directory already.
So we're going to clean up after
ourselves and delete the material.
We're gonna make a new material,
put the shader we want on it,
and then load it back.
Now, we're gonna make the atlas.
To make an atlas in Unity is really easy.
It's one line of code. You declare the texture.
And then you call pack textures,
give it the texture array.
And it will pass you back an array of rectangles,
where each rectangle at the same
index as the texture you passed in,
tells it where in the atlas it is.
And then this one, we also need to fix up.
We need to fix up our texture settings
because I don't want to
have to mouse click that later.
And we're almost done. Then, what
we're gonna do is simply create the meshes.
So we're gonna create 2D polygonal meshes,
create a new game object,
we're gonna set the name.
We're gonna set the position based on the
XML that we output from photoshop.
We're going to add it as an
item if it was an item control.
If it's an item, we need a attach
the item controller, the code to it.
We're going to set up the hit test.
So we're gonna get all the
hit test data, extract that out.
And then we're going to
set up the game object.
So this one line here is when we actually create
the game object. I'll look at that in a minute.
We set up the camera because
this is a brand new scene.
We save everything and we're done.
So, really simple. We process
all the textures using the XML,
generate a scene, generate meshes,
put the textures on the meshes,
arrange them in the scene,
save everything, and we're done.
And to generate a 2D
mesh in Unity is quite easy.
Create a new game object,
we just add the mesh filter,
we add the mesh renderer, we create the
vertices, the UVs, vert colors, and we're done.
Very simple.
And then we have the way
to extract the hit test data.
So, with luck, if I just go and run this.
So, I can go to go "assets," "create,"
so we put it on the menu.
There it is.
And then it wants me to choose.
It wants me to choose the file to import.
So here's the Greek hall that
we exported from Photoshop.
Today, 2:20.
We open that.
We wait a moment.
It's going through the importer scripts.
And when we're all done,
you can see it's generated
a Unity scene. All my items are
in the scene, just like they were.
We can see down here it's created all the meshes.
And if I go look at the Greek hall name,
you can see that the atlas is here.
We'll just double-click on this.
So it created a single texture PNG with all of my
background, all the little items scattered around.
And everything's there.
And it modified my camera.
And if I click on an item, like for
example one of the items like the bell,
you can see it's attached the item controller.
It's configured all the data I need, and
I can just run the game straight away.
And there you go.
I've got just a very simple--in my game,
I had like, obviously, a very nice UI.
But then for this talk, I just stripped that
out and used a plain, simple Unity GUI.
So you can see it's got all the
items down below on the bottom.
And my own game there,
I clicked on one that went away.
Idols, where are the idols?
I'm not good at my own game.
You run it again.
So, goblet.
Goblet is this one in the back,
so I click on it, it goes away.
So, really simple.
Right? And then this is basically the game.
Of course, you would add transitions,
or anything else that
you wanted into that.
If you want to look at the game
code itself, just for completion.
So we have the item controller.
So these are the fields that I'm serializing.
They're private, so I have to
mark them as "serialize field."
If you went to Tim Cooper's talk on
serialization, he goes into this more in depth.
So basically, it's choosing
the search items.
So we shuffle the deck every time you run the game,
it will randomly choose how many items to find.
Otherwise, we have XY hit
testing for picking item.
We don't use physics or any
colliders. And that's about it.
The rest of it is just simple adding
myself to a list, cleaning up after myself.
On start, making sure my Z-sort,
everything, is in the right place,
and shuffled. So very, very simple concept,
just to build a hidden object game.
And we did the HOG scene and the HOG
importer. These at the two main parts.
Now the other thing that I want
to--and that came into Unity, of course.
So when you author games in Photoshop,
or any of the tools actually, basically the idea is
simply making sure that the objects within the tool
are using metadata in their names. Right?
And by doing that, then you can
write some sort of exporter
that understands the
naming conventions,
extracts that data out, and generates
everything that you need to make it work.
And then we simply need
to use Unity's editor scripting
to make sense of all that in the end.
So we do still have some time.
I'd like to cover animation.
At our studio, we used Anime Studio
because it was Windows and Mac-based.
And it was very simple, straightforward, easy to use.
So I have an example that we did
on that. This is from the same game.
It's a simple dream sequence scene where she has
something, and there's some UI bits that come up.
But the basic thing that you like about
animation tools is how simple they are.
I have here three strands of hair.
I have eyes open, closed, and half.
I have the head.
I have two spirals and a background.
And that's it.
So it doesn't really matter
how long the movie is
I don't have to render it out
to some giant file, right?
We want our games to be very
lightweight and easy to use.
So is a very simple animation.
It just shows her blinking
and doing some things.
So the artist can come in here, and do that.
And then it's the same idea.
We would use some sort of exporter.
In the case of Anime Studio, it happens
to be Lua. It's a scripting language.
So same idea. We would write all of the
code that we need to export all the layers,
and get all the metadata
and stuff we want off that.
And then back on the Unity side,
we would write the import.
That would be here and
it's the same thing.
We create a menu,
we call the importer.
It's the same,
I mean it's copy-paste.
So once you've wrote your first one,
it's very easy to write more the these.
I mean really, this is
literally a copy-paste.
I rewrote the exporter on Saturday.
Last Saturday, I took like two hours,
its like, just copy-paste everything in.
It's got the exact same
mesh generation code.
The only difference was
the custom code to generate
all of the audio and everything
support that we have.
And that one as well, we
go into Anime Studio then.
We can export this to Unity.
"Projects," "2D workflows," "assets," "animation,"
"cutscenes," "dream sequence."
Save that--now this one's very fast because
we don't do anything with the images.
We just left them there.
So then that should come in.
I should see my--yup.
I got my XML data and
it's exactly the same.
I have a cutscene with
width, height, and layers.
So I created a cutscene class,
And same, with all the data that I need.
And then of course, this has a lot
of key frames. It has very few images,
but it has a lot, a lot, a
lot, a lot, a lot of data going out.
So on the Unity-side, we
simply link and import.
So we can create
importer cutscene.
And it's exactly the same as before.
We go into the dream
sequence, click open.
Does all the processing, I click run
and I get exactly the same thing out.
So there's no programmer
involvement in any of this.
Because of Z-sorting and Z-fighting,
it's hard to see all the elements there.
So everything in here is a proper Unity object.
You can see that the head,
eyeswitch follows exactly
what was over here with the head
and the eyeswitch as a child.
So it's just a really simple
mapping from one to one.
And everything goes straight through.
And you don't really have
to stop there as well.
You can go--so Anime Studio is a
simple animation tool that's scriptable.
And it uses Lua, whether
you love it or hate it.
It's not my favorite language in the world, but it
is small, fast, and clean, so it does does the job.
And there's really no limits to this.
Somebody's already done the hard work
for you on Flash. There is
a tool called Grapefrukt.
I don' know if you've
ever heard of it.
But it's a similar idea.
It's a set of action scripts.
You open up your scene, you drag in the
action scripts, you run, you just play your...
You hit play on the on the
thing, and while playing it,
it exports itself and creates
XML and image files out for you.
And all you'd have to
do is write the Unity side.
Sometimes though, even though,
if you're only given simple objects,
you can also, even without
an exporter and metadata,
you can still use
that in Unity itself.
So I'll just quickly talk about these two
because I think there's a bit of time.
So the Grapefrukt one is on GitHub.
You can go grab it if you want.
Just remember that it's
"grapefruit" with a "k," oddly.
And then, like I said, the other use case
you have is you've still just got images.
So I just want to show you this example too.
So back in Unity,
the example is
a friend of mine give me
all these images for the player
with all these frames, loose
images with no metadata.
And then I have, like, all the tiles.
I got all these with
just basic metadata.
So in this one, I
did the same thing.
Again, if you go and look at Tim's talk,
I created a scriptable object asset here.
And for that scriptable object asset,
let me open up the scripts itself.
So if I look at the static sprite.
So static sprite, same idea. I have
a class that's going to hold the data.
The statics sprite editor is exactly same.
It creates the menu item, creates the asset.
And then it basically does
all the mesh configuration.
It's all the same thing, again and
again, but just reoutputting it.
So this one allows me to basically
right-click anywhere I want.
I'll click in "tiles," "create," and have
created my own static sprite asset.
So I can add you know like,
level 2 titles if I want.
And then I can configure all
that, and so this is my class
with its own GUI. I can configure it.
I've already got one that's configured here.
And when I run this, then I can
immediately generate a scene.
So here's an example of a scene.
So I can take a block, duplicate
it, hold down control, snap, play.
And then still, I've just added
a block to the back, right?
So to make a 2D platformer game
is probably 20-30 minutes max.
And to write all the scripts, the
editor scripts, unscriptable objects,
even if you haven't done it before, it probably
won't take much more than a day to do.
So it's really, really easy, even if you
don't have any metadata, anything,
you can at least do it on the Unity side.
You can allow some ability to configure
it and make custom inspectors for that
on the Unity side, as well.
So basically, what I wanted to show you today.
I still don't know if we're out of time or not.
I wanted to show you that you can use
your 2D art tools and leverage them.
I'm a big believer in keeping people in
the tool that they're comfortable with.
If your artists is comfortable with
Flash, then let them stay in Flash.
Don't force them out of that.
If they're happy to do it in 3D Studio
Max or Maya, they can do that too.
You could easily write a 2D exporter
even out of Maya, right? You could write a
script to render all your sprite frames out,
put them into an atlas, generate the
XML and bring it straight into Unity.
There's no reason at all to
not create custom workflows.
So let each tool and each
person do what they're best at.
And the idea here is just to give meaning
to your assets where possible using metadata.
And if nothing else, do take
the leap into editor scripting.
It is the one reason why
Unity is really so successful.
Because no matter what skill level
you are when you look at Unity,
you see what you want in it.
And I don't know if a lot of people
realize, but Unity is written in Unity.
So when you're using the Unity editors,
sort of playing the game already.
And many of the windows and configurations
in Unity are also written in editor scripts
by our own team, internally.
So we use the same stuff
that everybody else uses.
So that's about what I have. I do believe we have a
couple of minutes for one, two questions, if that's okay.
One, two questions, if I have time?
No questions?
Okay, that's either a really
good talk, or I lost everybody.
Either way, at least we
ended up at an extreme.
Anyway, thank you very much for your time.
Enjoy your afternoon and have a pleasant day.
One one quick thing.
Could you guys just put the screen back?
If you would like some of these
files, you're free to email me.
Happy to share them with you.
My email address: brettb
at Unity3D dot com.
Very happy share that with you.
You can Skype me at bibbinator.
If you Skype me,
just say "I saw your talk"
because when "EvilGenius43"
wants to connect, I'm never sure.
Cool? And no Facebook please. Thank you.