Hello and welcome.
I'm going to talk a little bit about
how to protect your Android content.
I'm Erik Hemming from Unity Technologies.
Just a little quick background about myself:
I'm a developer set with Unity
Technologies based in Stockholm, Sweden.
I've been working with Unity for Android
for the last three years,
and I have a background as a game developer
making the Battlefield franchise games.
My main focus is on mobiles and game consoles. So, that is
Android, PlayStation mobile, PlayStation Vita and PlayStation 4.
So, this is a little bit about what we're
going to talk about today:
First, I'm going to do a little bit of an overview
of what is special with Unity on Android.
Moving on to Google Play
Licensing authentication.
Continue with application tampering detection.
A little bit about code obfuscation, and end with
encryption of "PlayerPrefs", scripts, assets,
and then hopefully a little bit of Q&A.
So, Unity on Android.
Unity on Android is essentially the big block
of the Unity run time.
We have the Mono VM, the virtual machine, which is
sort of the driving component for your script,
the content that you write, the game itself.
This all together is the application
that you sell on the Google Play store or similar stores.
From the OS level we have what is essentially
the Android, the Java, Dalvik virtual machine
and then the Linux Kernel.
So, if we look a little bit in detail we have
essentially the Unity runtime sitting in between
your scripts being run in
the Mono virtual machine, and
on the other side of Unity
we have the Dalvik Java VM.
So, you have essentially two different
virtual machines running separately.
To help with communicating between the
"C#.lang" and the "java.lang" we've created
"AndroidJavaObject" and a few other
classes
that then map to the Java counterpart, which
is like, in this case, a "java.lang.Object."
So, we have a few different objects
or few different types of classes.
We have the "AndroidJavaObject"
which maps to "java.lang.Object",
"AndroidJavaClass" which maps to "java.lang.Class",
"AndroidJavaRunnable" mapping to "java.lang.Runnable",
and in Unity 4.2 we added an "AndroidJavaProxy"
that maps to "java.lang.reflect.Proxy."
So, it's very helpful for implementing
Java interfaces on the C# side.
Essentially what all these structures are is basically a
way to map C# objects to "JavaObjects", classes or runnables.
We do that by name, we look up
the classes by name and instantiate them and
methods of and fields are handled through
reflection, which is essentially by name.
This is a small example of what the Java
code would look like and the equivalent in C#,
just to get an understanding of what
we're talking about here.
As you can see they're different,  but essentially
very similar in the key components of
the scripts, the code snippets here.
Starting off with authentication
with Google Play Licensing.
This is a system provided by Google,
and that means it's only available
for applications published on the Play Store.
It's essentially a verification of the purchase record
of an application, that is an online verification.
So, if the device is offline the verification will
essentially fail or you will not get any information from it.
There's example code provided by
Google, the License Verification Library or LVL.
It runs through the different aspects of how
the Google Play Licensing mechanism works,
but it's not a good solution for Unity apps on
Android because it's written completely in Java.
As such it could be a very
large part of your Java code
and that would essentially make it very
easy to find and then hack.
Just quickly running through the verification
flow with with Google Play Licensing.
The application sends a random number
to the Google servers,
and the Google server replies with a message and a
signature of that message back to the application.
So, the message itself is this purchase
record, a purchase status of the app,
this random number that we sent to the server
and a few other bits and pieces, like timestamps.
The signature is a RSA crypto signature
of the message
and the private key, which is
essentially only known to the Google server.
So, what the application then does is checks
the RSA crypto signature against a public key
and see that it matches the message itself,
and if it does then you can trust the
message to be valid.
So, as I said, this is an online check,
you can't do it when the device isn't
online, like having
an internet connection.
So there are a few ways that
you could deal with that.
You could require a constant
internet connection,
which is probably not a good idea,
unless it's a very online game,
because the game experience
will basically be
ruined if the user is flying, roaming
or otherwise without internet access.
So another way to deal with that is to do
checks only when you have a network connection
and in between trust the
application to be valid or
trust the user that he actually
bought the application.
Then essentially demand an online check every
week or every month
depending on your choice.
Obviously if the application
itself already has a few components
which require internet connection
it's a good idea to do this licensing
check at those points.
It could be like if you have
leaderboard stats, some kind of, you
know, synchronization with your own
servers.
So, one way to improve the
security of this verification
scheme is to use your own trusted
server to do the actual verification.
Again we start off doing the same scheme, the flow,
that we did with the client side verification.
We send some number, could
be a data request identifier, to the Google server.
The Google server replies with a message
and a signature back to the application,
but the application then takes the message and
signature and sends it to its own server.
The server then does the
verification and only if the
message and signature is
valid the server will then
reply with application data or the
application mechanism that was requested.
So, to ease a little bit of this
we've created a Unity plugin.
And it's written completely in C# or
almost completely in C#, there's
a small snippet in Java which is
embedded into the plugin itself and
the Java code is loaded dynamically.
So, it's very easy to
embed into an existing application
and it's also very easy to hide in
your C# or JavaScript code base
that you have in your game.
This is currently available on the Unity Asset Store,
and basically just click
download and its integrated.
The original project is hosted
on GitHub, so feel free to
fork the project there and
improve and submit any patches,
bug fixes or whatever back to us.
So, application tampering detection
then, because you want to see
if a hacker has done anything
to your application.
A hacker could... I mean the
simplest case would be removing the
licensing checks we already talked about,
a hacker would then have to change your code
in some way.
It could also be that the hacker wants
to change the code in the game to
gain some advantages, like making a
car drive faster.
In general it's an easy
way to determine if the application
has been hacked or changed or altered in some way.
So how you do this is, there are some different
aspects or different parts of the application
binary that you want to check.
First make sure that the application
is signed with your key,
since your key is your own private
key and a hacker could not possibly
sign the application with your key
if you keep it private.
Then make sure that the Java code is
intact.
Also make sure that the Mono class library,
which is sort of the Mono framework
that sits in the "mscorlib.dll", make sure
that that one isn't changed in in some way.
As if we do the licensing checks
that we talked about before,
those checks would rely on C#, the RSA encrypter
implementation in C#, and a
hacker could change that.
Make sure your own scripts are obviously
in a sort of good state.
That can be a little bit tricky, since you're
sort of checking what your actually writing.
So, a way to do that is to do the check in
Unity script for the C# part or vice versa.
If you have some native code or if
you want to make sure that the
Unity or the Mono code is intact
you could have some checks for that.
So, I'm gonna run through how you
could implement some of these checks.
This is what the APK signature check
would look like in Java,
it's probably familiar to at least some of you.
If we look at the the same code in Unity script,
using the
"AndroidJavaClass", "AndroidJavaObject" that
I talked about earlier, it would look like this.
As you can see if we move back
and forth between them
they are very similar, they are different
obviously, but they do
do exactly the same thing
but from Unity scripts.
Moving on to detecting changes in the Java code
or the Dalvik code which sits in the "classes.dex."
Here we do a little special trick.
We rely on the www class which is a standard
class in the Unity script API, the www class.
As on Android it has
the mechanism of reading
compressed files or compressed entries
inside the distribution archive.
So, we've essentially created a url
to the Apk entry classed as ."dex"
and then we read it with the www class,
create a crypto hash of that content
and check it, or in this case just
print it to the "log.cat."
A native library check, in Unity script
this time, would look essentially like this.
Get the native library directory
for the application
and read out the native library and do a
crypto check, crypto sum
of the file contents and
again print it to "log.cat."
Going to touch a little bit on code obfuscation.
Obviously we talk about code
obfuscation in two different spaces here.
We have the Java code in the Dalvik
VM which you can obfuscate with Proguard,
and you have the C# code or Unity script
code which lives in the Mono virtual machine,
and for that for obfuscation you can use
Obfuscar which is an open source project
available on Google code.
The code obfuscation is essentially a mechanism to hide
method and variable names, it does a little bit of
other things but that's essentially what it does.
The problem is that obfuscated
code is very much readable I'd say.
For semi-experienced hackers it's very readable
and in some sense this is a false
sense of security, I would say.
We're going to look a little bit at
the Java code here before obfuscation.
This is a small snippet of the
actual code in Unity that does
the playback of the fullscreen video.
If we take this code and obfuscate
it, this is what it would look like.
The method names, the
variables, the local variables, those
names have been changed, but all the
access points to the advert framework
are still there and they're still
very much readable.
So, it's still quite easy to
grasp what the code does.
If we then move on to encryption, if you want to
hide or otherwise make it tricky for a hacker.
So, if we start off with encryption of
the "PlayerPrefs".
The "PlayerPrefs", as you probably know, are a way to
store game specific information or game progression.
Obviously we want to protect the application
from simple cheating mechanisms,
like just changing how many gold
coins the player has received so far.
If the application caches some
mechanism of in app billing purchases
then we obviously want to protect that
as well.
In general it's good practice to hide, or otherwise
make it hard to find, this in someway sensitive data.
We do this by encrypting the key value
pair that you send into "PlayerPrefs".
So, we rely on the "PlayerPrefs", but we
only store encrypted data into it.
With this encryption it's good practice to use a user
specific encryption, not a device specific encryption key,
because the storage media for the
"PlayerPrefs" might be a cloud service.
So, the player might be playing the same game
on multiple devices.
Very quick, small examples here of how you could
do the sort of "SetString" part
of the "PlayerPrefs" encryption.
We start off with a key value in some
kind of secret code encryption key.
In this case we use a triple descriptor,
which is provided by the C# framework.
So, we transform the value into an
encrypted form
and we use a MD5 hash sum of the key and
then we store that in to the "PlayerPrefs".
This will make it not readable and you
definitely cannot change it either,
unless you change the secret,
if you know there is a secret code which would
require the hacker to decompile your whole
app, doable but still very much harder.
This is the equivalent of getting
the string back out.
So, we again in this case use a triple descriptor
that you decrypt, then return the decrypted value.
This is how we would interface with this encrypted
version of the ""SetString"()" / "GetString()" API.
We essentially just pass it the secret values, an
additional primer as a ""SetString"()" and "GetString()."
So moving onto encryption of scripts.
Why do we want to do that?
Well scripts in Unity, C# scripts and Unity
scripts, they are generally insecure,
they are not obfusticated, they are not
encrypted, we don't do anything to those
as part of the automatic building
process.
So, the hacker could read those.
It could be, as I said, gameplay could be altered
or the security checks that we have in
place, licensing check mechanism or
the tempering detection
code could be disabled.
There could also be code you want to
hide for some reason,
could be the in app building purchase
logic, could be something else.
So, how do we do this?
We start off taking the
scripts you want to hide
and we move them outside of Unity,
we're not compiling the scripts
through the automatic
compilation mechanism inside Unity.
We take them outside and compile
them outside manually.
We then run some kind of encryption on
them, could be symmetric or asymmetric,
on this "Script.dll", which is sort of the
managed dll which includes
the scripts you moved outside of Unity.
Move on to choosing a delivery mechanism, it
could be that you just want to embed the
scripts into your existing applications so
they are bundled with the original application.
Or it could be that you want to download
them on the fly from a server, so you could
change them after the
game has been released.
Or depending on the device or any other
type of mechanism you want to have.
Then at run time we decrypt the "Script.dll" in
memory, we don't store it to the device memory.
Then we load it through "Assembly.Load",
which is a C# framework API call.
So if we look at the different steps individually.
We start off with compiling the scripts outside
Unity and for that we need the Mono compiler.
So, we download Mono.
We compile the script, in this case "Plugin.cs",
with the GMCS compiler.
If you want to reference anything before
they use anything from the Unity script API,
you need to reference the "UnityEngine.dll" assembly
on the command line when compiling this "Plugin.cs."
This is just an example of what the
command line could look like.
Then we move on to encrypting the assembly.
One way to do that is to use OpenSSL.
The example here uses an RC2 crypto, encrypting
the "Script.dll" into encrypted ".bin" binary file.
While doing so it will output the key and the
IV necessary to decrypt the encrypted binary.
We then convert it to
a Base64 format,
raw text instead of binary, so we
can embed it in Unity as a "TextAsset."
If we look at this "Plugin.cs" or a part of it.
So, in this case I've added the
signature check again
as part of some important game class.
It's a good idea to not only have your
check in this "Plugin.cs", but also add some
parts which are
actually necessary to run the game.
If this sum important game class was responsible
for, for example, handling the physics
the code could then alter the physics simulation,
changing the parameters to the physics engine.
Making, maybe, the car slower if the
application is hacked or something like that.
Then we move onto decrypt
and run the assembly.
So, we have the text assets at the
top there, that's the assembly.
Which is a basics deforeign
coded encrypted assembly.
We then start off by converting it back
to a raw binary form.
We have the key and the IV from
the encryption step and then we again use the
crypto services available
in Mono to decrypt it.
Finally we load the
assembly up and
instantiate this important game class
to run the code we saw before.
Encryption of assets.
It might be necessary to encrypt assets
to protect them from tampering or maybe
you want to hide them in some way.
Assets in Unity is quite a loose term, it
could actually be a lot of different things,
not necessarily textures, meshes
or something like that.
It could be game logic controlled
from a ".txt" file for example
or Dalvik bytecode which is embedded as an asset.
It could be script code encrypted
or non-encrypted assembly.
It could actually be native code that you embed
inside your unit assets.
It could be essentially anything,
it's up to you what you want to put there,
but you might want to encrypt the assets.
How do we do this?
Create an "AssetBundle" of those secret assets.
Then we essentially use the same
mechanism as we did
with the encryption of scripts, but we
instead use an "AssetBundle.Unity3d" file.
So, we choose a delivery mechanism and then
we decrypt the "AssetBundle" in memory
and load it through the Unity script api function
called "AssetBundle.CreateFromMemory."
Some kind of conclusion here.
Be imaginative.
What I showed here is just to get you started,
there are many different ways of doing this.
However I want to point out that the APK integrity
checks that I showed before, they're very simple.
All the code snippets here
are not a lot of code, it fits into a slide
in a PowerPoint presentation, so
it's definitely not a lot of code.
It's so simple that essentially everyone should
have something like this in the replication.
As I said sensitive code must be protected.
There's no built-in protection in
Unity so you need to deal with that.
If you need to protect your sensitive
code you need to handle that case.
You can combine the different approaches
shown here or add new ones
or essentially pre-mute the way
you attack this problem.
Also a word of caution, don't spend
too much time on this.
The Android eco-system is, sort of,
built in a way that you will
most probably update your application
more than once.
So, you could then update how you deal with this
encryption or how you deal with
with the different mechanisms
of protection of your Android content for
each new release.
Which will then set back the hacker to square one,
where he will have to start from the beginning.
That was actually all.
A little bit quick
today, sorry about that.
So do we have any questions?
(Do you have any solution for
tech or teching devices?)
(For instance, Android rooting
application or in iOS that the device has been)
(jailbroken or something like that.)
There are ways to detect that, but I would actually
not recommend detecting that because I don't see
it as a problem in itself.
A rooted device still needs to, if you have for
example a Google Play Licensing verification check,
it will still need to talk to the Google
Play Licensing server.
So it doesn't really matter if it's
rooted or not, it still needs to do that
check and it will still fail if the
application was not purchased by that user.
So, I wouldn't care so much about that,
I don't think it's a big problem.
(So just encrypt the script like that?)
Yes, exactly.
There are many different reasons why
people want to root devices.
It's not always because they
want to to run cracked games
and most often it's not because they want run
cracked games, it's
because they want to get access to other
parts.
(Thank you.)
Anything else?
(Do you have any plan in
Unity to support)
(some of the techniques
described here?)
(Like script tampering
check in the Unity platform.)
You mean if we have anything like a
Unity plugin for this?
(Yea or future plans
for improvement?)
We will definitely make the slides here available,
so you can look at that.
Possibly create a small plugin of examples,
how to do the checks, that would make sense.
You mean if we are going to implement it natively?
No, I generally don't think that's a good idea.
As if we add the
encryption check
or application signature check into Unity, it
would be very easy for a hacker to hack all
Unity based applications
on Android.
Yea we could add it, but it would take five minutes
to create a crack that would crack all your games.
So, I don't think that's a good idea.
It would be a false sense of security
again.
Any other questions or general Android questions?
Oh we have some hands.
The Unity engine itself has a very small part
written in Java and that part is obfuscated.
So, any type of plugins that you add
to Unity in the Unity Plugins folder
would have to be obfuscated by you, because
we don't compile the Java code for you.
So, we don't obfuscate it either.
It's up to you if you want to obfuscate it.
When you provide it as a precompiled ".jar" you can also
provide it as a precompiled and pre-obfuscated ".jar" file.
Yes, we plan to make them available to the
public after our Unite Asia tour has ended.
Thank you.
You cannot load non-encrypted assemblies.
You cannot load assemblies on iOS, because on iOS
the assemblies are actually compiled
ahead of time into native code.
So, on iOS
everything is native.
Which means that if you want to load dynamic
code you need to load dynamic natively.
I'm not sure iOS supports that,
I'm not 100% sure.
It's not supported.
So that is a problem on iOS, that you
cannot load code dynamically in that way.
And the other questions?
So the place in the player settings that
you are talking about, inside the editor.
That was actually removed when we transitioned
from the 3. series to the 4. series.
So, it's actually removed.
So, to counter the removal
we added the plugin,
because we thought it made more sense to
provide a plugin that was written in C#.
So, that you could embed it anywhere in
your application and hide it wherever
you want instead of us doing
the LVL check for you.
As it made less sense to do that.
We think it's more secure if you can hide the
implementation somewhere in your application,
rather than us providing it sort of out
of the box, because it's easier to hack.
Does that make sense?
Anything else?
Well if you have any questions you
can just e-mail me on this address
or tweet something to me.
I'm happy to answer any questions you have.
I will also be around here a little bit after
the presentation if you want to ask something.
Thank you.