Hello everyone.
Welcome.
This is the Art Pipeline
Tips and Tricks session.
My name is David
and I'm a technical artist
at Unity Technologies.
The session today is gonna be a
little bit about how you can
trim valuable seconds off of the
various stages of the art pipeline,
and how cumulatively over the course of a project,
that's actually going to add up to big savings for you.
Before we start, just a
little bit about myself.
So I've accumulated 8 years now in game
development and architectural visualization
and in that time, I've worked on large-scale
architectural projects like this
for high-profile architectural clients.
I've worked in collaborative team
environments with 30-40 artists
and in total now, I've been
producing CGI for 15 years
since I was very, very young.
This is an example of the games
work I've done previously.
You might recognize these from Lego
Star Wars and Lego Indiana Jones.
But more importantly than
that, I was born in Wales.
And there's the Welsh flag.
Okay, an overview of how the
session is going to work today.
Firstly, I'm going to talk
about prototyping in Unity
and some techniques that you can employ
to hopefully speed up that process
Of course we're looking at the relative benefits
that this can offer you further down the pipeline
We'll talk about preparing your 3D
assets for taking into the Unity engine.
We'll talk about texture creation,
the actual process of importing into Unity
and also briefly, talk about
optimizing your scenes.
So I've just come off the
back of the Learn project.
If any of you have been to
the Unity website recently
then there's the new Learn section
and this is a collection of downloadable content
that people can take, installs itself into Unity
and then they can play with
assets that we've created.
We've also tutorialized this
and there's a range of video content
available that teach people how to
take these assets and takes
them through the process of
moving from a beginner to hopefully
somebody of an advanced level in Unity.
In approaching this, we've had to create a large number
of really quite high quality assets for distribution.
Much more so than if you're
actually producing assets for
a typical game environment, because
we're actually giving assets to people
that can take these assets, and they
can investigate them, play with them
so everything has to be of the highest quality.
Producing this stuff has also been
fitting around other work
commitments at the organization.
So in order to do this, workflow
optimizations have been required.
And these are just examples of the artwork
that we have created during the Learn process.
So, prototyping in Unity,
I propose that you should prototype thoroughly
when you're starting your projects. This is
going to help you to prevent abortive work.
If you're throwing away work, if you're producing
content is not included in your final product
then that's a 100-percent waste of time.
That work was discarded and
you've lost time unnecessarily
You need to identify areas of your process that can
be automated, and implement this automation early.
So if you can see repetitive tasks or areas
of your process that can be scripted
then I suggest that you should get that
scripting done early in the project
and reap the benefits later on.
Also worth bearing in mind is that small
savings throughout the art pipeline
add up to large overall gains by the
time you reach the end of the project.
It might be a few seconds
here, a few seconds there,
but after six months working on a project,
that's gonna add up to potentially weeks of time.
Okay, so the process that I'm proposing
for prototyping inside of Unity
is to first make use of Unity primitives
You've got various geometric
primitives that you can use to
lay out your levels and test
your mechanics early.
Also, I suggest maybe considering creating
your own custom shapes to test your gameplay.
Also, consider using the Asset Store.
And This is a great resource.
If you go to the Asset Store, it's available through
the web site, it's available through the editor
there are various tools out there that you
can use to actually help template and
create a rough rough prototype of your level
before you start going into full production
I'm not going to endorse a particular
product, but as an example
38 dollars can be very well spent on
a pack of premade template assets
I think you have to question the economy of
actually building the stuff yourself, sometimes.
Creating quality artwork is
a time-consuming process
if you go through this step of
prototyping your work thoroughly
then you're going to identify an
asset list that's 100-percent required.
Again, this boils down to the fact that
you don't want to be throwing away work.
Producing artwork for, particularly, next gen
applications is actually incredibly time-consuming.
So if you can ensure that what
you produce is actually required
then you can ensure that
not only is time better spent,
but by not throwing away
work, you're actually preserving
creative interest in the project, as well.
So we'll talk a bit about the "OBJ Exporter" now.
So if you go to wiki.unity3d.com,
search for "OBJ Exporter,"
then this is the script you find.
This is an editor script that allows you to
export .obj files from directly inside of Unity.
The exported OBJ that you get
is a good base to model over.
You can see for example here
that it's badly triangulated.
You know, that's not workable in-game asset.
But, what you have is a
good, vertex precise
base that you can snap to, when you're
actually going into your modeling phase.
This also helps you to identify
repeatable, modular pieces,
which you can distribute
amongst the team members.
So this is maximizing your
product bandwidth.
If you can take your work
early on, you can see exactly
what needs to be crated, because
you have the prototype layout.
You can then distribute this to team members.
You don't have to, sort of, guess who can do what.
You know you can just literally tick off the list
"this individual does this,
this individual does this."
And that's maximizing your production bandwidth.
So, this is a prototype level that we created
inside of Unity for the stealth minigame.
If you go to--again, if you go to the
Learn site, you can download this.
And this was created initially from a number
of wall panels that we modeled in Maya.
2 meters by 2 meters.
Using the standard asset controllers and
cameras, we're able to test the level design.
Both design, art, and the code apartments
could collaborate and agree on the design
in the same room, at the same time.
And this eliminates the problem you sometimes find
in larger collaborative environments where, perhaps,
somebody's made a decision at the design stage,
it's gone through code, code has approved it,
then it gets to art, and then you find that something
isn't feasible or, it could have been done better.
Okay, so with this specific example,
what we did was we took the prototype
that was created inside of Unity,
brought it into Maya using the OBJ
exporter, and we then rendered this out.
Rendered it out onto a light background.
And this is a good base to start sketching.
You know, taking things back
to traditional methodologies
is often the fastest way to iterate.
And this was actually produced on the train
on the way home from work one day,
by our content manager, Will Goldstone,
who sketched this.
It's very, very close to what
we actually ended up with.
Okay, so the next step was to
sort of refine it a little bit,
color code it, use the color coding
to help identify a flow to the level,
and then finally take this
to the concept stage.
Okay, so using this approach, we've manage to create a
very approved prototype very early on in the process.
And, we can assure that the art fits
a feasible layout from the outset
rather than having to refactor work.
This in turn reduces the need to refit
precise artwork at the modeling stage,
which is time consuming, again, in sort
of AAA or next gen production environments.
That artwork takes a very,
very long time to produce
and you can waste a lot of time.
So in summary, the benefits of
this simple prototyping approach
is that you get early agreement between
design, code and art departments.
There's less chance of time wasting by having
to reposition or restitch your models.
And then, you get earlier distribution of workload
amongst the artists, which means fewer dependencies.
So, preparing your 3D assets
now for bringing into Unity.
I propose that you should group
your objects by commonality.
So if you have a scene and it's composed
of objects that all pertain to the floor
or objects that all pertain to the walls, then
group those together into suitably named groups.
If you do this, when you bring
your scenes into Unity,
you're going to end up with
much neater hierarchies,
rather than recursive,
deep folder structures.
And this keeps your hierarchies
as flat as possible.
So if you find a suitable
taxonomy early in your project,
you can make use of the inherent organization
that you get from alphabetizing your work.
So for instance, if you go "kingdom,"
"species," "variant," in your object list,
Then you can create lists that are
very neatly grouped together.
And, I'd definitely suggest using
a renaming script to do this.
There are various, out there.
The renaming tools inside of Maya
and 3D Studio, as an example,
are pretty poor. So, make use of some
free alternatives that are available.
So, if you have scene that's composed of many
small objects, then this is inefficient.
Every object represents a draw
call, unless it's batched.
You can reduce the number of draw calls by combining
the smaller objects into sensible medium-sized chunks.
Massive objects, on the other
hand, represent a fill cost.
If you've got, say, a massive polygon
that's representing your floor,
and most of that isn't
seen by the camera,
then that actually represents a fill
cost still, because you have to
you have to have it redraw that, even
though it's not visible by the camera.
So we suggest splitting the
object into medium-size pieces.
This means that the inherent first-in
culling that you get from the camera
will actually not draw all of those polys where they're
not necessary, required, or are those texels.
When it actually comes to modeling your objects,
we also suggest equalizing your triangles
for better normal distribution.
So rather than having an object it's made of
polygons that are all bunched into the corners,
even though sometimes it might
be increasing your poly count,
you might get better results by adding some loops
to, as I say, equalize the triangle distribution.
If you imagine you have a
particularly massive polygon,
and you have one face, normal,
then if you're using
normal mapping techniques,
then the normals are
implicit across that surface.
So on a particularly large object, that means
you're going to start to lose smoothing precision
unless you subdivide.
So if you go to CreativeCrash.com,
there are plenty of alternatives out there.
Then you can find a range of
auto-exporter scripts.
And what these are, they're tools that will allow
you to export from inside of your 3D package
based on object
names, for instance.
And this saves a lot of manual naming and
manual tidying, which again, adds up to
quite a cumulative loss over
the course of a project.
Also, if you preserve the naming
conventions I suggested earlier,
then you're going to get always project folders
that are faster to navigate and just a bit neater.
So, in summary, when you're building your
3D assets, you want to avoid time wasting
by drilling through recursive hierarchies,
even to minimize the amount of
repetitive exporting and naming
when you go out saving files
to your operating system.
You also want to improve visual
quality with good modeling practice.
Okay, so texture creation.
So, texturing is a process
that is full of repetitive tasks.
Whether that's setting up a your Photoshop
documents, or applying filters, or sharpening,
sizing images for distribution, you know,
these are all obvious cases for automation.
I propose standardizing
your Photoshop documents
for easier collaboration
in larger team environments.
If you go team of 30 artists
and we're all producing work,
and distributing work amongst themselves,
every time you pick up a file,
you potentially have to spend 5 minutes trying
to figure it out and how it's constructed.
If you standardize your
Photoshop documents,
then you can eliminate this
this process of acquisition.
And this is only going to get worse as you move
into the next gen. That's even more assets,
and the problem becomes compounded.
So, the Master Builder is
a tool that I've created.
If you go to this web address,
I pretty much did a QR code,
I should get back to that.
And this takes you to my website.
I'll be giving that after the end, as well,
so if you didn't get it, then don't worry.
If you go to my website, you get
installation instructions for the tool.
And what the Master Builder is is it's
part of a suite of Photoshop actions
that help automate repetitive tasks.
It takes a range of source maps from
commonly used tools such as xNormal,
or the Algorithmic Substance Designer,
and it helps you to produce a standardized,
flexible Photoshop
document template.
Let me do a quick demonstration,
show you how it works.
Okay, so inside of Photoshop,
once you've installed the tool
it should appear here,
in the actions palette.
What you then need to
do is load up your maps.
So these are a range of typical maps you might
produce if you're working on a next gen asset.
Or current gen, these days.
So we have a cavity map,
we have a grayscale curvature map,
we have a tangent space normal map,
ambient occlusion,
UV layout,
vertex colors,
and also worldspace normals.
So when you're inside the tool, the first
need to do is to initialize the document.
And we do this because the maps
might come in a range of orders.
They've also potentially come from a range of sources,
so we don't know what they're going to be called.
And then by dragging these
into corresponding folders
we have a specific name that
we can work with later on.
So I'm just dragging this into the
named groups.
In which it goes in there,
and finally, cavity.
So this is all loaded up
and it's a lot quicker if you're
not using a track pad, obviously.
The second thing we need to do is to build the document.
I've actually got these on shortkeys, but for the
purpose of demonstration, I'm just going to hit play.
And what it is now doing is taking in the
information we've put inside of Photoshop
and it's splitting it open, and it's setting up this
this template document that I referred to earlier.
It doesn't look like much at
the moment. It's quite ugly.
But, with a little bit tweaking,
we can produce something that's half
decent as a base to start texturing.
So for instance, I can see here that the cavity map
isn't working too well. We're getting some jaggies,
so I'm just going to knock that back a little bit.
Similarly, the ambient occlusion is very, very faint.
So I'm just going to pump that up.
Also, what this produces is a range of
highlights using various techniques.
No one technique works every time,
so it's up to the artist to check them
out, and to blend accordingly.
So in this case, I'd say that this
highlight isn't working very well.
I can see from this that the curvature
highlights are barely working at all,
so we'll quickly adjust those.
And one of the advantages to this approach is,
again, related to the idea of standardization.
If you've got a larger team,
not necessarily everybody on the
team is at the same ability level.
So, some people want to know
about certain techniques.
Whereas, if you present a document to people
that has all these techniques already laid out,
it's up to the user then. They can play
with it, they can see what is achievable,
and blends to get the desired result.
Additional tool lists, you also get
your selections from your vertex colors,
and you also get the
worldspace normals.
So for instance, if you're going
to put dust on top of a surface,
then you could stick it
inside of this folder here,
and then you'd be blending dust just onto
the surfaces that face up in the world.
So as an example, this is one of
the finished documents we created,
and this probably represents
maybe 1:20's work.
So quite a short time.
If it has involved experimentation
from the from the outset,
if it had been passed to a more junior member of the team
who didn't necessarily understand some of the techniques
then it could have taken a lot longer.
But, because we have this
standardized document, you can produce a reasonable
next gen texture in a very, very short space of time.
As an example, the robot lab and the
stealth projects from the Learn website
involved the creation
of 433 unique textures.
I've worked out that on average, setting
up a photoshop document by hand
takes about five minutes longer than it
would do if you automate the process.
So, 433 x 5 gives you 2,165, which works
out to be four and a half working days.
So over the course of project, just by automating
the process of getting these textures set up,
that's almost a working week saved.
I also want to talk a little bit about image preprocessing.
So obviously, you can work inside of
Photoshop documents inside of Unity,
but there are certain advantages to working outside of Unity.
I propose that you should work in the
project folder set up by your 3D package
and use the image processor in Photoshop
to automatically apply actions to your images
before bringing them
into your Unity project.
And this offers some distinct advantages.
It allows you to flatten your Photoshop
documents to reduce your project size.
If you're using version control, and you're purchasing
a lot of assets, particularly hi-res assets,
in some cases up to a
gigabyte, 2 gigabytes,
then you can see how quickly you're
gonna flood your version control.
So I propose that you can flatten your Photoshop
documents prior to bringing them into Unity
in order to help
reduce this effect.
You can also normalize your histogram
levels. So with a specific example of
say, a specular mask, and you've got 8-bit precision,
that's 256 colors that are available to you.
If you're only using a few of those colors,
then you know, it's wasted precision,
it's wasted storage. So you're going to need
to think about normalizing your documents.
You can also apply artistic affects,
or sharpening to your images,
and you can reduce compression
artifacts with filter combinations.
And this is something I want
to talk a little bit about now.
So if you're working for mobile,
chances are you'll be using PVRTC,
and it's really good for crunching stuff.
But, it has some problems.
Using PVRTC, you can notice that banding
becomes visible in smooth gradients.
This is because colors within a certain range are
being grouped together to minimize the palette.
So the example here, you can see
that should be a smooth gradient,
but it splits into colors that
have been grouped by approximation.
So I propose that you can
use a high-frequency noise
on your textures to help
simulate the effect of dithering.
And this effectively tricks the PVRTC
compressor into preserving those colors.
So, I'll bring that back up.
So you can see here
on closer inspection, obviously,
there is this dithering pattern,
but from a distance, and certainly, in-game, it looks
a lot more acceptable than the image on the left.
And this is effectively through just
applying a high-frequency noise.
In summary,
preprocessing your images before importing is going to
allow you to reduce your version control sync times.
It's going to allow you to allow you
to apply stylized filter treatments.
It's also going to allow you to improve
compression results on mobile textures.
So I also want to talk about
importing assets into Unity.
So Unity was designed to work similarly to
Autodesk Maya in terms of its interface.
However, there are some
differences when it comes to 3D.
Scale is very important for bringing
in light-mapped objects and physics.
If you have a scene that is
particularly large, for instance,
then global illumination is
going to start to break down.
When it comes to lighting, Unity
expects a one meter unit.
So that's a hundred centimeters, whereas
Maya's default unit is one centimeter.
So therefore, we need
to scale the world.
A default scale factor of 0.01 is
applied because we assume that
there's a compatibility, also
there's a relationship between.
Unity and Maya, so therefore we
we have to default to something.
So, we default to 0.01.
Under the hand of 3D Studio Max, it
uses a default unit of one meter.
Again, Unity's default unit is a meter so therefore
we need to manually adjust the scale factor to 1.
In any case, you should
be doing a cube test.
And this is just literally
creating a Unity cube,
and then creating a one meter
cube inside of your package,
bring it in, then compare the two,
and it should be fairly obvious if you
need to adjust the scale factor.
Also important to consider is that Unity uses the
"left hand rule" for its cartesian coordinate system,
and this is the same as Direct X.
So, in the "left hand rule,"
positive X faces in the opposite
direction to right handed packages.
Maya, for example, is a
right handed package.
What's important to bear in mind is
that the world-space rotation around Z
is therefore going to be in the opposite
direction if you're eyeballing values.
So, if you're manually
copying values from Maya,
you're taking those into Unity.
Then you're going to start to experience
inverse rotations and other complications.
Also important to remember is that 3D
Studio Max uses swivel coordinates.
So, in Max, Z is
up, rather than Y.
Which, I know, is obvious, but it's just
something that needs to be highlighted.
Unity accepts .FBX, it accepts Collada, 3D
Studio, Maya binary, .DXF, and .OBJ files,
but it also supports the
embedded FBX standard.
And this means 3D texture assets can
be included with your 3D model file,
which is great in rapid prototyping situations
where, for instance, you might want to
minimize the time spent actually moving
documents around, bringing them into Unity,
but it can cause problems with cluttering your
projects. A lot of metadata comes with that.
For instance, as an example, if you're using version
control, this metadata is going to start to get quite ugly
and you're going to waste a
lot time filtering this stuff out.
So I'd say that in live production environments,
once you're past the prototyping stage, I'd definitely
consider using the standard FBX, rather than embedded.
So again, in summary, when you're bringing
stuff into Unity, you need to be aware
that Unity uses the "left hand
rule" for cartesian coordinates.
Always check your scale to avoid
problems with physics and light baking,
and use the embedded FBX
format for rapid prototypes.
And finally, I was going to talk
a little bit about optimization.
And this is a huge topic, so really I'm just going to
glaze over a few obvious techniques that you can use.
Now, I'm proposing that you
can use the Unity view modes
to troubleshoot and optimize
your poor draw performance.
And these are available from the
top left hand side of the scene view.
With the standard shaders
in Unity, we actually encode
the specular mask into the alpha
channel of the diffused texture.
And you can use this alpha view to check
your specular maps are displaying correctly.
Some cases, if you're using a Photoshop document, then
transparency on your base layer of your Photoshop document
can actually cause specular
to not come through at all,
and this is difficult to spot in RGB mode.
So moving it into specular mode is a very
useful way to troubleshoot this problem.
So if you look at the scene here,
if you had a specular mask
that wasn't coming through,
you'd expect the object to
be black or fully white.
And in the case here, we have fully white,
but that's for the windows, which have
full reflectivity anyway, so it's expected.
Overdraw represents a draw cost
without a visible on-screen result
except with the cases where
you're looking through an alpha.
For instance, you know, glass.
And this means that you are having to draw polygons
that aren't necessarily visible to the camera,
so you're wasting GPU performance.
So, if you move into overdraw mode, then
you get this additive color reproduction,
so that the lighter areas are representing
higher levels of overdraw.
And these are areas that
you need to address,
so you don't remove the polygons
from your model if possible,
or consider investigating techniques like
portaling, in order to reduce the draw distance.
And finally, I'm going to talk
a little bit about MipMaps.
So, mipmaps are obviously textures that
are storing a pre-computed subsampling,
which is effectively a smaller
version of the texture.
This is swapped at runtime to
ensure that the texture density
is appropriate to the
final on-screen resolution.
The mipmap view shows which
mipmap is currently being used,
and represents this
with a color scheme.
You get highest
in the foreground.
Ideally, you're looking for
highest in the foreground,
yellow in the middle, and
red in the distance.
If you're getting red in the foreground, this
means that your text resolution is too high,
and the low mipmap level is being used.
And this is a waste of memory because
you don't need that resolution.
If you're getting blue in the background,
this means that your textures
are likely to be low in resolution,
and they're going to be blurry when
you get in close to the camera.
So, using the inspector,
you can set an appropriate
maximum size for your textures.
With the example here,
it's been set to 1024,
but it's just indicating that that's the
value that you want to change.
You're ideally looking to
balance the scene view
to get a correct distribution
of blue to yellow to red.
In order to ensure that memory is not being
wasted, you're preserving visual quality.
So, in summary,
use the Alpha view to identify shaders not
correctly displaying their specular component.
Identify wasted GPU time with
the Overdraw view mode.
And, ensure optimal texel density throughout
your scene using the Mipmap view mode.
And that's it.
Any questions?
It's question time?
Could we get a microphone to this guy?
Just yell.
(Hi.)
Hiya.
(Just for clarification, you said the gradient, like from,
was it red to yellow to blue, or blue-yellow-red?)
(Is that from foreground
to background, in order?)
So you want to see progression
from blue to yellow to red, ideally.
(So blue would be
in the foreground?)
Blue is the foreground, yellow in
midground, and then red in distance.
(Okay, thank you.)
Anyone else?
Okay, thank you.