皆様、ようこそこんにちは。
Welcome, everyone.
本日は「バタフライエフェクト」というムービーについてのプレゼンを通じて DirectX 11 グラフィックス機能を紹介します。
I will be doing a presentation on a movie called "Butterfly Effect,"
that will show off some DirectX 11 graphic features.
それでは自己紹介から。
A bit about me, first.
私の名前はアーランドで、
My name is Erland
ユニティ テクノロジーズのスウェーデン オフィス所属です。
and I'm from Unity Technologies' office in Sweden.
主にそこでデモに関連した研究関連の商品を扱ってます。
What we mainly do there is demo-related
and research-related products.
言い換えると Unity を様々なエリアでテストを行なって
That means basically that we test Unity in various areas
改善できるところを探してます。
and see where we can find possibilites for improvement.
私はAAA出身です。
I come from a AAA background.
Unityに入る前はEAで働いていて
Previously to Unity, I worked at Electronic Arts
DICEを仕事場にして、バトルフィールドおよびミラーズ エッジのフランチャイズに関わってました。
specifically at DICE, where I worked on the
Battlefield franchise and Mirror's Edge.
それでは、短い映像を紹介します。
So, I will bring you through the short film.
早速見てみましょうか。
We will watch that.
後で見たい方にはYoutube動画も利用できます。
It's also available on YouTube if you want to see it again.
次に様々なグラフィックス機能およびその未来の可能性について
Then I will walk you through the various
graphic features and possibilities
DX11 を通して実現できたことを紹介して、
that made us able to do this through DX11,
さらにUnityの中でのグラフィックス実現についてデモをします。
and demonstrate the graphic capabilities directly in Unity.
では出来るだけリアルタイム デモをして
So I will do more like a real-time demonstration of this
この動画作成に特化して開発されたUnity ベータ版を使用します。
using the beta version of Unity that we developed
specifically for the purpose of this movie.
ではムービーを再生しましょうか。
So, let's watch the movie.
これで終わりですね。
That's it.
どうですか、楽しんでもらえましたか？
I hope you enjoyed it.
ムービーで使われたグラフィックス機能をご紹介していきましょう。
So now I will bring you through the
graphic features that were in this movie.
まずは制作過程について。
The production, a bit about that.
リアルタイム再生のショートフィルムで2分半の映像は
It's a real time short film, about
two-and-a-half minutes long
全て Unity を使用して作成してます。
and it's fully using Unity.
先に申し上げたとおり研究プロジェクトから生まれました。
It was done, as I said earlier, as a research project.
これは Unity, Passion Pictures, NVIDIA の共同製作です。
This is a collaboration not only between
Unity, but Passion Pictures and nVidia.
Passion Pictures の CG アーティストはアートのほぼ全てを扱いました。
Passion Pictures were the CG artists that
did almost all the art for this.
ピーク時において、25 名 の CG アーティストと
It was, at its peak, about
twenty-five CG artists and roughly
およそ 5 名のフルタイムプログラマが協力しました。
five full-time programmers.
Unity, NVIDIA のプログラマです。
These programmers were from
both Unity and nVidia
Passion Pictures は純粋にアーティストのみでした。
but Passion Pictures only supported with artists.
製作期間は全体で 14 週間。
The total length of the production
was about fourteen weeks.
最適化および調整にさらに時間をかけたのは
We added some additional time on that be able
to polish and basically optimize it
アーティストがリアルタイム映像が未経験のためです。
because these artists had no prior
experience with any real time film.
プロジェクト全体で 40 GB のデータがあり
In total, the whole project is about 40GB of data
容量の大部分はアニメーションのポイント キャッシュ データです。
and mainly the biggest chunk of that goes
into point cache data for the animations.
見て分かるとおり精巧な クロス (Cloth) 物理挙動が含まれてます。
As you could see, there were some
elaborate cloth physics happening there.
ここはあまりにクロス (Cloth) のレイヤーが多いため、事前シミュレーションが必要で
It's actually pre-simulated because
there were so many layers of clothes
さらに高速な動きがあったため選択肢はない状況でした。
and they were moving so rapidly
that we didn't have any alternative.
このときアーティストは事前シミュレーションしたクロスを完全に制御できました。
It also enabled the artists to have full
control over the pre-simulated cloth.
容量のもうひとつの大きな部分はライトマップです。
Another large part of that is the light maps.
ほぼ全てのシーン毎に別のライトマップが使われてます。
Almost each scene has a separate set of light maps.
その理由は、基本的に
This was because we wanted to be able to
ショット毎に別のライティングの向きや別の大域照明が必要だったことです。
have different lighting directions and different
setups of global illuminations per shot, basically.
プロジェクトではキャッシュサーバを最大限に活用したことも付け加えます。
Also, I should note that we were using the
cache server for this project quite heavily.
このプロジェクトの最大のゴールは DirectX 11 を実装して
During this project, one of our biggest
goals was to implement DirectX 11
Unity の 64 ビット エディタが大量のデータを実際にハンドリングすることでした。
and to have a 64-bit editor of Unity to actually be
able to handle all these large quantities of data.
それではこのプロジェクトのゴールについてもう少し。
So our goal for this project.
この CG スタジオのオフライン ツールを追求して学習し、再現したうえで
We wanted to explore and study and mimic
the offline tools from this CG studio
Unity 上でどのように動作するかみて、
and basically how they worked, in Unity
そこから学ぶことが目的でした。
and study that.
ハイエンドのデモとして Unity を最大限にストレステストして、
This was intended to be a very high-end demo
that stress-tested Unity to a great degree
ひとつは製作期間できるかぎり短くすること、
both by having a very short production time
もうひとつは大人数のアーティストが同時にプロジェクトで作業をすること、を意図してます。
and having a large amount of artists
working simultaneously on this project.
さらにアーティストにとって、馴染み深く直感的なワークフローにして
Also, we wanted to create a very familiar and intuitive workflow
for these artists that reminded them very much of
普段使い慣れている 3D Studio Max, Maya, XSI のネイティブ プログラム、
what they're used to in their native programs
such as 3D Studio Max, Maya, XSI,
あるいは何らか別のシミュレーションやエフェクトのプログラムに近い操作感を再現する期待もありました。
or any kind of simulation program or effects program.
当時、Passion Pictures はリアルタイム映像やゲームはまったくの未経験でした。
Passion Pictures had, at the time, no experience
whatsoever doing real-time film or games.
Unity を短期間で学んだのですが、学習速度は早いものでした。
So we had to quickly teach them Unity,
which they adapted to very fast,
また、そこから改善できるワークフローのフィードバックも得られました。
and from that also have them feedback to
us what workflows we could improve on.
映像の主な目的は高品質なムービーを作成して
The main goal of the film was to
produce a very high-quality movie
オフライン レンダリングを再現することでした。
that would resemble what you could do in offline rendering.
ところどころでアーティストは比較を行なって、
At points, these artists could
actually compare their results
3D プログラムと Unity とで見比べて同じ結果が得られるか確認できました。
in a 3D program and in Unity and they
would get very similar outcomes.
これが映像ターゲットの例です。
So here is a visual target.
これはアート ディレクターおよび Passion Pictures のメイン ディレクターの共同により作成されてます。
This was done by the art director together
with the main director at Passion Pictures.
これは映像の最終的なあるべき姿としての最終ドラフトでした。
This was their final draft basically of
how the feel of the movie should be.
現実的な描写というより漫画チックで、エキセントリックです。
A bit more cartoony and eccentric, rather than realistic.
Passion Pictures has a long experience
doing a very niche kind of style
and a bit more imaginative.
So this this kind of landed right in their area of expertise.
Here's another one.
This shot actually never made it into the film, but
it still is very typical for how we wanted it to look
with very vibrant colors and a more stylized sense.
So the concept itself, what Unity wanted to do with this,
was to have a style that actually targeted our end-users.
We didn't aim to have any space marines
or stereotypical characters in this film.
We wanted it to be colorful
and slightly surreal.
It was fun to push the limits of
what's real or not and very extreme.
Also we wanted this movie to not
just be a real-time movie but a movie
that actually was watchable for people who
had no understanding of real-time film.
So there was not supposed to be any game resemblance,
or any connections with games whatsoever.
Talking a bit about DirectX 11
I'm not a programmer, so I can't go into the
specifics, but there have been talks already here
that have touched on DirectX 11.
Kuba Cupisz
made a talk yesterday where where he addressed
DirectX 11 specifically from a programmer's perspective,
but I can brush on it a little bit.
For those of you who don't know, this is a collection of
Windows multimedia APIs that are used mainly for games.
DirectX 11 opens a much broader visual scope
for graphics by using the GPU more heavily and
providing much more fidelity to the art.
It also offloads efforts from the programmers,
they find easier solutions to do
very complicated things,
and gives artists the ability to use procedural
techniques that are really computed fast
and are really practical, both in
terms of memory and rendering time.
So DirectX 11...
Our test case was done before Unity 4,
but it was transferred into Unity 4.0.
Since then it's been available.
So, what did it exactly enable us to do?
We got physically-based, energy-conservative
shaders on skin and eyes.
This is related to materials.
We have hair rendering with tesselation
for very fine strands of hair
and on slippers as well.
We were able to do full-screen
post-effects, massive amounts of those
that corresponded very well to what a CG studio
expects to do in post-production.
And we were able to add some volumetric effects,
like that explosion at the very end.
A bit about the physically-based shaders.
Fundamentally, that is a material that just follows
the laws of physics with very predictable results.
What to gain from that is not only a very realistic
material, but also but it's also a material where
the artist cannot really fail.
It requires less tweaking and less cheating
to achieve a very realistic material.
Also, it's energy conserving.
Basically, light energy is distributed between the diffuse
reflection and refraction so it's balanced.
This happens automatically and this can be
very tricky to do this manually in a material.
So you save a lot of time by using this
and it's much more intuitive.
This is a material that we got inspiration from.
Mental Ray.
This is a widely used one in the movie industry.
We studied it quite closely and tried to adapt it
into a real-time version that worked fine in Unity.
So the bottom line for this shader is: we
use it on almost everything in this movie
and it can be used for almost anything. Anything
that is a hard surface material is able to have this.
That puts exceptions on organic materials, of course,
and also such things as skin and eyes.
So I will demonstrate this in Unity.
Let's see...
Let me open up the file...
As you can see, the project has a lot of files.
Here we are.
What you can see here at the
bottom is a sequencer that we
constructed for Passion Pictures to
be able to scrub through shots
and be able to work directly
in Unity with that
as they were animating or setting
up various camera angles and such.
If I show the material...
Let's see...
If I pick this one, for example...
Sorry about that.
I can pick this one.
Let me hide some of the more irrelevant things for this.
Here we go, here's a simple example.
As you can see,
for those of you that are familiar with
material inspector, we made some changes.
We made a custom material inspector for this to be able to
fit all the properties that were necessary for this material.
Apart from having just a simple diffuse,
you're able to adjust roughness.
I don't know if it's visible, but
that basically determines how rough
the surface of this material is.
We have reflection, so we could basically
adjust the specularity, as everything else.
Nothing really new there.
Reflectivity amounts so we can make it very reflective.
The reflectivity is taken from real time
reflection probes that are placed in the world.
Let's see if I can bring this back up.
Glossiness.
So this was achieved by basically
stepping through different mipmaps
of the cube map reflection.
So you could have it very shiny, or not.
Fresnel
or BRDF (bidirectional reflectance distribution function),
as it is referred to as here
and two passes of normal maps that were
basically applied onto each other and merged.
Let me continue.
So as you can see here,
these are two comparisons that we did.
On the left side we have the original
Maya shader, the Mental Ray shader.
On the right side, you can see the results
from the Unity adaptation of that shader.
These are basically spheres that we rendered
in in an array with different amounts of
reflectivity, specular and other properties.
Skin Rendering.
This was actually--
One second, sorry...
The skin shader was derived from
the Mental Ray-inspired shader.
Since it wasn't able to do organic materials,
we tweaked it to actually do that.
As well as with the Maya shader, this one
also is very intuitive for the CG artists.
Basically they have all the parameters that
are available in their 3D program.
That includes having three different skin layers, two
specular layers, and backscattering on the skin.
In some scenes you can see the sun
hitting the character from behind.
Then the ears, which are the thinnest
pieces of skin, are glowingly red.
That's basically the translucency
as the sun is penetrating the skin.
Instead of using the DirectX 11 tesselation, we actually
had a Catmull-Clark subdivided solution instead.
The character artists are much more
acquainted with this kind of tesselation
and we were able to get much more
identical results by having that.
I'm going to demonstrate the skin as well.
Just a minute...
Okay, let's open up the...
So I can find a good spot to look at skin.
Here he comes flying.
They're about there...
There.
Let's see if we can find him now in this shot.
He's already been tweaked a bit, so
he's a little bit green at the moment.
In that case if we adjust the
greenness back to a yellow color.
And close this so we can see better.
Give him a bit more yellow tint.
Sorry.
I can increase or decrease the different influences
from the various layers of skin,
change their color,
tweak normals if that's necessary,
the amount of blurriness of each layer,
and add AO (ambient occlusion) on top of that.
I don't think it's very visible unless it's in closeups.
Adjust the amount of backscattering on the skin,
how much it should saturate when
the sun is actually hitting it,
reflectivity amounts.
So, let's see if we can--
Sorry.
If we can decrease or increase that...
As you can see on the tip of the ear,
it's a little bit red and orange.
That's the backscattering that's showing there.
Let's see if we can bring that up.
I guess it's not visible on the screen.
Of course this one has, just like the Mental Ray
shader, two normal maps that are overlapping, basically.
One that gives the detail in the skin, the pores
and one that supplies the bigger details,
such as a wrinkles and creases.
To continue, next is hair and tesselation.
We use that for three
different characters.
There is this old grandma that is driving the car,
there is the the bus driver,
and also the main character.
Apart from that we had a different variation
of the hair generation on slippers.
So, using DirectX 11 we were able to
generate hair and render it with tesselation.
This basically allowed us to
sculpt any kind of hairstyle.
The hair was placed in Unity by adding
emitter meshes to the character.
That was a separate mesh that just determined where, on what
location, and which faces of the character should have hair.
We applied it to the top of the hair
of the main character and eyebrows.
The grooming of the hair, the style...
the hairstyle...
the bedhead as he wakes up.
His hair is pointing in various
directions and there's another
set of hair when he's going at full speed when the
hair is actually animated backwards and moving.
This was done in in a 3D program.
Specifically for this it was XSI,
where the character artists were able to set
up guide hairs to sculpt the hair as they liked.
So I will show the hair for you.
Okay.
Bring back this, as flying through the alley.
Good thing the rope wrapped around his leg.
Stop right there.
Now look at him.
I'll close this.
He's a little bit shinier now since
we just changed the material.
So a close-up.
As you can see we cheated a bit with the shadows of the
hair by just painting it directly into the diffuse map.
That worked quite well.
We had a special solution for some close-ups where we just made
up a variant of the skin that was missing the painted shadows.
So this hair was able to LOD.
There were levels of detail of the hair depending on
the distance that were determined automatically.
So it goes from very detailed hair to
thicker and fewer strands of hair.
You can adjust the length.
Clumping, that's the grease in the hair that
basically ties the strands of hair together.
This causes a much more natural look.
Various parameters such as noise,
to create a bit of irregularity
and wind animation speed.
That's the movement that's happening
in the hair as he's going down the hill.
There's no advanced simulation for that hair,
it's basically just noise displacing the tesselation,
the tesselated surfaces.
You can play a bit with with the hair color I
think, to get an understanding of what we have.
We added a fake rim to it.
Let's see if I can demonstrate that so you can see.
Along the edges, there's a bit of red.
This rim helped us create fake lighting for the
hair that gave a bit more of a fuzzy look to it.
Here we go, now you can see how it's...
That's basically just scratching the surface
of all the things we can do with the hair.
Now I'll show you how it worked
with the fur version of this also.
This is the scene where he's going
down the hill and flying off.
Let's rewind and have a look at this.
Look at the slippers.
Close this window to get a bit more space on the desktop.
This is how they are very close up.
You get somewhat similar types of shading as we
could do with physically-based material
and some parameters basically just to control the hair.
So there's length, and that could make them very fuzzy.
Or...
Control the clumping of those as
well, so you could get thicker hair.
Color, some nice pink ones.
And adjust the specularity,
the shine on the hairs, basically.
Going back to this,
The post-effects.
As I mentioned earlier we had a lot
of post-effects applied to this
I will shortly demonstrate how many there were
and what they actuallly did to the final shot.
The big things that we added to
this were depth of field and bokeh.
That was specificially due to the
requirements of the CG studio.
This was combined with an anti-aliasing
that was very DoF, depth of field, aware.
So it worked very nicely together
with the character and the hair.
We were able to have depth of field
blur behind the hair of the character
without any obvious interference or artifacts.
We had two layers of high dynamic range
bloom placed on top of each other.
One worked basically like a bit of tone mapping and the
other one gave the glows around specular highlights.
We had an RGB channel noise and grain,
which is not something extraordinary
but it was interesting to see that
these artists were using.
Instead of having a global noise they were working with
the noise amounts differently in the various RGB channels.
On top of that we added color
correction, the grading
which we did with 3D lookup tables.
So let me quickly demonstrate this.
So you may recognize this scene.
He is again flying,
this time through a diner.
So this is how it looks without the particle effects.
Let's play it.
I will do a breakdown now of the various post-effects
and you will be able to see how it was added on this.
As you can see in this inspector these are all the
different types of components that we added on top.
Camera jitter was something that we
added to camera at a very late stage
because it gave a bit more of a documentary
feel to it, a bit more lively camera.
It's basically just randomly
offsetting the camera a little bit.
Hardly noticeable but still gives a
much less artificial camera movement.
Noise and grain,
but I guess that's not very visible
up there on this big screen.
There was an overlay
light bleeding simulated with just a plain
texture that we put on top that was
supposed to look like light actually
hit through the camera lens.
The grading,
the bloom,
second pass of bloom,
the vignette, basically the darker areas
around the frame.
Anti-aliasing,
depth of field,
screen space, or in fact we used
horizontally-based ambient occlusion,
and blur.
So this is how the shot looked completely untreated
and this is how it ended
up looking in the final.
Going back to this,
we had some volumetric explosions in the end.
We initially thought about doing this with fluids,
but it just proved to be slightly too expensive
and a bit too difficult for us to actually control.
Instead, we went for a distance
field-ray marching variant.
This is just a volume rendering technique that is able
to process volume data instead of surface data
like a ray caster does.
On top of this, as you can see in the
bottom right there we had volumes.
These volumes were given
its surface, this pyroclastic surface
by offsetting the various parts of the
original sphere with Perlin noise.
The shade, or the color, the value of the
surface was based on the displacement distance.
So the further the distance was from the center of the
fireball, or the sphere, the darker and grayer it became.
So at the very center it's warm and orange
and it gradually gets darker and grayer.
This gives a smoky effect.
These volumes unexpectedly worked
very well with world geometry.
They fit in nicely and we were able to wrap
them around corners of houses or buildings
or fit the character to blend
very nicely with them or busses,
as in this shot.
Also the particles work very fine with that.
Initially we added smoke particles
that were combined with this effect
but the end and we ended up not using them because
they didn't add as much as we anticipated.
Also, I should note that this effect could could be lit
and therefore also have ambient occlusion added to it.
So we've got a very defined surface to this
I will demonstrate how they appear.
Right here...
Just a minute...
This is the effect.
Boom!
He flies off.
There's the fireball in the background.
So I will show how this is made.
So let's get rid of everything
and then let's pick out the effect.
Actually, let's bring it back, in fact.
The user is able to control this by
just applying it to primitive spheres.
It works basically like this.
This was a sphere originally
I think if you look at it through a
wireframe it's not even rendered
as it's not typical geometric data.
Then we could scale it, I think.
Or not, possibly.
That's basically how that worked.
I'm running out of time here, so I will skip
these examples that I added towards the end.
But feel free to contact me and I
will show them to you after this talk.
If you're interested in seeing
them, I will be around for a while.
Thank you to everyone involved both
from Passion Pictures and nVidia
I hope you enjoyed the talk and, as I said, feel free to get in
touch and I will explain more about the procedure for you.
Thank you.