Hello, it's very good to see all of you here today.
My name is Na'Tosha Bard.
I am a lead software developer at Unity.
Originally I'm from America, but about three years ago
I moved to Copenhagen, Denmark to work for Unity.
Now as a software developer for Unity, I
work on a lot of many different things,
but the reason why I'm here today
is because i'm one of the Linux
platform developers.
And i'm going to talk to you about Linux publishing in Unity 4.
This presentation is going
to be probably a bit shorter
then the rest that you've seen.
I'm gonna first cover a
brief introduction to Linux
for those who may have not used it
before and are wondering what it is.
Then we're going to talk a bit about about the
state of gaming on Linux
in the past and today.
And then finally I want to talk specifically
about the Linux export feature in Unity 4.
So I would actually like to get to know
you a bit better before we begin, so I'm
going to ask a couple of
questions to the audience.
First of all,
how many people in here personally
use or have used Linux, could
you just raise your hand?
OK, that's a higher number than I
expected. So that makes me very happy.
Second of all, how many of you either
already are or are planning to
publish your game onto
the Windows or Mac
desktop, in addition
to any other platforms
that you already are publishing to
So let's get started.
Now first of all, what is Linux?
This may be a bit redundant for
those of you that have used it before
but they are some people I could see
in the audience that haven't
so I will cover this section.
Linux is a Unix like operating system
and it's the third most popular operating
system in the world behind Mac OSX.
The defining characteristic of
Linux is the Linux kernel.
And all of the software on
top of the Linux kernel
can come from anywhere
and be developed by anybody.
The main user space tools and applications
come from what is known as the GNU project.
The most unique characteristic of Linux
is the fact that it's open source.
In fact it is it is one of the most prominent examples
of free and open source software collaboration.
And this is one of the reasons why, I personally,
am very, very passionate about Linux and have been
a Linux user for many many years. Long
before I ever came to work for Unity.
The fact that it is open source means
that the underlying source code
can be used, modified, or distributed
either commercially or non-commercially
by anyone under an applicable license.
Now this open source nature of Linux
has led to the creation and distribution
of a huge number of Linux distributions.
Some of the most popular of these distributions
are represented here on this side
You can see distributions like Ubuntu,
Debian and Fedora and several others.
A Linux distribution will be a packaged
installer or a live boot disk consisting
of the Linux kernel and usually a set of
libraries and utilities from the GNU  project.
Graphics support for desktop distributions
is provided by the X-Window system.
Some distributions are commercially backed,
such as Ubuntu, Red Hat and openSUSE,
and other distributions are community driven.
Obviously both commercially backed and community
driven distributions have been quite successful.
Linux has been ported to more platforms
than any other operating system.
And distributions exist not only for the
desktop but for servers for mobile
phones, for embedded systems
and many other platforms.
Many of the devices of course that are around you
everyday are actually running Linux internally,
but the environments that are most interesting for
gaming are the desktop and server platforms.
So that's what we'll focus on for
the rest of this talk.
One other bit of exciting news
for Linux is that recently
China announced Ubuntu as its
state endorsed operating system.
Canonical, which is Ubuntu’s
commercial backer
is working alongside the Chinese ministry
of industry and information technology
to bring a suitable Ubuntu version to China.
So that's just what I believe to be an interesting
thing to note about the
state of Linux today.
And now I want to cover just a few technical
facts about Linux for those who may not not know.
The Linux Kernel is written in
the programming language C.
Probably most people have heard that
the kernel was originally released by a man
named Linus Torvalds who is from Finland,
but due to the open source nature of Linux,
he is only the author of about 2% of
the kernel code now. The other 98% has been
written by open-source contributors around the world.
Linux is much more popular in
the server space, most definitely,
but desktop usage is growing steadily.
For rendering Linux uses
OpenGL just like Mac OSX,
while Windows of course uses is Direct3D.
One interesting characteristic of Linux is that
server-based installs often
have no GUI whatsoever.
This is relevant for gaming because that
means applications that were designed
to run specifically on a desktop are in many cases not
going to be able to run out of the box on the server.
And then another interesting, what I believe to be
an interesting fact about Linux is that it is run on 90% of the
world's supercomputers.
One of these supercomputers is owned
by a company called Weta Digital.
Weta Digital used their Linux cluster which
was running, I believe, Red Hat Linux
for the creation of the film Avatar.
So we're seeing recently how Linux is becoming more and
more important in the area of digital content creation.
So now that we've had a brief overview
and an introduction to Linux itself,
let's go over a very brief
history of gaming on Linux,
and then we'll talk about the state of gaming on Linux
today and how that is relevant to Unity developers.
Historically, Linux hasn't been seen as what we
would think of as a serious gaming platform.
It shared a lot of history with
the Unix gaming scene,
and commercial support for Linux started in
the early nineties with the release of Doom.
Although we saw a steady
stream of open source games
and a few proprietary titles released over the
years, it's taken a long time for Linux to start
being seen as a platform
worth targeting.
There are a couple of reasons for why
this transition has happened so slowly.
In particular their are a few notable
stumbling blocks that I will discuss briefly.
The first one is a historical lack
of good graphics drivers.
Several years ago all graphics drivers
for Linux had to be developed by reverse
engineering the proprietary drivers for Windows.
These drivers in many cases didn't work
very well, particularly for gaming.
Not only because they would have a lot of bugs
and a lot of instabilities, but because they
couldn't take full advantage of the features
of the graphics card in the same way that
a proprietary driver would be able to.
Now luckily for us, this
situation has changed,
and we now have proprietary
drivers being supplied directly by
AMD, Intel and Nvidia--the predominant
graphics card manufacturers.
Another common historical
stumbling block
is a a concern that
has always existed
about supporting a large
number of Linux distributions.
They've always been concerns,
even within Unity technologies,
about how it could actually be possible to
support so many different Linux distributions.
You can see here a graph of the split
of Linux distributions up through 2011.
So this data is about two years old,
but you can see a huge number of Linux
distributions that are still active today.
For those who don't know, Linux distributions
can generally be grouped
into three groups, and
the difference between
these three groups
revolves around the package
management system.
And when I say package management system,
I'm speaking about the system that is
used for actually
bundling and distributing
and installing
applications and tools.
This graph shows that we have
three primary groups
of Linux distributions.
One, which is shown on the top are Debian
based distributions and for package management
they use what we call "deb packages."
The bottom group are what we call "Red Hat"
or "rpm based" distributions,
and for package management
they use rpm packages.
And then the middle group are what
we call source based distributions,
and the way that these distributions
solve the problem of package management
is by downloading, compiling and
installing all applications and tools
directly from source. So we see
a large number of distributions,
and there are some differences between them.
But the good thing here, is that these various
distributions are all fundamentally the same.
They will run the same Linux kernel,
they're all going to have a C++ runtime,
and they will use X11 for input
and window management.
So even though it looks like a very
difficult problem to solve,
the problem is not actually
as big as one would think.
Another likely reason that Linux hasn't
been targeted as a serious gaming platform
is a concern that Linux users won't
actually pay for commercial games.
This has always been a concern and
it's also a never-ending cycle,
because historically very few commercial
vendors have brought games to Linux and so
we've had very little data
to indicate whether or not there actually
is a commercial market for Linux.
Because of that people have not shipped
more games for Linux and then we
still can gather data and this is just
continued over the years.
In the years past we have seen a few games
that were shipped commercially for Linux
turn out to be very, very successful.
And more recently initiatives like the
Humble Indie Bundle
have indicated that the demand for
commercial games on Linux is growing and
it's not as insignificant as we once thought.
so knowing this, let's talk about the
current state of gaming on Linux.
In 2012, two significant things
happened for gaming on Linux.
First of all, Valve announced
Steam support for Linux,
and second of all Unity announced
Linux runtime support.
Steam support for Linux was
announced in July of 2012
and Valve shipped a beta
client in December of 2012.
Official support for Linux
in the Steam client
was released in February of this year,
so not very long ago.
Linux runtime support in Unity
launched with a game called Rochard and Humble Indie Bundle 6.
Since then games like Splice and Snuggle Truck,
which are some well known Unity games,
have followed in later Humble Indie Bundles.
And other Unity games for Linux have shown
up on other distribution platforms as well.
I will go over the current set of distribution
platforms available for Linux in a minute.
In 2013, Linux continues to grow.
This year a minimum of fifty million computers
will ship with Ubuntu Linux pre-installed.
Linux market share on the desktop is
something that is really hard to estimate.
it's definitely small, especially compared
to the market share of Windows,
but it is growing.
From 2008 to 2009 alone, Linux
market share calculated
via web browser analytics,
rose from 1.3 to 2.2%,
but the browser-based estimation is primarily
a North American based web measurement.
So it's not believed to be a good indicator
of what is happening in the entire world.
Linux has a much higher penetration
in non-North American markets
and it's actually estimated to be as high as between
eight and twelve percent in some Asian countries.
Next, I would like to cover a few of the
top distribution methods for Linux
because after we released
Linux runtime support
one of the most common
questions we actually got was,
"It's fantastic that I can publish my
game for Linux now, but I have no idea
how to actually ship it to
potential customers."
The most successful distribution
method for Linux is Steam.
Steam for Linux launched publicly in
February of this year, as I mentioned earlier.
Statistics from March show that about 2%
of all Steam users are on some variant of Linux,
compared to about 3%
on some version of Mac OSX.
One thing to note is that many Unity
games actually getting into Steam via
a program called Steam Green Light.
For those who don't know,
Steam Greenlight is a system
where Valve uses community voting
as a mechanism to determine what
additional games should
actually go on Steam.
Another easy distribution method
is the Ubuntu software center.
The Ubuntu Software Center is an  App store for Ubuntu.
The nice thing about the Ubuntu Software Center is that Canonical
offers a free packaging service
that will package the raw binary
output from Unity into a Dev package.
We talked a bit earlier about how some
distributions, like Ubuntu, are commercially backed.
in this case Canonical is
Ubuntu's commercial backer
and provides financial support for the
development of the operating system.
And then we also talked
earlier about how
different Linux distributions have
different package management systems,
and one of the prominent package
management systems is a system
that uses what we call "dev packages,"
and Ubuntu is one of those systems.
The free packaging service from Canonical
and submission to the Ubuntu Software
center can be accessed by going to
developer.ubuntu.com and just
setting up a free account.
Desura is another digital
distribution platform.
It has clients for Windows, for OSX, and for Linux.
It tends to cater to smaller indy
developers, who are not large enough
or not yet large enough to be able
to negotiate deals with Steam.
There's not really much else to say
except that it is very straightforward.
And when I've spoken to some of the people
that have founded Desura, they told me
about how games that have a
Linux port sell significantly better
then the games that don't
have a Linux port.
And then finally, The Humble
Indie Bundle is very, very popular,
and many of the bundles have done
over one million US dollars.
And together the 21 completed bundles
have done over 33.2 million US dollars.
Often games are scouted
for these bundles, meaning
that the organization that compiles
and ships the Humble Indie Bundle
will approach developers asking
if their game could be included.
But if you would like to submit your
game to them for consideration,
all you need to do is go to their
website and fill out the submission form.
The Linux developers at Unity
in particular are very
happy to work with
any game developers that are trying
to get their game ready specifically for
the Humble Indie Bundle.
Oftentimes when game developers
are using this, this is the first time
that they've ever shipped a game for Linux
so they have a lot of unanswered questions or
potentially can run in into problems.
Now next I want to discuss the export feature
that it exists in Unity 4 for exporting to Linux.
In Unity 4 you can export your game to Linux in the
same way that you can with Windows and Mac OSX.
The export feature is available in both
Unity free and in Unity pro.
We don't require an extra license
in order to use it.
Actually building the player is very, very simple.
In Unity 4 the build settings
window now shows
Linux next to the Windows and
Mac stand-alone targets.
If you select Linux as the target platform, you'll
have three different options for architectures:
One is for X86 which will produce binaries
suitable for 32-bit architectures,
One will be X86-64 which will produce
binaries suitable for 64-bit architectures,
and then finally there is what
we have called a universal target
which will contain the game data and the
player binaries for both architectures.
The system requirements for a desktop
Unity game on Linux are very, very simple.
There's three main things that the user will need.
One is a C++ runtime, which the user is guaranteed to
have if they have any tools or applications installed.
They need to have a machine
with 32 or 64-bit architecture.
So some kind of an ARM platform, for example,
won't be able to run the Unity player.
And then finally they
need a graphics card
and drivers that will provide
hardware acceleration.
Additionally in Unity 4.2, which is currently under
development, there is a headless mode option.
This option will produce 32-bit or 64-bit
binaries designed for headless servers.
I spoke earlier about how Linux installations
are different oftentimes on the server
that they are on the desktop
and on the server they don't have any kind of a UI.
So if for example you
want to use the player
for a network server for
a multiplayer based game
for example, and that
server is running Linux
and it is a headless install of Linux then you'll
want to build a player with its headless mode option.
That's exactly what it was intended for.
These players will start up
automatically in batch mode.
They don't require running X11
session they don't even require running
X11 install in order to work, so if you've
installed a standard Linux server distribution,
then the headless player will
just work out of the box.
In fact the only system requirement for the headless
player is simply a C++ runtime.
So that covers of how you can
very easily export your game.
In terms of distribution support at Unity, we offer
what we're calling official support for
Ubuntu Linux version 10.10 or later.
The reason why Ubuntu was chosen is
because it has by far the highest
desktop market share amongst
Linux distributions.
But the player actually runs without problems
on a very, very wide range of Linux desktops.
Our analytics showed right after we
released it that people were running it on
everything from a Ubuntu to Linux Mint to Arch Linux,
a huge number of Linux distributions that I
didn't actually even expect people to be using.
So users should not be afraid of filing
bugs found on any distribution of Linux.
And of course we give preference
to addressing issues on
Ubuntu specifically, but we're happy
to look at any bugs that you file.
Next I will cover a couple of tips
for developing Unity games for Linux
that I've personally
found important.
On some machines
there is a Compiz is setting. Compiz is
used by most compositing window managers.
The default desktop on Ubuntu for example,
relies on Compiz and many others do as well.
And in Compiz there's a setting called
"unredirect fullscreen windows."
In many cases the setting
is not turned on.
The setting allows, when
applications are in full screen,
for the drawing on full-screen windows to
not be redirected to off-screen pics maps.
So for any 3D application the setting
will significantly affect performance.
Sometimes not having it on can actually
affect the frame rate up to fifty percent.
So it should always be turned on.
We've talked to the developers
of Ubuntu and in their
12.10 release, which came out
in Fall of this last year,
the setting is now on by default,
but in previous versions of Ubuntu it was not
on it may not be on on other distributions.
So if there is any kind of a performance
problem this is the first thing
that developers should look for.
And then next is related to
the Build Player Pipeline.
Because there's no editor
available for Linux
you have to edit and build your Linux
game on Windows or Mac OSX.
One thing that speeds up this process
for me is to use a post-process build step
that automatically copies my build player
from OSX or Windows to my Linux machine.
I personally do this with
an editor script and it's
a very simple very
straightforward editor script.
In this example a directory on
my Linux machine is mounted
as a share on my OSX
installation, but you could
modify this to simply copy with
SFTP or SSH without much trouble.
You can find out more information
about post-process built steps if
you don't know in our online documentation
and I've included the link to the specific
page that is relevant for this example on this slide.
And now finally we have a few things that are either
done but not yet released or are in development
that I want to share with you.
These things include headless mode,
which I previously mentioned is
going to be releasing in Unity 4.2,
and webcam support
which will also be released in Unity 4.2.
One of the things we want to work on
in the future, is better
Steam integration.
A lot of our users have
had a lot of trouble
integrating with Steam's
APIs and libraries,
so we would like to make that
process as easy as it can be.
And then finally we want to spend some
time optimizing for open-source drivers.
I don't believe they will ever be
able to provide, or always provide
the same user experience with open-source
drivers as we can with proprietary drivers,
but we haven't really optimized it all and I think
that's one area that we can improve on a lot.
So at this point that includes all of the
content that that i've prepared to present.
Are there any questions from our audience?
(Thanks for your talk.)
(What about the editor? Is it coming to Linux?)
So the question is, "Is the
editor coming to Linux?"
I get asked this question all the time
and I wish I had a better answer.
It is being researched.
We haven't decided either way whether
or not we actually will ship it.
A lot of it is a question for
demand and benefit for our users
as compared to the development time and more
specifically the long-term support burden.
There's obviously a significantly
larger amount of tech
that exists in the editor than
exists in the runtime,
and we also use a lot of
third-party middleware
in the editor that we
don't use in the runtime.
So there's a higher development cost there, and
we have to be sure that the benefit
to our users is going to be worth
committing ourselves to the
long-term support burden.
It's being researched. We
haven't decided either way.
People who wanted and have a use case for
it, I would encourage you to make yourself
known the Unity community
and to us as a company,
because we take user
feedback into consideration.
(Can I ask one more? Do you make any guarantees about
which version of OpenGL will be used by the runtime on Linux?)
We haven't published any guarantees,
and I can't remember off the top of my head,
what we're assuming in the rendering pipeline.
But I would be happy to look that up for you
and contact you with that
information at a latter time.
(Thank you very much.)
Ok, any other questions?
(Does Unity plan to support Open GL 4
in the future?)
Do we plan future Open GL 4 support?
It's not something that
we're specifically working on right now, but
I believe that we will need to
support it because eventually
it will just be a requirement for
users to be able to run our content,
not only only on Linux but also on OSX.
Any other questions?
Okay, if you'd like to speak with me
privately or if you would like to
have on my business cards in case you have
future questions feel free to come up here,
and for everyone else, arigatou gozaimasu.