Hello, my name is
Kim Steen Riber.
I'm glad to see so many
of you here today.
I'm gonna talk to you today about
the memory profiler in Unity.
Day-to-day I work at Unity
as a core developer.
Before I joined Unity,
I worked at several game studios
and released games like Limbo,
Watchmen, and Total Overdose.
At Unity, I am primarily focused on
optimizations and performance
and making the tools to enable you to profile your
games and get them as performant as possible.
And I like Legos.
So, when you're creating your games,
there's several things that you'll want to address
when when optimizing your games.
The obvious, of course, is frames
per second or framerate,
which is where the user gets the smooth
experience of the game that runs 30 or 60 FPS.
So there's two limiting factors to this.
Namely, the time game takes to to run
a frame, and that's on the CPU side.
So that could be game code, physics, skinning,
other heavy tasks that run on the CPU side.
And then there's the GPU side, which is things
that run on the graphics card
and that's drawcalls,
shaders, fill rate.
And the game never runs faster
than the limiting factor of these two.
So, another thing to think about
is not to have spikes during your frame rate,
because that'll feel like, for the user,
you'll have a jaggy experience
because you get frames spikes
because of heavy CPU tasks
like garbage collection, or physics
world rebuild, or scene load.
Also, memory is an important thing
to keep in mind when developing your game
and there two main reasons for this:
Keeping the runtime memory low, so you
can fit in memory on the device,
and then to to keep the memory activity low
to avoid the garbage collector to kick in.
So in Unity Pro, we have a tool
for this. It's the Unity profiler.
And this has several focus areas like
CPU, GPU, audio, physics, memory.
But this time, I'll only talk about
the CPU profiler and the memory profiler.
A new thing in Unity 4.1 is that
we have a detailed memory view
of what is in memory
at the moment
and coming in Unity 4.2, we also
have reference view for this
so you can see where a
certain asset is referenced from.
The CPU profiler. It will let you use time
consumptions for each frame for each method.
So this is displayed in a hierarchy
view, as you can see up here,
and it can be sorted by the
most time consuming
or the most garbage... the most
memory heavy functions.
The profiler also has the ability
to connect to a running player,
so if you have your game
running in iPhone or Android,
you can connect the profiler
and can actually see
the profile from the game
running on the device.
This is done by using the menu up
in the top of the active profiler menu.
So in the editor, you also have
to turn on deep profiling.
This will instrument all calls
in your managed code.
So it'll give you a much more
detailed view, but it also has
a large overhead because all
methods are instrumented now.
But it can be used in small scenes to drill down
and find fine details on your performance.
And so in Unity 4.1, we also have made
some improvements to the memory profiler,
which will let you inspects the memory at
runtime at a much finer level than you used to.
There's a simple view and
a more detailed view.
The detailed view you can see up here.
It's expensive to calculate so that's why
there's a button for it-- it's "take sample"
and then you'll get a snapshot of how the memory looks
at the moment on your device or in the editor.
So, detailed view will show you a list of all Unity
objects, like assets and scene objects
and it will also have some calculations of
some of the core areas of Unity
like webstreams, Mono
managed heap, shader lab,
many more areas that
take up memory in Unity.
This view will then let you find
more memory consuming objects.
If you, for example, have an uncompressed
texture that slipped into production
or an excessively large section
that should be reduced in size
let's you pinpoint these much easier.
And then in Unity 4.2 we've also
implemented the reference view.
As you can see up on the screen
where you can actually see where
a certain asset is referenced from
what script, what game objects, and so on.
that'll help you to to pinpoint if you have memory leaks
because you're holding references to an object.
So, the simple memory view in the memory profiler
shows some key numbers and in the used memory.
As you can see, it has used size
and the reserve size,
and that's because in Unity
we reserve a block of memory
and use that to make our locations from.
So there's reserved and used, both for Unity native
and for Mono, the managed memory.
There's also a GFX driver point up there
and that gives an estimated calculation
of what textures and meshes
are uploaded to the graphics driver.
But it's an estimate because you can't really get
the correct or the precise numbers from the drivers.
As you could see in the simple memory profiler, the
memory is split into managed and native memory.
The managed memory is what Mono uses.
It includes what you have allocated from your scripts
and wrappers for the game objects you have in your scripts.
This memory is handled by Mono and this garbage
collect is whenever the garbage collector kicks in.
On the Unity side, we have the native memory and
it's holding everything in the engine
so this data includes texture data, vertex data,
mesh, audio, animation, game objects, components
so everything that's held in native code where you
have just small wrappers for it from the managed code.
And it also covers, of
course, engine internals
like rendering, culling, shader lab, particles,
web streams, files, physics.
There's a whole bunch of things that of
course goes in the Unity core.
This memory is not garbage collected,
but handled explicitly.
For assets you will need the "unload unused assets"
call from your scripts to free this memory.
On the Mono side, the managed memory reserves a block of
system memory to use for allocations in Mono.
And then this heap space is just being used
whenever it's exhausted, whenever there's no more free space,
Mono will run the garbage collector and
remove all memory that's no longer referenced.
If Mono, after this garbage collection, can't find memory for
your allocation, it will have to allocate a new block
and will expand into this block of memory.
And this this will grow to fit the peak
memory usage of your application.
The garbage collection can be a
time-consuming operation
so you don't want to run this if you can avoid it.
And another reason is that with high memory
activity, the memory is likely to get fragmented,
and all the small, free memory fragments will
be unusable for large allocations,
and then your your heap will grow
beyond what was actually needed.
When Mono is giving memory
back to the system
if such a heap block should completely be emptied, then
mono can give this back to the to the memory.
But you can't really control this,
and it's also likely that there's
allocations left in the heap segment, and
then Mono can't give it back to the system.
So keeping the memory activity low
is a good thing.
Here is a little example, just to show fragmentation.
If you have all these small
holes in your heap block.
Mono comes in, if you ask it for
some memory, it can fit it in there.
Next time you ask for the same memory,
because of all the holes, you can't really fit
it in. And even though there's enough free memory,
there's just not enough contiguous
memory to give this allocation
then Mono has to allocate a new heap block.
Again, a reason to to keep the memory activity low.
Even though scripting happens
in a managed language like C#
there's a number of ways you can control the memory
and reduce amount of allocations
made in your code and the memory activity.
So if you have routines in your code
that need some temporary memory
then it's worth considering allocating that memory
on your class instead of allocating it in the function.
Because then you allocate it once and reuse the buffers
and you don't incur the memory activity in Mono.
Another thing to consider is creating pools of objects.
So if you have something that's used very
often with a short time span
for example, bullets from machine gun or something like that,
it's worth creating a pool of these
objects. And every time you need one,
grab one from the pool, and whenever
you're done with it, put it back in the free list.
This way, you don't have any memory activity and you
also save the the cost of instantiation
of instantiating this object every time you need it.
So a third thing to consider is using
structs instead of classes,
because structs are allocated on the stack
while classes will be allocated on the heap.
So if it's small data containers, then consider
if it's worth the using a struct instead.
Don't use OnGUI, because it's very memory
heavy and has a lot of memory activity.
It's good for prototyping for debugging purposes,
but in your final game, use
something else to create your GUI.
There's a small example here
where on the left side, I just made a script.
It's nothing special. It just has a data processing function.
Every time this function is called
it allocates a working buffer
and does nothing with it.
But let's just fix it.
It also passes in a little working
struct, which is actually a class here,
and not much should be happening
but what you can see up here is on the
memory, on the CPU profiler
there's a lot of memory activity
going on in these functions.
And they also take quite a lot of time
because of this special allocation.
I've just changed these a little bit.
I've put the working buffer on the class,
I've changed the work data to be a struct
and then, you can see that's down here
and there's no allocations.
And it takes no time, because
there's nothing to do and since there's no
memory activities there is virtually nothing to do.
So just keep that in mind to try to reduce your allocations,
and use the CPU profiler to investigate and make sure of this.
Some Unity objects that you allocate in scripts have
a large native memory footprint in Unity.
An example of that is the WWW class which,
on the managed side, is only a small wrapper.
But on the native side, it contains several buffers:
a compressed file, decompression
buffers, and the uncompressed file.
And this backing memory is not cleaned up
until the finalizers are called from Mono
or if you call dispose on this WWW class manually.
So if this is left to the garbage collector to finalize,
then potentially it can take a very long
time before this memory is cleaned up
and then you have some some memory
just lying around that should be cleaned up.
So the way the garbage collector
works is kind of shown here.
You have a reference to an object
and then you remove that from Mono
by either setting the object to "null,"
or the object going out of scope.
And after a while, the garbage collector will run
this will either be because the heap space gets
exhausted, or if you manually call "GC.collect()."
So when the memory is collected by the garbage collector
this object is then put on the queue
for the finalizers to clean up.
And this is handled on another thread
and eventually, the finalizers will
run and call "dispose()" on the object.
But you can't really tell when
or if the finalizers will run at all.
So you have no control doing it like this.
So to skip this round trip, you should
call "dispose()" directly on the object
to free up the the memory and then the
object will not be given to the finalizers.
So I have a small example that shows this.
So I have the profiler,
and I have a very small example here.
Where I have trouble navigating...
I connect to the running process over here.
So we have this memory.
So if I do a load of a webstream
and then I just...
Do you see this?
If I null it, then you can see
the memory drops pretty quickly.
But if the heap space..
There it is.
Now I just allocated a lot of heap space
not really used for anything, but...
but it means that
Now Mono has a lot more
memory reserved.
So there's a lot longer up to when
the garbage collector will run.
So I load the stream,
and I just remove the reference.
The memory stays high because the
garbage collector is not running.
So if I do that manually,
then the memory drops.
So of course, when you load,
then if you dispose your object instead,
then the memory goes down immediately.
That's just something to remember.
I will just move this away...
So for asset bundles, when using asset
bundles, it's important that you know
what memory is used by Unity
and what was allocated in the various stages.
So that the webstream, the WWW class
the web stream data here holds several buffers,
depending on the settings of the stream of course.
But if it's a compressed stream, then
it will have the compressed file,
it'll have the decompression
buffers used by LZMA,
and then it tests the final uncompressed data.
The asset bundle is then created
from this web stream or WWW object,
and allocates a map of objects that is
in the asset bundle and offsets into the file.
And then when loading the objects from the asset bundle, these
objects will be created in memory from the decompressed data.
So when you have your "assetbundle_url" file,
what you do this you can load this file
asynchronously by calling the new WWW
and this will load the compressed file into memory.
It will start the decompression,
and the decompression algorithm
will allocate some buffers.
And in Unity 4.1 and before,
this required a buffer of 8 megabytes decompress,
and that's just because of the settings
of the decompression.
This will then unpack the data and
allocate buffers for the decompressed data.
To avoid this 8 megabyte decompression
buffer reallocated for every file,
in the backend of Unity we keep one 8 megabyte
buffer around for the next decompressions.
So keep in mind that several parallel loads will
then each allocate such a decompression buffer
and this will result in a large memory spike.
To avoid this, try to load your webstreams one at a
time, because then you can reuse this 8 megabyte buffer
and you won't get this peak.
And so for Unity 4.2 and beyond, we have changed
this compression, so it'll use much smaller buffers.
So after the file is loaded, you construct the asset
bundle from the file calling the "www.assetBundle."
This will load the map of objects
and the offsets into the webstream,
and the asset bundle will then
retain a pointer to the webstream.
Because if you load something from the asset
bundle, it needs the webstream to be around.
So even if "dispose()" is called under WWW object,
it will still be around until the
asset bundle is unloaded.
So when objects are loaded
from the asset bundle,
then the data from the webstream is used
to construct the requested objects.
Then the asset bundle has a little
list of what objects it has constructed.
So to load objects from the asset bundle
you can use either "load," "load all," or the
"dot main assets" methods from the asset bundle.
In the example I'll show later,
I'll just load a texture,
and this texture will be instantiated
from the asset bundle.
And when the texture is uploaded to the GPU,
on players, it will then be deallocated from the main memory.
On editors, we keep this data around,
because of the possibility of you
changing some flags in the editor.
And also, on platforms that use
the multi-threaded renderer...
The textures transfer to the render
thread and then there's a transfer buffer
between these two threads and
that'll grow to fit the entire texture.
Of course, this is not real-world example, because I
hope none of you have 32 megabyte textures in your games.
So when all the objects you have
have been uploaded to the file,
you can get rid of the webstream
data and the asset bundle.
So the WWW objects should
be deleted by calling "dispose()"
and not left for the for
the garbage collector.
And so, as long as the
asset bundle is still around
the webstream will not be unloaded.
So you need to delete the asset bundle as well.
And this can be done by calling
"unload" either false or true.
If you call it with false, the map and the
reference to the webstream are unloaded,
and the backing memory will be be deleted.
If you instead call it with "unload(true),"
then the asset bundle also uses
a list of instantiated objects,
and deletes these objects as well.
So bear in mind that if you "unload(true)," then if
you have references in your scripts to objects
created from the asset bundle,
these will be nulled and you'll get null point
exceptions if you start accessing anyway.
So when you're done using your assets you can
unload them by still having the asset bundle,
and then still having a reference to the
asset bundle and then calling "unload(true)."
You can also not have the asset bundle around
and then call "UnloadUnusedAssets()"
when all references to to your
instantiated objects are gone.
So if an object is not--or an asset is not--
unloaded when you call "UnloadUnusedAssets(),"
it's because it's still being
referenced somewhere in the code.
In the profiler in Unity 4.1, you'll be able to
see if the object is referenced from script,
or if it still has references,
or if it's marked as hide and don't save.
So in Unity 4.2, we've added additional
functionality so you can actually see
if it's referenced, what script it's referencing, the
object, or what material is referencing the texture.
So it will help you pinpoint where
your references are being held.
So for the most efficient way of
loading an asset bundle
memory-wise, it is, if possible, to just
load one asset bundle at a time.
Load what's needed from the asset bundle, and then
destroy the webstream and the asset bundle again.
So here's a small example:
Load a texture from from the asset bundle, and
whenever this code routine is done running,
all memory from the webstream and
the asset bundle is unloaded and destroyed
and there's only the texture memory left.
So to later get rid of this texture, remove the
reference and call "UnloadUnsuedAssets()."
So I have yet another small example.
Well, it's the same example.
There is the the web stream.
If I load that, notice that the memory...
That the memory grew.
What we'll do is just go to
detailed view and take a sample.
Here, we can then see that in "others,"
we now have a webstream loaded
and we have the name name of that
stream, and it's taking up 32 megabytes.
Most of this is in 4.2, so you'll have to wait a
little bit to get the the latest features of this.
If we load the asset bundle, we
can dispose of the webstream.
But you could see that the
memory still didn't go down.
That's because we still have the webstream
around, because it's referenced by the asset bundle.
So we load a texture.
We now see that the asset has
grown and now has the texture there.
We can also see that it's referenced once,
and is referenced by the script, because
I'm just holding a reference to it.
We can "unload(false)."
So now the webstream, the
backing data, is gone.
Of course, take a sample.
See that the web stream is
gone from the from the list
Also the transfer buffer I was talking
about from the graphics GPU
is this 32 megabytes that I've allocated here.
This is not going to be relevant
for a real game project,
but it's just to show that it's
there and it's being registered.
So if we then remove the texture reference,
see, the memory didn't really go down.
We take a sample and we can
see that the asset is still around,
but now, there's no more references.
So that means that is you
call "UnloadUnusedAssets(),"
the memory will go down,
and the texture is gone.
So this is just to show you
how you can investigate your memory
usage using the memory profiler.
So in assets, the texture is gone
and everything is back to normal.
Yes, that's it here.
So, conclusions about this.
Avoid memory activity to keep your
Mono memory unfragmented,
and to avoid the garbage collector kicking
in and causing frame spikes in your game.
Use the memory profiler to monitor memory usage.
Or actually, both use the CPU and the memory profiler
to monitor memory activity in the CPU profiler,
and see what objects you have
allocated using the memory profiler.
To keep the memory peaks down, try to
load just one WWW object at a time.
Use "dispose()" on these objects
that derive from IDisposable.
WWW is an example of that.
Because they have a large memory footprint
on the native side, so you you want
to get rid of them as soon as
possible and control that yourself.
And then of course, use "UnloadUnusedAssets()"
to clean up the assets from memory.
So, that's it.
So, any questions?
(Thank you very much for your talk.
I have a couple of questions.)
(Well, just a question about
the new memory profiler.)
(Will it be possible to automatically give detail as upshots?
Right now, I think you have to press manually,)
(but I would like to have like, I don't know,
every ten seconds or something like this.)
Yeah, I'm thinking about making the option
where you can actually do it every frame.
Even though you'll take the
perfomance hit from it,
you'll actually be able to see
what goes on every frame.
Or maybe, as you say, doing it with a
time interval. That makes a lot of sense.
Another thing we want to do is to make a tool
where you can make a div between two snapshots.
- (This will be in the next release or 4.3?)
- Well, the detailed will.
But, every frame, or with intervals and the div, that will be in
yet another future release, but yeah i'm working on it, so...
(Another one, about the reference view in
Unity 4.2, I guess it's only for Unity objects?)
It's for for assets, but...
It's for Unity objects, but some assets.
A material, for example, that can
reference a texture...
But yeah, it's only for Unity objects in terms of
assets and game objects and stuff like that.
(Say for instance I create my
own native object or whatever it is.)
(Is there a way I can tell the profiler like, "send the
reference" or something like this, so it can count this too?)
No, not at the moment, but
it's definitely good in the end.
Just send that feature request to
us and we'll look into if it's possible.
Because of course, we want to empower you to
be able to get as detailed a view as possible.
(Okay. Thank you very much.
Very interesting.)
Yes, a lot of it can be done in the editor,
because if you have objects that are not unloaded
because you still have references to them
and so on, that's good to use the memory
profiler to find those and clean it out.
But, if you want to get a precise measure for what
your textures and assets are using on the device,
you should to run the the game on
the device and connect to the profiler.
Because the numbers you get in the view will then be
calculated on the device and will be very precise.
In some cases, a little bit estimated, but usually it's the
precise footprint of what those assets are taking on the device.
And we don't we don't emulate in the editor
out how much it's going to take on the device
because that's that's always going to
be off, and so we don't want to do that.
Yes, if you do an object pool
of, for example, bullets.
Then you instantiate all those objects into
your pool, so you only call "instantiate"
a fixed number of times. Then you grab
the objects without instantiating them
but just grab them in and out of the pool.
And then, of course the memory
on the Unity side will also
not fragment, because it will just
stay in memory. And you just
pull the object in and out of your
scene, but it's always in memory.
Object pools, you also save the instantiation
if you just instantiate your objects.
And there's, I think, the astrodude
project on the Unity asset store
uses object pools a lot, so you can see a
lot of stuff best practices in that project.
Yes
I heard this also when we were in Korea,
that some guys on an Android project
also had some big memory
footprints from their scripts.
I was a little puzzled about that because
it shouldn't shouldn't be that bad.
But of course it's always a good thing to not include
things in your project that you're not using.
But, it seems like there's something, a bug, somewhere
about these scripts because we've seen it before
and you also seem to have it.
And please report these
bugs because it seems wrong.
I can't really tell you why, because
20 megabytes for a couple of scripts
doesn't make sense anywhere, so we would
really like to investigate that and find out why.
And that being said, the the memory profiler, even
though it displays a lot of the memory that's going on,
we're not catching everything.
So if you see big differences between what is
actually reported on the device and what we report,
then tell us, because then there's something we're not
catching and we want to get this as precise as possible.
But it's a work in progress, and we're trying to
get it better and better every time.
But just tell us and we'll
make sure we get it better.
Yes
You should avoid using it totally.
Because as soon as there is
an OnGUI function on a class,
even though it's empty, it will start
calling the GUI layout managers.
and setting up a lot of stuff, and it calls your OnGUI,
and then it's just empty, and then just returns
but it has already done all this
setup, and it does that every frame.
So, if you need OnGUI in your editor
for debugging purposes, for any reason
then use preprocessors to get
rid of the entire OnGUI function
on when you compile for
your target platforms.
Ah yes, it's time, but if you have
more questions, feel free to come by.
I'll be out here afterwards, so you can
just come come over and ask questions.
Thank you for listening.