Welcome.
Welcome to the Unity rendering pipeline talk.
I'm Kuba Cupisz,
and this talk has been prepared by myself and Tim Cooper,
who's doing another talk tonight.
So, who am I?
I'm a graphics programmer,
and I've worked at Unity technologies for quite
some time already, for almost four years.
And before joining Unity I
worked on some small games,
like probably most of you do now.
So what we will cover today
are quite a few topics.
And most of them are related
to the new 4.x features.
And some of them are
just nice tips.
So, we'll start by talking a bit generally about
what Unity is good at, and what it is bad at.
So, the rendering pipeline is very
flexible, it has three rendering pipelines
that allow you to make it fit
for different kinds of games.
It has a vertexed path, the
forward, and the deferred path.
It allows you to write custom shaders,
and do custom lighting
models for those shaders.
And it's basically
completely customizable.
Because of the flexibility, it's also difficult to
configure because there are just so many options.
Also, since there are so many
parts to the rendering pipeline,
some parts are more well
maintained than the others.
Also, the default settings, they suit quite a
few projects, but of course not all of them.
So, you need to take care to actually make sure
that your rendering settings are fitting your game.
And, well, there are a lot of settings so
it takes time to go through all of them.
Unity ships with built-in shaders, and those of course work
with all the rendering configurations that Unity allows for.
So, it works with all
the rendering paths.
It works with realtime
lighting and lightmaps,
with shadows of course,
and all those things.
They support the standard lighting
models like lambert and blinn-phong.
And, of course, they work on all
the platforms that Unity supports.
What they're not good for, though,
is, for example, stylized games.
Since they only provide the standard lighting models, you
might want a game where the lighting behaves differently.
You might have a game where
you don't do lighting at all.
And, of course, in those cases it might make
sense to actually write your own shaders.
Also, even though those
shaders perform really well,
if you can make some assumptions
about your game, about your content,
often times you can optimize
your shaders to run even faster.
Also, the size of the binary
that we compile the shader to
is quite big, because they
support a lot of variants.
Those variants can be lightmaps, realtime
lighting, shadows, or no shadows and et cetera.
So, when would you
write your own?
Well, when the built-in shaders are not custom
enough, or when they're not fast enough.
But in this case, of course,
profile -- never assume things.
In cases when you know exactly how your game should
be rendered, well, feel free to write your own shaders.
So I will give you some background now to
introduce a new 4.x feature.
But basically, when you're writing shaders by default,
the built-in shaders they have many variants.
So, in the case of the built-in
shaders, as I mentioned before,
that allows you to do shadows, or no
shadows, lightmaps, or realtime lighting.
But you can use exactly the same system to
make different variants of your own shaders.
And that allows you to reuse big parts
of the code, and just switch different
small subsets of the
shader to something else.
And you do that based
on shader keywords.
Normally, you set them globally, but
since 4.x, you can do that per material.
How do you define them?
Well, you write a line that
declares a set of defines.
And it looks, for example, like this: #pragma multi_compile.
So that will compile the shader into different versions.
Then you specify the set of keywords. So in this
case, it's a keyword AAA, and a keyword BBB.
So, that gives us two variants. One where the first
keyword is defined, and the second one is not.
And another variant, where the second
keyword is defined, and the first is not.
We'll see in a second
how that is useful.
Well, we can also add a second line, where we
define a set of keywords with only one keyword.
But that still gives
us only two variants.
One where the keyword AAA
and the CCC are enabled,
and the other, where BBB
and CCC are enabled.
If we extend the second line, and
add actually another keyword there,
we end up with four variants
as you might have expected.
So, in 4.x, we actually are allowed
to set those keywords per material.
And that's very easy to do -- it's just an
array of strings that you set via property.
You can also write a custom
inspector for the material.
And that allows the user to actually
select the keywords that will be set.
How do you do that? Well, you
extend the material editor class.
And that allows you to
make a material inspector.
In that, you override the "OnInspectorGUI", which
allows you to extend the GUI for the inspector.
And in cases where you call base."OnInspectorGUI",
that gives you the default GUI for the shader.
Now we will look at an example
of how we can use that.
We have a simple example
where we have two spheres.
They're both using the same shader as a custom darkened
or difference shader. It's the same here and here.
The difference between those is the mode. One has the
mode set to darken, and the other one to difference.
Those modes are just the
way we blend textures,
and they are the same as the darken
and difference modes in Photoshop.
So, if we look at the shader,
what you will notice first
is that we have the
"#pragma multi_compile" line that we talked about
before with the darken and difference keywords.
So, as you remember, only one keyword will be
enabled at a time when compiling this shader.
So, if we say, if the darken shader keyword
is enabled, then we can run one path.
Otherwise, we will
run the other path.
So, that's basically it. It allows you to
run different code based on the keyword.
But the rest of the shader is exactly the same, so you
don't need to duplicate code between different shaders.
Now how do we define the editor?
We just write "CustomEditor", and then we provide
the name of the class that defines the inspector.
In our case, it's
"CustomMatInspector."
So, if we look at this class,
it's inferenced from "MaterialEdtior", and
it overrides the ""OnInspectorGUI"" method.
Since it calls the base
""OnInspectorGUI"", that gives us
the default parts for the
inspector that take textures.
Because in our shader, what we have are just
two properties. Both of them are textures.
But now we want to allow the user
to actually select the keyword.
And to do that,
it's quite simple.
You just need to do a pop-up, and you
provide two options for the user.
Once the user has selected,
you set the shader keywords on the
target material to a list of strings.
In this case, it will be only one string, because
it will be either darken, or difference.
And that actually
concludes the example.
So, if we just look at one of the spheres,
we can switch from one mode to the other.
How can we use that?
Well, you can use it to, for example, switch
the lighting or the looks of your game
globally with one
shader keyword change.
Of course, you can do it also per
material, and that becomes very useful.
How we plan to use it, is, for example, to
instead of providing many many shaders,
like, if you look how many built-in shaders
we have now, it's actually quite a lot.
We have bumped diffuse, bumped specular,
diffuse, diffuse detailed, et cetera.
And of course, the same shaders that do self-illumation,
transparent shaders, exactly the same set.
So, instead of adding complexity
here, we could just provide an
inspector that allows you to
decide those things by checkboxes.
Or in case we have a
slot with a normal map,
if you drag the normal map there,
then we use a bump map shader.
If you don't provide a
normal map, we won't do it.
So, it will allow us to
simplify the interface for you.
We will switch to another example now.
In Unity, you can do
shader replacement.
That basically allows you to render objects with another
shader than they typically would be rendered with.
So, all the objects will
still use the same material.
Whatever properties were set on this material,
whether those were textures or flows or whatever,
all those properties will still be
passed to the new shader that
you want to render your objects with.
The sub-shader, since you're providing only one
shader for the entire shader replacement rendering,
then you might want different objects to be
rendered with different sub-shaders.
You can do that by sub-shader tag matching.
And I'll explain how that works in a second.
So to use replacement shader, either on the
camera you can set the placement shader,
or you can invoke on the camera,
render with shader which
will render the scene once.
The first setting is sort of persistent
until you change that of course.
And the second one is
only one off call.
So, in case you want to specify
the tags, then all the objects
will be rendered with a replacement
shader that you have provided.
It will use the first sub-shader from the replacement shader.
But this is not that interesting.
Instead of looking at the slide, let's just look the
example because it's much easier to understand.
By default, Unity
provides a few tag types.
So, it has the "RenderType" tag, which defines the
type of the renderer that we're looking at.
And the ones that we define in Unity are,
for example, Opaque for opaque objects,
Transparent for transparent objects, and
"TransparentCutOut" for cut out objects.
This is the replacement shader that
we will be using for this example.
So, what is happening when we are setting this
shader, is that all the objects that by default
were rendered with an opaque
shader, now will be using
the sub-shader that
has the same tag,
the same value of the "RenderType" tag.
So, all the opaque objects will now
be rendered with this sub-shader,
transparent with this one, and
transparent and cut out with that one.
The example is actually kind of handy, and you
might want to use it in your own productions.
What it does is, it adds the lighting-only view, that
allows you to skip rendering the albedo textures,
and view only the lighting.
So, this is a very useful to, for example, debug light
maps or figure out how are things actually lit,
and see that, well, this object is dark
because it has a really dark albedo texture,
but the lighting on it
is actually quite bright.
How does it work?
Well, apart from the shader that we had there, we
also need to have a script that will set it up.
The script is very simple. It just plugs into
the menu, and it finds our shader by name.
And then, it uses a handy function that allows
you to set a replacement shader for the scene view.
So, it says the shader, the
lighting only shader, and it says
match the sub-shaders by the tag called "RenderType"
-- so, the tag we have already seen before.
That concludes that example.
We already talked about that, but of course instead of using
the built-in tags, you can use your custom tags.
I mean this is just a string, so you can define
whatever you want, and match based on that.
The lit-shader replace is actually
available only since Unity 4.1.
Before, when the replacement shader loop was run,
it didn't provide any information about lighting.
So, you didn't know that the directional light
is there, that there are some point lights here,
or that you have spherical harmonics
sent into the shader either.
This is very useful for scene view
enhancements or special effects.
So, it works exactly as normal shader
replace, as you might know from before,
but it provides just more information for you, so you
can use surface shaders that do lighting in there.
We'll switch to
another example now.
I know that endless runners
are quite popular now.
And for those games on mobile, it still
makes a lot of sense to bake lighting.
But the problem with an
endless runner is that
it's the type of game where the track is
assembled at runtime from different blocks.
It's not really feasible to bake
lighting for all those possible
combinations of blocks, because you might
want to first have one block then the other.
And in another set it might be the
third block or the fourth block.
There are many combinations.
So, you don't want to be baking lighting
for all those possible combinations.
Instead, you would bake lighting
for each block separately.
But then when the player goes from one
block to the other, the lighting will pop.
So, I'll show you how to use light probes to light
dynamic objects in a scene with baked lighting,
and to still have
smooth lighting.
So what we'll do, is we'll bake light
probes for each block separately.
Then, when the player will move from one block to the
other, we want to switch to light probes for the new block.
And we do that by setting the
"Lightmapping.lightProbes" property
to the assets that hold the
tetrahydralized light probes.
But the problem with that approach
is that when you're just switching
from one light probe set to
another, that will give us a pop.
Let me show you that.
I'll just open a new project
for that, just a second.
So, this is our example project, and you can
see that we have those different blocks.
This is a really simple example
that you will have access to.
So, it just has two blocks. But of course, we can add
twenty more, and it will still work the same way.
So, we have a red block,
and a green block.
The difference between those two is the red
block has some more light probes here,
where the bumped lighting is
actually supposed to be yellow.
So, it actually needs to capture that
data, hence we place the probes there.
If we just...
When switching from one
block to the other.
Let me just turn off the lighting here.
Can you see that?
When we're switching from one block to the other,
now we're just setting light probes to the new set.
So, that gives us a pop.
It pops from red lighting to green
lighting, and that's not very pleasant.
We can fix that quite easily, let me just show you how
it looks first, and then I'll tell you how it works.
Now the transition is smooth,
and it's smooth again.
So, what we do, when
we look at one block,
we can see that we have something that we
could call, like, a start set of probes.
These are the probes that the player is
going through when he enters the block.
And, we have the
end set of probes.
So, these are the probes that the player
goes through when he leaves the block.
So, if we attach one
block to the other,
then what we need to do is to make
sure that the layout of those probes
is the same between the start
probes and the end probes.
That will basically make sure that
once we load one block after another,
the end probes of one block will match
with the start probes of the next block.
That alone, of course, doesn't
solve the problem yet, because
the probes baked for one block
had red lighting, and the one
baked for the other one
had the green lighting.
So, what we can do, is when the player
actually moves from one block to the other.
Let me actually show
this, in this area.
Here we can see the
baked probes.
And now, since we're in the red block,
we have the red bounce lighting.
Now, when we go to the second block,
what we want to do is set the
start probes of the new block to the
end probes of the previous block.
So, even though we are now in the green
block, we have set the start probes
to the last probes of the previous block.
And that makes sure that when the player switches
on the border from one block to the other,
the lighting still continues.
How do we control the transition
to the proper set of probes?
In this case, the green set.
We can add another set of probes
here, just after the start probes.
And depending on how close or far away
from the start probes you put them,
that will control the
transition distance.
So, if we look at another transition...
still nice and smooth.
But this is not the only problem. The second
problem is that baked data is not movable.
So, since we have been baking the data where
the blocks were positioned at (0,0,0)
because that was just
the easiest to set up.
And of course, at run time the blocks can
be positioned anywhere in the level.
Since the baked data is not movable, normally the
player will sample outside of the volume of the probes.
Let me show you how that works.
So, if we select the player,
and we play the game.
We can see that now the player
still gets the yellow lighting.
And now, it still gets
the green lightning.
But actually, the position that we used
to sample this volume defined by probes
is the position outside
of this volume.
We extrapolate that information, so you
still get proper green lighting here.
But once we reach some actual meaningful lighting, like
we go back to red, and now we're over the yellow part.
We don't get any yellow part because we're not
sampling lighting here -- we're sampling it here.
So, what we can do is actually...
the fix is quite simple
because in the renderer component, we
can set a light probe anchor override.
So, this is a transform that will be used to
actually sample the volume of light probes.
And to make it work,
What we do is...
When a player moves from
one block to the other,
we just offset the
light probe anchor.
I have that anchor selected now, so
you can see where it is in the world.
We offset the light probe anchor by the current
offset of the block we have just entered.
So, if we go to the next block,
it jumps back again to proper position.
And what is cool about just parenting it under
the player, is that we just need to offset it
when we're switching from
one block to the other.
But otherwise, it just follows
the player naturally.
So, it's actually a
very easy setup.
So, those two things basically allow you
to use light probes for an endless runner.
Of course, this example is sort of 2.5D, but you can easily
use that for a 3D endless runner in exactly the same way.
The next topic that we
will cover is Direct X 11.
That's new with Unity 4.0.
What is interesting about that, is that
it basically gives you more flexibility.
It allows you to use techniques
that were previously either
not possible, or just not
feasible to do on the CPU.
The first topic that we'll
cover is tessellation.
So, what tessellation is, is basically
a subdivision of geometry.
It adds more triangles.
But, by default those triangles are
added in the same plane as the original
triangles for which of those
small triangles that are added.
So, if you had a
big triangle here,
and you added more, they would still not
increase the amount of detail that you get.
Nor would they make the
edges more smooth.
You would still have
those sharp edges.
But to get more detail,
you have two options.
The first one is to displace those new vertices
by using displacement texture, for example.
The second one is to use phong tessellation,
which basically uses the interpolated normal
to figure out how to inflate the geometry, and
basically give the object a more smooth appearance.
And that just inflates the geometry, so it works best
for organic objects like rocks, trees, and such.
How would you use that with surface shaders?
Well, hopefully it's very easy to use.
In the line where you define the
surface shader, you just specify
the tessellate keyword, and
then the "FunctionName."
And the "FunctionName", in its simplest form,
just returns the tessellation amount.
Now, how to calculate the tessellation amount?
Well, we provide two helper functions for that.
The first one is the
"UnityDistanceBasedTess."
And that tessellates more the objects
that are closer to the camera.
The second one is
"UnityEdgeLengthBasedTess."
So, that tessellates more the
objects that have bigger triangles.
And that basically allows you to make
sure that the resulting geometry
has the same amount of detail, no matter
how big the original triangles were.
So, if you have a cube
with huge triangles,
and then put a player with small triangles after
tessellation, both of those objects would have
more or less the same size
of the Nth triangles.
And let's look at an example.
Switching back to the
Vertex 11 project.
Here, we can just see the
built-in Unity plane.
But what's interesting about it is that
it's using the tessellation shader.
And once we come closer,
you can see that
quite a few triangles are added, and
those allow us to displace that plane
to actually gain proper detail,
and look like cobblestone.
Of course, adding those
triangles is not for free,
so at some point you might
want to fade this out.
So, here we didn't tweak it to perfection,
so you can see that at some point
the cobblestones fade out.
But you can tweak it so that
it looks much nicer than that.
But once we go far away, we don't
tessellate anymore, because it's simply
not needed, and the difference
will not be visible.
If we look at another example...
Here, we just have
three objects.
Actually, those two objects, they
originally are from the same mesh.
The mesh looks like this
-- it's an icosphere.
But the difference between them is that
this icosphere was imported with...
Actually, let me just show
you those import settings.
It was imported with normals set to calculate,
and the smoothing angle was set to 60.
So, that basically makes
sure that each face
has a different normal, and those
normals are not smoothed out.
The second sphere was imported with the
smoothing angle set to 180 degrees.
Which basically means that all the normals were
smoothed out, and there are no hard edges.
Both of those spheres are using the phong
tessellation mode that we mentioned before,
which basically
inflates the geometry.
So in a case where the normals are smooth, that gives
you a nice organic shape which is, well, very round.
Whereas in the first case,
that gives us a shape
that has splits in it, because in those
cases, we had hard edges in the geometry.
So, it won't work nicely for the case where you have
hard edges, but it will work nicely for organic stuff.
The third example is just a really
simple example for displacement.
And that's it for the
tessellation example.
Another feature of Direct X 11, that
I think is much more interesting,
and actually handier than tessellation,
is unordered access view.
That basically allows you to write to a
"RenderTexture" or a "ComputeBuffer" at any position.
Normally, when, for example, you're
in an image effect and you're
processing your image, and writing
to another render texture.
Then, the position on which you're writing
to the destination render texture
is very well defined and
you cannot modify it.
So, even though you can sample from different
source pixels, you are always writing
to a well defined pixel of
the destination texture.
And this is quite limiting.
Unordered access view allows you to write
at any position within the destination buffer.
So, you can sample here from any pixels you want, but
you can also write to any pixel you want in the destination.
So, you can write both to
"RenderTextures" and "ComputeBuffers."
And the render textures, well, most of
you are probably familiar with those...
Those generally store colors, and they
come in a bajillion different formats.
So, it can be ARGB32,
ARGBHalf, ARGBFloat,
one component, 8bit,
16 or 32, et cetera.
"ComputeBuffers" are actually
more flexible than that.
They are called "StructureBuffers" in Direct X 11 speak,
and they store structures or structures of simple types.
So, they can store whatever you want. Of course it can be
color, but it can be anything -- counters, you name it.
And simple types -- those can be integers,
floats, unsigned integers, et cetera.
So, how do we use that? The example will
actually show you how to use compute buffers.
But it's as simple, if not simpler,
to use just render textures.
So, you need to create a
"ComputeBuffer" script,
and the constructor basically
takes the count and the stride.
And the stride is just the
size of one element in bytes.
Then, you initialize the
contents of that with "SetData."
So, in most cases, you want to initialize
it to zeroes, or black, or whatever.
Then, you need to set the buffer on
a material to be able to use it.
And normally, when you set
textures you call "SetTexture."
But for a buffer, you just call "SetBuffer."
So, the naming is quite sensible.
Let's just jump to the example now, because
that will be easier to understand.
The example shows
you a histogram.
So, what it does, you can see
that in the lower left corner,
it basically looks at how many pixels of a certain
color you have, and it does that per channel.
So, in this case, we can see that we have quite a few
dark pixels because they're on the left hand side.
But once we go through some more green areas or
red areas, the appropriate channels jump up.
So, actually let's
look at it again.
So, the width of this
histogram is actually 256.
So, for each value from zero
to one for an 8-bit color,
we just count the amount of pixels in the screen
that have this value, and we do that per channel.
And if we have a look
at the shader...
The shader's actually
very simple.
It reads from the main texture.
In this case, it's a simple image effect,
so the main texture is your source texture.
Whereas the destination texture normally was a render
texture, and in this case is also a render texture,
but there we actually write...
We just return what
we have sampled.
We're not modifying that at all.
Our actual output is in those
three structured buffers.
So, compute buffers on the Unity scripting side.
So, what we do is we look at the color, we
saturate it so that it's within zero to one range,
and then we multiply it by 255.
And that basically gives us
the index into the array.
Because, remember that those compute
buffers, they just behave as arrays.
So, you index them
exactly as arrays.
So, per component, we just increment
the value at this location.
The trick here is that incrementing a value
is more tricky than just setting a value.
Because the GPU is running
many threads at the same time,
for many codes of this method,
we could be writing at the same
time to the output buffers.
So, what we need to do is make sure that the
operation that increments the value is automatic.
So, it first needs to read the value that
incremented by one, and then write them back.
And making that operation automatic
is as simple as calling "InterlockedAdd",
which will make sure that the synchronization
happens between all the tracks.
If we look at the script,
it's also fairly simple.
What we do is, we create the "ComputeBuffer"
with 256 elements per buffer,
and with the strides set to four because
we are storing unsigned integers there.
One thing to note is that we
need to actually store...
Well, we're storing integers,
not unsigned integers.
One thing to note, is that to be
able to use "InterlockedAdd"...
So, to synchronize between the threads, you need
to use an integer or unsigned integer buffer.
Otherwise, those operations are not available --
you cannot use them on a buffer full of floats.
If we jump back to the script, there are
a few more things that are interesting.
Setting the buffer, as we said
before, is just "SetBuffer."
Then, we specify the name in the
shader, and set the buffer.
So, once we have all this information, how do
we actually show it as the graph on the screen?
In this case, it's
actually very simple.
We just have three lines that, by default,
run from this side of the screen to here.
And, in the vertex shader, we sample the buffers
to decide how should we offset vertices.
And those lines have
256 vertices each.
So, each vertex maps to one
position in the buffer.
If we look at the shader for the line,
we can see that in the vertex shader,
we sampled a histogram
"ComputeBuffer."
So, in this case, those will be the red buffer,
the blue, and the green buffers appropriately.
Then, we use the color channel
from the mesh to figure out
what is the index of the current
vertex we're looking at.
And we multiply that by 255 because
this is in the zero-one range.
So, we want to be able to index it
with the proper index from 0 to 255.
And once that's done, we're just scaling
it so that it actually fits on screen,
because you can have many many pixels with one specific
color, and then it will just blow out of the screen.
Like here, we're not
using a second pass.
We could do a second pass where we're counting the maximum
amount of pixels, and then scale everything like that,
but I'll just leave that to you
as an exercise after the talk.
There's one more interesting thing
that you can do with Direct X 11.
And that is to use
compute shaders.
But I'm not sure it makes sense to go over that now,
because the example is a bit more tricky to explain.
The whole talk is available
online with all the examples.
So, I think it will be easiest if you
download that, and check the examples out.
The example basically uses
Direct X 11 to fill a 3D texture
based on some simple calculations that use
the IDs of the threads that are running.
Yeah, and I think that will conclude the talk, so that
we still have a few minutes to go over questions.
It would be good for you to
actually download the examples.
So, just note that link that's
in the bottom left corner.
Fetch the project, and
play around with it.
And if you have any
questions, please ask now.
I will also stay around, and you can ask me after the talk
if you have a question that is specific to your project.
But general questions,
please shoot them now.
Yeah, and don't be shy.
Yes please.
We should have someone with
the microphone coming.
You can ask the question in Japanese
or English -- whatever works.
Are you talking about
the shader keywords?
So, setting those shader keywords
globally was available for a long time.
Then, setting it per material...
So, for some specific objects that are using
a specific material -- that's only since 4.1.
Any more questions?
I'm not sure what the
question is, but...
So, as we said, when you are defining a set
of keywords with pragma multi compile line,
then only one of those keywords will be enabled
at a time when the shader is being compiled.
So, what you will end up with is two different
versions of the shader in the final binary.
And either one will be invoked at run
time, or the other one will be invoked.
So, if you have "if" defined
darken keyword, "else" something,
then only one path will
be invoked at run time.
So, it's not like runtime if it's
a totally compiled time choice.
And then at run time, you just choose which shader
will be used by setting the currently enabled keyword.
Hope that explains it,
or answers the question.
One more question, please.
Yes.
Like half a year ago,
that number was 32.
But now, we moved it
to 64 some months ago.
But that's still... Still, some
of them, we use internally.
Like the ones for light maps
being disabled or enabled,
shadows, native shadows, or non-native
shadows, or shadows off et cetera.
So, we use about fifteen or
twenty of them internally.
And also, typically, when you're enabling or disabling
features, you want to have an on and an off keyword.
So, that basically makes the amount that is
actually available to you around twenty.
Like, it's forty divided by two, because
you need an on and off keyword typically.
But, if you're hitting the
limit, then that's not nice.
But, at the same time, I'm pretty sure that the compilation
time for your shaders already take a long, long time.
So, at this point, it's probably better to just use
separate shaders, at least for some of the things.
Any other questions?
Okay, if not, I think
we'll end it here.
But, I'll stick around, so you
can approach me after the talk.
Do you have a general question? Do you
want to ask it now? Or a specific one?
Let's take one more.
Yes, on the platforms that support it.
And those are most... Actually,
all of the current PC platforms...
PlayStation, I guess...
iOS, unfortunately,
doesn't support it.
It was enabled for one release of
iOS, but then it was disabled again.
So you cannot use it on iOS.
And, you can use it on
some Tegra devices.
But it's not fully supported, so make sure
you have a fall back solution for that.
A sample for a fall back,
or a vertex texture fetch?
Yeah, we had that, actually,
in the histogram.
If you look at this shader --
the histogram line shader.
In the vertex... Well, actually,
it samples a "ComputeBuffer".
But you might as well sample a texture
here, and it would just be a normal...
I can send you an example by e-mail.
I guess that might be easier.
But, it's basically
thanks to the LOD call.
Because, the thing is that you need to know
which MIP level of the texture to sample.
And the texture to the LOD allows you to specify
the MIP level that you will be sampling.
If you just Google that method,
everything will become clear, I think.
Okay, I think that's it.
So, if you have specific questions,
you can just talk to me afterward.
Thanks.