Hello, everybody.
I don't speak any Japanese, so...
My name is Carl Callawaert.
I work as a product--Closer? Okay.
I work as a product evangelist at Unity Technologies.
I perform workshops, training around
the world, mainly in the Americas.
I'm always happy to be here,
but it's still snowing where I live.
I live in a remote place in Canada,
so to be away from the snow is great.
Today we're going to talk
about Shruiken particles.
What I'm gonna' do, I'm gonna'
show it directly in Unity.
So I'm going to cover how to
create particles like fire, like this,
explosions,
and effects,
another kind of fire,
but I will break it down--why and how I use it.
Like explosion effects,
like magical effects,
other ones,
like totally different.
But, you will see what
I'm talking about.
Like storms and we're
going to deal with that.
Other effects.
We're going to start
with this one.
So I'm going to go back to
my Powerpoint presentation.
So after this presentation, you
should be able to create complex
particle systems in an
easy and fast way.
Also, some advice for you on how
to use Shuriken for mobile.
Raise your hands. Who of you
has already used Shuriken in Unity?
Raise your hands. Who has problems
sometimes creating the effect you want?
So first, we're going to talk about
how to create your effects.
So, for people who don't know particles,
it's just a collection of sprites
and 3D objects that are emitted.
We can use it for
rain, smoke and fire,
but also to show impact
or magical things.
Later on, I'm going to talk more about that,
but always ask why you're going to use it.
Don't start to use particles if there's no why,
and if you can do it in another cheaper and
faster way, its more interesting sometimes.
How do I learn Shuriken?
I used particles before, of course.
But there's a lot of particle effects
on our Asset Store you can download
and learn from there, from the interesting ones.
I look at real particles
in life and analyze them.
I go to YouTube for that.
The problem is when you look at
Shuriken, or when you open it in Unity,
it's a lot of parameters, a lot of sliders.
It's overwhelming.
But if you learn a slider,
never ask what that slider does.
That is useless.
Think about why I will use that slider.
This is the first essence of creating
particles or any software.
If you use buttons with
the reason "what is it?"
we call that "buttonology."
And the knowledge of
buttons is not useful for me.
So we're going to talk about
fire and explosions, like this.
I work in four steps.
First, I define how many
particle systems I will need.
Then I analyze how they move,
and then I do the colors and the materials.
And then the little effects
to make it magical.
But, mainly I'm lazy.
I just buy the packages on
the Asset Store and I'm done.
So the question is "how many
particle systems do you use?"
When I look at this particle
system, I see four.
But, I don't agree with that.
Why?
Because, when I close my eyes,
and I look really simply through my eyes,
I see two major things.
It's the glow and the
shockwave. The light.
That's enough sometimes
to create the effects
instead of creating all the particles.
Especially when you do cartoons,
think about just the essence,
what you need.
The more particles you
put in your scene,
the more it becomes difficult on
your draw calls and your overdraw.
And, if you have a lot, then you
cry and you stop your production.
But let's talk about how to
create a simple fire particle.
See the glow?
And that's very important,
just one element of glow.
When I open my eyes a bit
more, I see the shockwave.
When I open my eyes more, I see
actually the flames, the fire.
Open more, I see smoke.
So depending on what quality you want,
how many more particles you're going to add,
all those different layers
become my particle system.
When we have this explosion here,
we have the glow.
And this is actually one particle.
I don't use objects for that.
And one simple particle.
And we have the shockwave.
Again, it's one simple particle.
But, you're going to see my workflow. I just
take the same particle and I duplicate it.
I do not create new particle systems.
Explosion. The fire.
We have also the inner fire.
I have the the debris.
And again, each particle
was duplicated.
I never created a new particle
system. It was just a few changes.
Because it's all connected to the same
forces, the same energy that works in it.
The sparks too. The little
sparks will come up.
I just changed the material
and the force in it.
So let me talk about the
movement of particles.
We have here smoke and the fire.
Both particles move along a
path or in a certain direction.
If you recreate in Unity a default particle
system, a Shuriken, you have a shape.
Raise your hand if
you use that shape.
Almost everybody.
I would say "never use it."
The reason is here.
The particles are moving because of
forces and the velocity in the particle.
In reality, that shape does not give
me enough control for a movement.
I cannot animate a shape.
So we're gonna talk about the velocity
over time and force over time.
So that shape? Never
use it. Turn it off.
The particles still have
speed. They're coming out.
Who of you uses speed?
Raise your hands.
Again, don't use that.
Because in Unity,
the speed is five.
But in reality, question
yourself "why?"
"What is speed?"
A car drives forward.
That is speed.
But smoke? The car goes forward,
but smoke has no speed.
Fire has no speed, because
forces work on it.
I have never seen a particle
with an engine in it.
Never seen it.
But, tell me if you see one.
When I look at the smoke here,
I wonder if it's speed,
force, or velocity.
I could move up because of heat,
and heat changes over
time. It cools down.
So speed does not work for me.
It goes to the left because
of a force of wind.
So I never use speed, but
pure force and velocity.
So again, this speed doesn't give me
enough control, and it's not realistic.
So I turn off speed, and now I have
one particle that stands in the middle.
So we're going to use
again velocity and force.
But understanding force and velocity is the
essence of creating a great particle system.
And sadly, our manual does not
go in depth to explain the power.
So I have here a particle system,
and I put a force on it of two.
My particles, over time, will go more and
more into the X-axis because it's added to it.
It becomes more and more stronger.
It sounds great.
So we get that curve.
What is velocity?
If I add a velocity to it of two,
all my particle system turns.
But, it does not add.
It does not get
stronger and stronger
There's a huge difference there.
The one is linear,
and the one is at that curve.
So here's the power of velocity.
I key frame it.
If I put it to four, and then to
minus four, I go to left and right.
But when I put it to
zero, I go back up.
So I am fully in control of
the motion of the particle.
When I use force, it
becomes difficult.
Look now.
The value is zero, but still my
particle goes to the right.
Because I added--four minus four is not
actually zero with this. It becomes two--
it comes to minus two.
So it becomes very difficult to make the
mat to get a control system over this.
So I never used force for the
direction of my particles.
When do I use force?
If I want to add
force for gravity,
like for explosions, if I want
to add it to my velocity.
So for the look of the particles, the easiest
way I found, is to create materials.
There's a lot of different textures out there that
I can use to create the random feelings to it.
I also use a lot of animated textures. I like
to have, over time, the materials change.
But I use it also like for debris.
Instead of animating rocks that tumble, I use
particles and an animated texture sheet.
Now there's a very
complex, very intriguing
connection between the flow
of the particles and the look.
If I look here at my fire to the left,
and the smoke, both have the same flow.
So I duplicate my fire
and I change the color.
So it's smoke.
The only thing I have to do is actually change when
my particles become visible and how long they live.
That's how we make very fast particles.
You duplicate it, and then you
just change the factors in it.
Because you are using the real physics,
the real gravity and forces, from real life.
So let me talk about
Shuriken and mobile here.
One of the issues is of course the
overdraw, when you use it on particles.
Unity 4 has a lot of
improvements on performance.
But ask yourself the first question,
the first most important question.
"Do you need a particle system?"
A nice example is Shadowgun.
On the left, you see those crazy machines
with the green things that are moving.
Your first reaction is, "wow,
did they do those particles?"
Well, no, they didn't do particles.
It's animated textures.
It's much better on performance.
So it's the same with rain.
Why do you use rain in a game? It's because
you want to create a dramatic feeling to it.
But will thousands of
particles create that?
But maybe I can go another
way to create a feeling?
Just by bringing down the lights, maybe
lightning, instead of rain to get that feeling.
So the more particles and also the more particle
systems you use, you're going to have more overdraw.
If you have a short particle system,
where you have an instance to overdraw,
I highly advise that you download a
Sprite Packer on the Asset Store.
It's a free package that was actually
created by one of our employees
who on a regular basis comes
to the office, sometimes not.
The cool thing is it converts
it to a sequence of sprites
instead of having problems
with the overdraw, then.
It's for free and nicely
converts it for you.
The cool thing is also if you dig up your old
particle systems with the legacy particle system,
it can convert automatically to a Shuriken
and then create a sequence of
sprite animations out of it.
You also have to question yourself "should I use
animated meshes?" versus animated mesh particles.
Especially when you
create effects like this.
The one on the left was
animated by using 3D meshes.
Trail rendering.
I have more draw calls, of course, on it--
on that one--but a lot less overdraw.
But when I did it in particles,
so my particles were actually
not moving, no speed.
The only thing I did is animated the
direction and animated the material over it.
And, a little bit of trail render.
I had, of course, a lot less draw calls.
But my overdraw was
high. Look at that balance.
What is most effective and
most performance for mobile specific.
Another thing you can
do is create a script
that controls the emitter rate; how many
particles are emitted based on distance.
If you go further away, don't use all
your particles. Just reduce them.
And also look at the transparency. Maybe I can
swap it with a texture that's not transparent.
Another very interesting one is the
parameter of Max Screen Scale.
This parameter helps you like when
you're gonna walk through clouds,
and it can basically define how big the particles have to
be before it gets rendered, or it can remove it, basically.
Since Unity 4, we have
also World Collision.
So that means that all particles can
collide with anything in the scene,
even animated objects.
Really great, but if you're going to put that
in mobile, you might have a little problem.
The first thing I want to point out is that
in the quality settings, you
have high, medium, and low.
High means that you're actually gonna cache all your
particles for the collision, but at every frame.
And then you have low, medium.
And then medium and low means basically you're gonna
cache a certain amount of your particles for the collision.
And then the cool thing is actually that you can define how
much your Particle Raycast Budget is based on your platform.
And this is a screenshot
from in the quality menu.
And from there, you can say for my iPhone,
you're gonna use 64, and for my PC, 8500.
Because of that, you
can have nice control.
But if you use like an explosion, you don't
really need a perfect collision, always.
Just from major ones, yes, and that's why
you put your raycast budget much lower.
Another issue that a lot of
people have is scaling Shuriken.
When I select the root of
Shuriken, I cannot scale it.
So that's really sad, because you can make a beautiful fire,
and then you create a new project, a new game,
and you have a much bigger scale in the game.
It doesn't it work. You cannot scale it.
The cool thing is, in the asset store you
can find Cartoon Effects Easy Editor.
This is a nice extension that it can add
and you can scale your particles in that.
Just click any scale, even when there's different
particle systems underneath the structure.
And the cool thing is I like to use
my scaling of my particles because
like I'm running around with a shotgun, I have a
little particle system, and when I see far away,
another particle is bigger.
Thanks to that, I only
need to create one.
And then with pooling, you have one in the scene and
then you move them around with different sizes.
Let's go a little bit hands-on here, now.
So I'm gonna' quickly go over those
different particle systems, here.
So what we have here is the
in this case we have the fire.
We have here the...
first, the fire here.
RGB.
So this is my fire and
I have my smoke here.
So you can see already that my
fire and smoke are actually the same.
But my smoke lives longer
and starts a bit later.
And then we have sparks who live longer
and have a little bit more force to it.
But let's talk first about the inner
particle, here. Let's create that also.
So I create here a particle system
and I move it to the right here.
The particles come out. So as I said
before, I do not like to use speed
because I want full control over it,
and I do not like to use a shape.
So I'm going to create some
force for it, velocity for it.
And here, the Y, I'm
gonna put it to "world,"
and the Y, I'm going to bring it up.
The particles go up.
I'm gonna say "okay, that's
good." Maybe one up.
And I can't in the X-axis, or--In
the Z-axis, you'll see it better.
See, we cannot define?
But I want them to go left and right.
So that's why I'm gonna say here click
"random" between two curves.
So we have here the Z-axis,
and I'm going to do between
one and minus one.
And I don't want them to go too much
out so I can animate it over time.
And you have the life of the particle.
So now they go both directions, here.
I can do the same for my X-axis.
But in my Y, here.
So I give them a velocity of going up, here.
But in the beginning, I want them to go
faster and then slow, and that's how we nicely
can adjust this function curve here. Maybe
I'm gonna put it to four or five going up,
and then here, bringing it down.
So over time, what we see is the particles
go up fast here, but they slow down.
Just going to do it for this one too, here.
And we make it a little random, here.
So you see now, I start to have
nice control over the shape.
Especially here in the Z-axis, now.
I can define the Z-axis.
See, I can define how my
shape will be for my particles.
Otherwise, if I use a regular shape, I
have no control over exactly what I want.
So particles come out.
Now, let's make them a little bit shorter.
So one, and the start
life, maybe 0.8.
But some particles will live a bit longer,
so random in between two values.
Maybe 1.5.
Let's add a bit more particles to it.
Like 50 particles.
So we see nicely the effect on
it. It goes left and right a bit.
Now what I want also is that the
sizes are a little bit different.
So maybe like 0.6 up to
maximum, 1.3 or something.
So we have different sizes in there.
So now I start to be happy with
the movement of my particles.
I'm gonna add here now
color to it, like smoke.
So we can use a texture like this.
I'm gonna add it to
my particle system.
So we have this.
Okay, let's add some color to it.
Color over lifetime.
And then click here.
All my particles start--like fire,
in general, starts to be yellow.
And also, we can put
here some yellow color.
And it will become red.
And I have to use this one.
So first, I start yellow.
Over time, they become red.
And over time, they become dark.
In the beginning,
they will be more transparent
because they are starting to create,
and overtime, they're gonna
fade out, my particles.
That's how I start to create it.
I want a little bit more change, like
the flames are turning and twisting.
So what I can do is really, simply the starting
of the particles have different rotations.
So between like zero and 360.
Let me show you that in the wireframe mode. So, you
start to see that the particles have different rotations.
But over time, I can also moved them.
So, rotation over
lifetime, random again.
And now we see it start to twist
and rotate the particle itself.
And that's how we start
to create our fire, initially.
Then the really simple thing is
that we're gonna call this fire.
What I do now is that I duplicate
it, and I have a "fire," here.
And I'm gonna call it "smoke."
I'm gonna make it a child of my inner fire.
Make sure I select
the right smoke.
That's my smoke. Okay.
And fire, okay. Smoke...
Okay, cool. The moment you make it a child,
they're both running in simulation, here.
So that's pretty cool.
So the only thing I have to do is that my
smoke will live longer. It's really simple.
So the lifetime?
It's the life time, here.
I'm going to make it from
0.6 to 1.9 or something.
So they live longer, here.
And then we can go
to the colors, here.
So our--they will be more darker
than here from the beginning.
But, you can put here also
darker than the beginning.
But I don't need them really in the beginning here.
What I do is just move the transparency to here.
Make it more transparent.
See, and nicely we don't have any beginning.
And then more in the end.
In the end, make sure they're
fully transparent, here.
If you look good, sometimes you're going to see artifacts.
Some particles don't know which one to render first.
And how you can fix that, my
fire should be rendering first.
And we can do that in
the Sorting Fudge.
So I just bring the
Sorting Fudge up,
and that gives those particles a priority.
So they're gonna render first.
And also I'm gonna say that they should--
that all those particles
should render first.
And then I can add a
bit more particles to it.
And then, really simple. Look, my
smoke. Y'know, duplicate that.
And I'm gonna change the
material to little dots.
So I have here a flash-something.
So we have now dots. We're just
going to make them smaller now.
Okay, 0.66 or something.
And 0.2.
Okay, so we have those little dots.
Make it a bit more
visible, for the fun.
And then the color. Just the
color, we have to change again.
Click. This color.
We're gonna make it yellow.
And then we can make different colors.
And so we have those dots.
And then I'm gonna just make them
a little bit--live longer again.
But when you look very good at fire, those little
dots fly more around because of the forces on it.
They're so light
and there's wind.
So now, how are we gonna use force?
So we're gonna add forces, here.
If I put X up--let's see world again--the Y here,
up and down, I'm gonna bring it a little bit up.
And Z to the left.
But I want it also to the other
side. That's right, actually.
What I'm going to do is just
random between two values.
So like four and minus four.
So now we see them going left.
And minus four.
So you see the particles are
going left and right now.
But what actually wants is that sometimes they go left
and then they randomly exchange different values.
We can do that with
randomize. See?
And now I have those
particles going left and right.
So this is a technique
I mainly use.
Just duplicate the particles and change
what has to change from a natural flow.
This needs to be then to the storm here.
When we look at this dust
devil here, this particle,
the motion is fully
controlled by the velocity.
See the X goes more
and more and more?
That's what we create that pattern of left and right.
If you want to turn a little bit afterwards,
you can now use the force.
And here, like a random
or a constant value.
See, now you can.
Make sure you have that one correct.
Now you can move your particle system.
Let's look quickly
at this one here.
We have here our fire one.
So we see those particles and we understand that now.
But how do we control something like a glow like this?
It's really simple, actually.
You create another particle.
It's a particle system.
No speed again, and no shape.
The emission, I don't need ten particles.
This is a bit complex here in Unity.
We have the maximum particles, the rate, so that we can
never more than a thousand particles basically, over time.
And ten here.
So you're gonna do
plus zero. Zero particles.
But at frame one, I'm gonna generate
30 particle. I'm gonna say one.
So we're just gonna create one particle system,
and I'm gonna make it a duration of one second,
and not loop the moment. So press play.
Where is my particle system, here?
Gonna loop it.
So we have that one particle here.
But I don't need that fireball here now.
So we see that one
particle here created.
And we're not going to loop it.
So what we're gonna--not loop.
So we have that one particle it creates.
And now, you just animate the transparency
and the color of the lifetime.
I think we're gonna put
it here to yellow.
So I'm gonna press play here.
And we can now do transparencies.
So now you see we have a particle.
That's how I can do my intensity and I
can add a bit burst and a bit rate.
And then I'm going to get
that feeling of a particle.
We can duplicate it.
We can look here now at an explosion.
Then I go to my explosion here.
So, we saw the...
Okay, wait a second here.
Okay, my explosion we're
gonna remove this. Sorry.
So we have a glow
here that we saw
and that's that one particle.
Then we create and then
we animate the transparency.
The shockwave is exactly
the same structure.
So, stop this.
Remove the sparks for the moment.
So I duplicate the one particle
and the only thing I have to do
I put another material on it.
You animate the scale a little bit over time.
That's how we get the shock wave now.
And then the sparks.
This again.
A burst of 15 particles,
I'm going to create.
Like in-game object, gonna
create a particle system.
And I'm going to put the--let's
see... To one, here.
We're gonna put the speed
again to zero, and no shape.
And I want to create the sparkles flying out.
So the best way to do that is to actually
create a velocity over lifetime again.
And we can do again random curves.
So I want to do it in X and Z, both.
See, we bring them out.
Then, in Z, we're going to do exactly the
same so that they go in all the directions.
And that's an explosion.
It goes in every direction.
And there, we use the velocity because
the energy comes out and it slows down.
Again with the Z,
with the Y too.
So you know my particles
go in every direction.
Most people would use an emitter sphere, but the
problem is that you don't have control over a sphere.
So particles come out, you can
add a bit of gravity to it.
No, do a little bit, so the
particles come out.
The size, I'm going to
make a little bit smaller.
And now we can use our
force on the particles.
And again, random between
two curves in our values.
Again, make four and minus four.
Four and minus four.
And four and minus four.
And that's what we start to
get that particles going out.
I could have done a bit more gravity to it,
but the cool thing is in the render here.
Click here, we're gonna stretch the billboards
and scaling
and based on that now,
you can create the
feeling that they fly out.
And that's how we start with that.
Then you can duplicate that and
things and materials in that case.
Using those bursts, that's how
I created that heart, here.
It's really simple. You have
one particle system.
That is one particle and it goes
up. You give it a bit of force up.
And then you create the
slice particle here.
And then the only thing we
have to do is to start a delay.
And then we have a left particle system,
like for the left heart, with one object,
and also start a delay and put
the gravity to--put forces on it.
And then the right side is a duplicate
of the left side, and you flip it.
And now that's how you get your particle system by
just duplicating one single instance of particles.
It is the same for the ground impact, here.
Press play.
Okay, I'm gonna show it to you.
So the floor is one
particle system.
And then the rest makes
sense now for you guys.
So the ground impact here, we use a horizontal
billboard so that it's flat on the ground
instead of straight facing the camera.
And that's the only thing you have to do.
And when we look at the force
field here, this is a 3D object.
You're actually using one
particle for the fading,
and the other particles are just objects
you move around with a trail renderer.
And then this one, I did
is actually the same.
I took objects, put a trail renderer
on it, and move them around.
But the last thing I
wanna bring up here,
I'm gonna go to this one.
Let's talk about World Collision.
And I should have
here somewhere rain.
No?
Then I should go to scenes here,
and test.
I saved it just before I can hit World Collision.
So what we have here is
we have our rain here.
So our particles of our rain come out here
and when they hit the floor,
another particle is created by collision.
Something we had before.
But what the new thing is that when you do your
collision to world, it collides with all the objects.
You can define by layers how
many objects will collide.
But the most important thing
is that here, in the collision,
here, it's changed from
a simple plane to a world.
And here is the quality.
Medium, high, low.
But the most important thing is, for mobile,
is that you go to your quality settings.
And in the quality settings, you can, per
platform, define your Particle Raycast Budget.
And then the cool thing is that
you get cool effects like this.
This you can download from our blog.
So this was a a quick overview on how you
structure you particles, and you duplicate them.
Don't use speed,
don't use shape.
You control it, so you can
create what you want.
And the less parameters you need to use--
if you mix it with speed, it becomes complex.
And check out the Asset Store, so you can
convert your particles to a sequence of sprites.
For mobile, it helps a lot, and
use your quality settings.
And use some of the techniques.
So thank you for paying attention.
I have 3 minutes left on the stage before they
put in a box and ship me back to the snow.
So, what are your questions?
Wait a second.
What he can do is basically here.
You've seen...
You can...
A particle system.
So this particle here,
they die here, and you want from
there to create a new particle.
So, what I would do is
I will go to
subemitters.
And when my particle is dead,
I'm gonna create a
new particle system.
But this particle system,
that's a mirror.
Remove. Go to the emission.
And the burst to one.
So when that particle is dead,
you create a new particle.
Now if you want to continue that,
so you say "look," you're
gonna change the color here.
What I would do is inherit the velocity,
bring this up,
I'm gonna put it to one,
I'm gonna make the size of bit bigger.
Start the size here--okay, here.
No, it's a bit too big.
So now, when that particle dies,
a new particle system comes up.
So it's really around, instead of
activating and deactivating.
Another way you could do it
is animate the transparency.
Lifts, certain time, becomes
transparent and comes back.
(Yeah, thank you very much.)
Thank you.
One more question?
You can definitely do
it from a surface,
so if you go in the emission
here--no, shape.
Emit from...
Okay, you have here...
Here you can say it emits from a sphere.
Gimme a sphere, a box, or a mesh you define.
Okay?
And it will pick it from the vertexes.
Now I'm not 100 percent sure, but if your mesh is
animated, then it will still come out the vertex.
But I've never tested bringing
it out from an animated mesh.
Open project...
so it should be and should be and uh...
So it should be in...
It should be a mesh that is actually
animated like with an enveloping,
or "skinning" they call it, but I don't have an
example here ready to just test it out.
I definitely got to test that out.
So, okay, I will be in touch. I'm gonna test
it here right away after the presentation.
Thank everybody to take your valuable
time over and come to listen to me.
Feel free to contact me with
any questions you have.
I'm gonna give you my
contact information here.
You can follow me on Twitter,
and connect on Facebook,
Linkedin, Payal... No.
Thank you so much. Enjoy your
evening, and I'll see you tomorrow.
Time for sake.