Hello and welcome.
Or as I would say in Denmark,
"Goddag og velkommen"
The title of the
session is Unity Hacks
I'm going to start off
by introducing myself.
My name is Emil Johansen
I usually go by the
nickname of AngryAnt online.
That's a photo of me
I'm a game developer at Unity, which means I work
with the different developer teams to ensure that
all our different features work well
together, and I do internal demo work.
Some of which goes into standard
assets and that sort of thing.
And I specialize in AI as well.
I've been at Unity for four years.
And for the past five years, I've
worked with Unity the product.
And before doing so, I worked with Unreal
Engine 3, CryEngine 1, and Renderware
I live in Copenhagen, Denmark.
And in my spare time, I create some
additional projects such as Path and Behave.
These are AI middleware
solutions for Unity.
This is my second time around on the Asia Tour.
Last year, I did a talk called "Rapid
Network and AI-Ready Game Development."
It's a very long title and
I'm sorry about that, but
I couldn't come up with a shorter one.
So this talk is kind of the practical
counterpart of that talk from last year.
My website is AngryAnt.com.
And I gather some of my code snippets, examples, projects and
videos such as the recording of last year's talk.
This is my daughter, Lily.
And today I'm wearing a
different set of glasses.
Not out of a fashion choice, but because on my birthday
in February, she chose to tear the old pair apart.
So she's a feisty little devil.
Obviously, who can blame
her with those looks.
Let's jump onto the contents of this talk.
Unlike some of the other talks today, I've tried to
make this talk more of a
fun playful kind of thing.
I hope that you can take some of the
examples I'm going to show here
and if not use them directly.
They are designed for that, but
I really hope that you can
take some of the ideas and approach
and hopefully be inspired by that
to create your own Unity hacks.
So part of the theme here is
Mission: Let's Just Ship This Thing.
Which is where is this ties in
with last year's talk as well.
One part of that is to minimize your
needed workload by working smart.
And part of that is data and code reuse, which
I'll go in and demonstrate in a few ways.
And another part is shaving iteration
time as closely as possible
by managing your workflow.
We'll also get into that.
So, in regards to shaving iteration time,
that means adapting your workflow
and getting relevant feedback
data as quickly as possible
and reducing the amount
of manual work required.
In general, I'm trying to communicate
a theme of "Good Enough" can ship
in the pursuit of rapid
game development.
The way I'm going to go about
presenting this content is
I'll show a whole lot
of cool hacks and code
I'm going to show some good examples
of examples of data reuse
and a lot of editor scripting.
So let's start off by looking at
some examples from the runtime.
And initially, I want to touch on
the subject of animation curves.
The initial example here is
directional speed of character.
In many games you have a sort of humanoid
character or some avatar you need to move around.
This avatar will have a
facing and a heading.
By default, when the facing is equal
to heading, you'll want to
move that character by the top speed.
When at an angle, you'll usually want to, within the first
twenty degrees or so, keep this angle or this constant speed.
Though when you start
moving more sideways
and particularly moving directly back,
you want to weight the base speed.
And of course this
works mirrored as well.
So one way I propose doing
this with animation curves
is to divide the angle, or basically scale the
angle between the heading in the facing
between 0 and 180 degrees
and normalize that.
So this allows you to define an animation curve
where you can use the height of the curve to
define the scale of the speed.
So in this example, I'm showing showing
the curve that I demonstrated earlier
where you see initially, the curve - as we're close
to zero - moving forward, the speed remains 1.
And as we go further towards 1 or 180
degrees, we go down to half-speed.
Showing this in a real environment.
You can see if I move forward,
I have quite a lot of speed.
You can also see the speed indicator
in the upper-right corner.
But as I move around, I get
different speeds based on how the heading
moves around compared to the facing.
So, looking at a script.
The script I'm using for this is fairly simple.
Actually, the part that takes
up the most space is just
where I take the input and formulate
that into a directional vector.
So this is just getting
the input axis.
Then in each update, I just, for this
example, translate the transform
where I translate it by
my directional vector
the default speed, which is at 5.
Since it's an update, of course
it's scaled by Time. DeltaTime.
The interesting bit is where I get the angle between
the forward vector of the transform and my direction
I divide that by 180,
thus normalizing it.
And then I evaluate my animation
curve called Speed Scale
which I have made public so I can define it
exactly how it needs to look in the editor.
By calling evaluate, I get the height
of the curve at my given time index.
So another example of animation curves is
using it for camera blending and clamping.
In the same setup you have a character
with heading or a facing
and a camera observing the
top of the character
usually looking a bit over
the head of the character.
A fairly a common set up is that you want
to clamp the movement of the camera
between an upper angle
and a lower angle
in comparison to the reverse. Or basically,
the backwards facing vector of the character.
And you commonly also have a bit of logic to handle
clipping of objects, so you move the camera closer.
In this case I'm not using an
animation curve between 0 and 1
because I want additional data.
I actually want two
data points out of this
I want to know what the lower
and upper maximum is
as well as I want to know what the
update speed of the camera should be.
So I'm using the time index of the
animation curve to define the
upper and lower bounds in degrees.
So this basically says that
it can go 20 degrees below
the backwards facing vector,
and 30 degrees above.
And then I use the height to specify how
quickly it can move toward these extremes.
The effect of this is that as we are above medium,
and continue to move forward or upward
the camera will update
slower and slower.
So instead of getting a hard
clamp, we get a nice soft
lead into that clamping
and the same in reverse.
So if we look at the same example,
and I move the camera up
I keep a constant speed of the cursor.
But even so
it moves slowly in the end.
Taking a look at the code for this
this is slight more complex, so I'm
going to just focus on a few key points.
Initially, I define my animation
curve called "VerticalSpan"
where I set the default values to
start from the keyframe, minus 20
and end on the keyframe, 30.
And initially I just set it to have a start and
end value of 1, so this is just a flat curve.
I then use the editor to go in and add this
scale on either end to get that bell shape.
Then I have a few simple properties for figuring out a
normalized position on the arc that the camera can move on.
And finally, when I update my camera,
I have a "targetHorizontalRotation"
which an input scripts provides for me.
I then initially figure out the speed at which should
update this camera position or camera rotation.
If the vertical position
is above half,
and we're continuing up,
then I take my update speed and scale
it by the evaluated vertical span
using the angle as the index, because
remember we used angles for the X-axis.
If we are up, but we're not
continuing further up
this logic will not get executed, so therefore
we will just keep the regular update speed.
And the same is valid for the reverse.
So then I update my rotation.
And I apply the second step of checking
if my angle goes beyond either extreme.
So I clamp it and that's it.
So just to recap.
Animation curves are basically
just a number of curved 2D values.
So while they are most useful for, and
initially designed for animation
and these two examples were
probably quite animation related
you can basically use them
for just about anything.
Since you can just sample the data at
any point; it's just simple 2D data.
One example, I saw a guy on Twitter
recently who had used it to
he used an animation curve to define the difficulty level
of his different scenes, which is a very nice use case.
So anything from game logic to AI
whatever you can come up with,
we need a set of 2D values.
Especially because the curves are
visually editable in the editor, so
you can, very easily, instead of
spending a lot of time iterating over
some magical numbers, or a certain bit of
code that does something programmatically
you can basically just
go, "Here's a curve,"
and send it to your
game designer or artist
and go, "Okay, so you go ahead and tweak this."
And they can do this in play mode.
It's a very nice way to reduce iteration time
and offset a task that really should
belong to the game designer or an artist
offset that away from the programmer who
would otherwise become a bottleneck.
Additionally, it's a visual thing, so it's
easy to debug and understand what's going on.
For one example, I used
an animation curve
not as the source of the data,
but as a visual tool
because I had some programmatic animation going on, and
I didn't quite understand why it behaved the way it did.
So my solution for it was to, at
runtime, create an animation curve
and every frame, or every
N-number frames
insert an animation key,
key framing it
so I could visually see what was going on,
and that helped me to very quickly
go in and change that bit of
logic that was misbehaving.
Moving onto data reuse
in this example going to talk
a bit about a stealth system.
So, in many games where you have a dark environment
it's common that you have some sort of sneak mechanic where
the level of lighting you're in determines
how well an enemy character can see you.
And the way this is usually done is
by setting up these trigger volumes
for determining that at this point you're in
shadow, but at this point you're not.
This has several problems because
these basically give you two
pieces of data to update every time
you make a change to your level.
Not only do you have to change your
lighting, but also these logical triggers.
It also gives a fairly bad
user experience because when
the character is in this position, he's in
light, but when he's there, he's in dark
which is quite jarring
and strange for the user.
Actually many games ship with having an out of
sync update where they update the lighting
and they forget, in their rush to to finish the
game, they forget to update the logic triggers
and then all of a sudden you
have a lot of very angry users.
So what I've done in this case is
instead of this direct break
I have a sliding scale for how
much in shadow the character is.
Which I'm gonna show you how I do here.
The way this works is basically in Unity 3.5, I believe
we added the system of light probes.
Initially, this system was added in order to give you
something that seems like realtime lighting using baked data.
So you get them the nice realtime lighting feel using
baked global illumination without the runtime overhead.
So what I do here is basically use the same system
to get just the basic lighting information out.
Since we have full global illumination
here, I have all sorts of
directional values as well, but I found
that for this use case, actually just
getting the common
lighting is sufficient
I then take some numbers which are
fitted to this particular level.
So in this example, these are constant values, but
they should probably, in an actual use case, be
per-level defined because each level's
lighting is a bit different, and
the idea of what is shadow
and not is different.
But I basically just scale the lighting between
these two values and normalize it.
And that gives me a nice normalized value
of whether you're in shadow or not.
So just to summarize, we are
reusing existing data here
which means there's
no duplicated effort.
You change your lighting,
you rebake, and that's it.
It also means that what the user sees is
what he actually gets in terms of game logic.
So there's no disconnect for the user.
And it's high quality data unlike the the
simple trigger volumes, you can have
much more varied
gameplay where maybe
the AI has been implemented so it kind of almost
sees the character and goes closer to investigate
and then you can maybe
move further into shadow.
And it's very intuitive to maintain.
You change the light, you hit bake, you're done.
Finally, there's no runtime overhead for this.
This is using a system that's already there
it's simply sampling between
some values and interpolating
so it's extremely low-cost.
I'm gonna show you a small
example of a menu set up here.
So this is just a quick example menu
with a main menu and some level
setup, settings, and so forth.
It's not really exciting, but if we look at the
code, things start getting a bit more interesting.
So the idea here is that
once the script starts up
based on my "State enum" definition, I create
a dictionary indexed by this "State enum"
pointing to action delicate handlers.
So way this is built is basically that I used reflection
to find any function that matches the prefix "on"
the name of the state, and
the postfix "MenuGUI"
So for the default value of
"State. Main" I'll get
a dictionary index of "State. Main"
pointing to function called "OnMainMenuGUI."
This means the first
iteration of "onGUI"
I call the delegate pointed to by the dictionary
indexed by the current state being "Main"
That will invoke the
"OnMainMenuGUI" GUI handler.
Switching between different menus is simply a matter
of changing the value of the state variable
which will then either call on "LevelsMenuGUI,"
on "SettingsMenuGUI," or on "CreditsMenuGUI"
This is a very straightforward
setup easily readable.
Looking a bit on this: This is a
nice example code reuse where
we basically, very easily limit
the points of failure on this.
Either you have a mismatch between the function
name, and the enum name, or it will just work.
It's a very natural syntax.
You write the enums, you right the functions,
you can easily see what's going on.
Moving onto an example or a
self-contained WebPlayer
I'm just gonna try and do a quick live build of
it here, and see if everything breaks or not.
This is a simpler example where I
have a bit of website JavaScript which
sends a message back to my WebPlayer.
Looking a bit into how
this script is set up
I simply have a public
TextAsset variable
and on start, I call "ExternalEval" using
text content of that text asset
and I provide a JavaScript callback
method for JavaScript to call.
If we look at JavaScript code for this.
That's all the JavaScript in there.
It basically gets a reference to
the WebPlayer, sends a message to this
game object called this function
with the return value of the website
JavaScript function "prompt."
So, very straightforward and easy to understand.
If we continue here.
The nice thing about this is that you have all the
relevant code contained within that project
which means versioning becomes very straightforward.
You have no external dependencies.
Whenever you make a change to
your website JavaScript
you can vary easily couple that change set
with the relevant C# or Unity JavaScript code.
It makes for easy testing and deployment because you
just have one project to build and run, and that's it.
So, just reiterating on
rapid game development.
Last year's talk by this title,
it's available on AngryAnt.com/videos.
With this talk in baggage
this other talk will probably
be a bit more useful.
Moving on to the editor side of things,
and initially looking at importers.
My first example is about package setup.
This is for an asset store package or at bit of
code that you reuse a lot between different projects.
If you have any non-script dependencies
which aren't a texture or something,
something which is the project setup like
player settings, or whatever that might be,
this is what I'm addressing here.
As an example:
I have a custom asset which contains
some tags, layers, and input axis.
This is quite useful if you have a character
controller which requires a specific input setup
and you want to share
this between projects.
Having a bit of code which uses the serialization
system which Tim Cooper talked about earlier
to reconfigure your Unity setup to
match what this script requires.
It's a very nice solution.
As an example here, if I add another layer
to my custom asset here, I can hit import
and go to my layers, and you
can see it has been added here.
And in the same way, if I change the layer,
and go re-export it, it updates here.
This allows me to very easily
move dependencies around.
Moving onto workflow automation.
The main goal here is to eliminate
common, repetitive tasks.
At the very core of it, it'll
boost your team morale.
No one wants to do a lot
of the factory work.
And it also speeds up your iteration
time since you can produce more.
As an example here, I have an Android
plugin that I want to work with.
Basically I wrote this piece of code the
first time I wanted to do Android plugins
because my Java is not the best
and I knew I would have to go through a
lot of iterations on this Java code
and fix a lot of bugs.
Basically the current workflow for doing an
Android plugin involves a lot of command line
hand coding or hand execution.
This is a very simple test which provides
a function that'll call back to.
Unity just like the website
JavaScript we saw before.
The way that I have this compiling
I basically wanted the same kind of
workflow that I'm used to with C#
so I wrote an asset post processor.
What this allows me to do is find any file or handle
any file within the path "Assets/Plugins/Android/src"
And if the extension of that is .java,
I want to compile all my Java code.
The way I do this is basically by
using the .net process start info
to launch the built-in
system Java compiler
I parse in the Java files in my project
the reference to the
Android jar file
from the Android SDK, and the
Unity jar file, and so forth
I also create the signature needed
finally just build it into a
jar which I put in my project.
The resulting workflow is basically
that I save my Java code
which we can just quickly do here.
Create a compiler error here
I get that compiler error in my console.
And I can quickly go in and say, "Okay, this line,
go and change that," and there we go, it's compiled.
So this means I can optimize my workflow
in a way that I'm used to working with.
So moving onto a topic of bundles.
Initially, what I want to talk a bit
about is the manifest for bundles.
What I want to achieve here is, I
want to have a hands-off update approach
whenever I change something in my bundle, I
don't want to have a lot of manual steps.
And I want to have direct access
at runtime to the assets in there.
I don't want to have a lot of runtime code which searches
by name and all this stuff because that's not very
solid in the end; you'll get
a lot of errors from that.
What I have here is basically a
simple scriptable object custom asset.
And the core of this is it has a list of prefabs,
so this is a bundle manifest for prefabs.
And it just realizes this list and provides a few
accesses for adding an object and accessing it by ID.
The runtime equivalent of this.
Once I build the bundle with that generated
manifest as the main asset of the bundle
I can simply, once the bundle has been downloaded,
I can go in and
basically cast the main asset of
the bundle to my manifest type.
And once I have that, I can ask the
reference to that manifest to give me
the prefab reference based on
the ID that I already know.
So there's no searching for anything; it's just an ID
which I can store in my build process of the bundle.
Here's an example of prefab bundle use.
The goal here is still the
same natural workflow
a simple deploy build method.
And the way I've set it up here is,
I have this ".prefabBundle" folder
and my build script just goes in and finds all
prefabs in any folder called ".prefabBundle"
So this is the original prefab which
has a box collider and a cube on it.
And once my build script runs, it populates
the manifest here as we saw before,
so there's a reference to my
prefab here, and it has an ID.
What it then does is it
creates a reference prefab.
So the nice setup here is that I can continue building
my game using prefabs like I normally would
without worrying about having
to use bundles later on
I can just go build my bundles, or
go build my scenes with prefabs
put those prefabs, which I want to bundle
up, put them in a prefabBundle folder
and my build process then automatically replaces the instances
in my scene with these reference bundles or reference prefabs.
So if we exit play mode
here, you can see
initially my amazing cube here,
since it has been built
I have this bundle prefab reference
which holds the bundle ID
and the prefab ID within that bundle.
But other than that, any other information
has now been pushed to the bundle.
So this means when we load this up
you see that the cube
appears a bit later
as the bundle is loaded and instantiated
based on the data in the reference.
Here's another example of bundle use.
Normally you cannot include any
additional code in a bundle.
All your code has to be
built into the core game
and any additional assets can
then be put in an asset bundle.
However, there are several cases
where you might want to
put some code in bundles, such as if
you have an additional character
or weapon or something like this
which has some custom logic to it.
You want to continue with your familiar workflow
of having all your scripts in the same project.
Not all of them compiling to your main
project, but the same kind of workflow.
The way I've gone about
implementing this is I have
put a folder called "script bundles" in the
folder called "Assets/WebPlayer templates."
And the important thing about
this particular folder
is that for the folder WebPlayer templates,
the compiler and all importers are turned off.
The reason for this is WebPlayer templates
might contain JavaScript code
which is website JavaScript
so you of course don't want this
compiled in with your main project.
But we're taking advantage of that fact
and putting a script
bundle folder in there
and my build script then goes over
all subfolders of this folder
and taking all the scripts found in there,
and compiling them to a .net assembly
using a very similar technique to the one
you saw used for Java compiling before.
So I basically used the .net process setup to invoke the .net
compiler that was shipped with Unity, and built in assembly.
And this assembler saves it out as a text
asset by calling it "myassembly.bytes"
That extension makes Unity
import it as a text asset
but it doesn't do an text encoding on it,
so you don't lose any important binary data.
But it means I can include that
asset in an asset bundle
and then access it as a text
bundle and load it into memory.
And I can show you this in a minute.
If we go to the bundle manager...
This is the bundle manager
we took a look at before
I have a core routine
into load a type
which basically initially
loads the bundle.
And once it's available...
Once it's available, I access the main asset
for this which is the assembly that I've built.
And that's a text asset,
so I can cast it.
And accessing its .bytes property gives me
a bytes array which I can pass
into the .net assembly. Load.
From within this, I can get
the type that I'm looking for.
So if we look at the
code that uses this...
Here I ask the bundle
manager to load
the type "NewBehaviorScript" from within
the bundle called "BestScriptsEver."
And once it's done, I want this method
called "OnReceiveType" to be invoked.
This will pass me the string that I used to
search for the type, plus the type itself.
Once I have that type reference, I can simply
add it as a component to my current game object.
The result of which, you can see here.
You can see there's an
additional script here
which Unity has no information on;
There's no script name or anything
because it's a component
we have loaded at runtime.
A bit more interesting than this.
If you check in the log, there are two log
messages here: One called "We're in!"
and then one saying "From
a script bundle even."
The way this is set up is, if we look at the
code for the component I've compiled in here
you can see I have to log
messages, the two that we saw
but one is within a pre-compiler define.
So this allows you to, once you
automatically build your bundle, you can
have logic separated between
whether it's in a bundle or not.
Of course since you're just invoking the .net
compiler, you can have all sorts of additional setup.
One I suggest is, for instance, include resources
from the same folder as references on the assembly.
Okay, so just in summary.
This is, as I mentioned, a somewhat
practical counterpart from last year's talk
I hope this was
inspirational and useful.
Of course, once the Asia tour is done, all this code
and examples and all that stuff will be available.
More than that, I hope that you'll go
home and think about how you can use
data you already have and code you already have for
different purposes to optimize productivity and workflow.
Just to reiterate, this is about reuse and
re-application, and again, workflow.
That's the end of my talk. If anyone has any questions, I think I
have like a minute or two. Otherwise, I'll be around for a while.
And if need be, I'm sure we can find
someone to help translate. Thank you.
Do we have time for questions?
We have one question.
No? Well that's easy!
Oh, there's one here.
[Speaking in Japanese]
Yes. Basically, I might make subtle modifications
to this as I go through on the Asia Tour.
And I think the plan is to release slides and examples at
the same time as we release the videos of the talks
but this project is
already on GitHub
I'm just waiting for videos to be available, and
then I flip that repository online or public.
So yes, everything you see
here will be made available.
Okay, thank you for coming